<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An essay to promote virtue by example in a collection of excellent sayings (divine and moral) of devout &amp; learned men, in all ages, from the apostles time, to this present year, 1689 / By William Whitcombe, gent.</title>
            <author>Whitcombe, William.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1689</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 202 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 116 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A96335</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W1743B</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R42718</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">38875643</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 38875643</idno>
            <idno type="VID">152497</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A96335)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 152497)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2299:7)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An essay to promote virtue by example in a collection of excellent sayings (divine and moral) of devout &amp; learned men, in all ages, from the apostles time, to this present year, 1689 / By William Whitcombe, gent.</title>
                  <author>Whitcombe, William.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 236 [i.e. 218] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for the author: and are to be sold by Edw. Evets ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London:</pubPlace>
                  <date>1689.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"Licensed, March 2d. 1688/9."</note>
                  <note>Title within double line border.</note>
                  <note>Numerous errors in paging.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: William Andrews Clark Memorial Library, University of California, Los Angeles.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Maxims.</term>
               <term>Conduct of life --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:152497:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>AN ESSAY To Promote VIRTUE <hi>By Example,</hi> IN A COLLECTION OF Excellent Sayings (Divine and Moral) OF <hi>Devout</hi> &amp; <hi>Learned Men,</hi> In all Ages, from the Apoſtles Time, to this preſent Year, 1689.</p>
            <p>By <hi>William Whitcombe,</hi> Gent.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Licenſed,</hi> March 2d. 1688/9.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for the <hi>Author:</hi> And are to be Sold by <hi>Edw. Evets,</hi> at the <hi>Green Dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gon,</hi> in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s <hi>Church-yard,</hi> 1689.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="collector_to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:152497:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:152497:2"/>
            <head>TO THE CHRISTIAN READER.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>I</hi> Here preſent to thy Peruſal and Conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration theſe Serious Sayings, following; Spoken and Delivered not Raſhly, but upon the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience of whole Lives; and
<pb facs="tcp:152497:3"/>that too in thoſe moſt ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly Reflecting Moments, the Cloſe of Life, and Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach of Eternity. And moreover, not by any one Party, or Perſwaſion, or of any one Age; but of all Men, of all Perſwaſions, of all Ages: Spoken too, when they were ſo diſintereſted and diſobliged from the World, as neither to be deluded or abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed thereby; nor by any the moſt tempting Baits of Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour or Wordly Profit what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:152497:3"/>
            <p>With this Authentick ſtamp upon them, they are offered to thy Reading, and retired Thoughts; and for this Great End, That theſe Memoirs, and Reliques of the Learned and Pious in all Ages, together with what other Examples of the like Kind thy farther Converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion with Good Books, or Good Men may afford thee; may, in ſome Meaſure, excite thee, by a Zealous Imitation of their Lives, to endeavour to arrive to the Comfort and
<pb facs="tcp:152497:4"/>Peace of their Deaths; and that Eternal Glory that Crowns them. And conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering how certainly, and very ſhortly we muſt Die, as they did, thou may'ſt there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Labour to Die as happy too. The Deſign of theſe Collections, of ſo many War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning-pieces from departed Saints, being no other, than making the Dead an Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment towards the Salvation of the Living.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>W. W.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:152497:4"/>
            <head>Excellent Sayings OF DEVOUT AND Learned-Men, &amp;c.</head>
            <head type="sub">Alphabetically Digeſted.</head>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Abby-Lands.</head>
               <p>THE <hi>Pope,</hi> by a <hi>Bull,</hi> would confirm <hi>Abby-Lands;</hi> but who (ſaid <hi>Burleigh</hi>) can confirm the <hi>Pope's Bull?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In the Secret Judgment of <hi>God,</hi> it is to be Admired and Adored, in that thoſe <hi>Houſes</hi> and <hi>Abbies,</hi> that were ſo full of all Abominations, (as appeared to the <hi>Kings Commiſſioners,</hi> upon Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amination, and remains upon Record) ſo Horrible to be heard, ſo Incredible
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:152497:5"/>to be believed, that it is a Wonder <hi>God</hi> would ſuffer them unpluck'd up: So that we may ſay with <hi>Mat. Paris, Cujus foetor uſque ad Nubes fumum toter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rimum exhalabat, i. e.</hi> Whoſe filthy Stink did Breath a moſt Peſtiferous Fume, even to the Clouds of Heaven; and, with <hi>Sodom</hi>'s Sins, cryed aloud for Vengeance, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Accuſation.</head>
               <p>IF <hi>God</hi>'s People be <hi>Accuſed falſly, <hi>Chriſt</hi>
                  </hi> will <hi>Iuſtifie</hi> them: If they have Sinned, and truly Believe, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent and Amend, He will Pardon them, thro' His Meritorious Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs and Sacrifice; and will make them, and pronounce them, Juſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Adverſity.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>PRoſperity</hi> is not without many <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ears and Diſtaſtes, and <hi>Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity</hi> not without many Comforts.</p>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:152497:5"/>
               <p>The Vertue of <hi>Proſperity</hi> is <hi>Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perance,</hi> the Vertue of <hi>Adverſity</hi> is <hi>Fortitude: Proſperity</hi> doth beſt diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver <hi>Vice;</hi> but <hi>Adverſity</hi> doth beſt diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover <hi>Vertue: Proſperity</hi> is the Bleſſing of the <hi>Old Teſtament, Adverſity</hi> of the <hi>New,</hi> and the clear Manifeſtation of the favour of <hi>God.</hi> The good things of <hi>Proſperity</hi> are to be Wiſhed; the good things of <hi>Adverſity</hi> to be Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mired.</p>
               <p>My Lord <hi>Cook</hi> would ſay, <hi>That no Wiſe Man would do that in Proſperity, whereof he would Repent in Adverſity.</hi> His <hi>Motto</hi> was, <hi>Prudens qui Patiens.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Adviſes.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>EDward</hi> Earl of <hi>Rutland</hi> left theſe <hi>Four Adviſes</hi> behind Him, <hi>viz. Firſt,</hi> Be always Imploy'd: <hi>Secondly,</hi> Look to the Iſſue: <hi>Thirdly,</hi> Be Fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed with a Friend: <hi>Fourthly,</hi> Reflect on thy Self, <hi>Vita eſt in Reflectione.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:152497:6"/>
               <head>Affections.</head>
               <p>OBſerve this Rule, That we never give this <hi>Affection of Love</hi> leave to run out alone, without <hi>Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> and <hi>Conſideration</hi> going before it, and along with it: That we ſuffer not our <hi>Paſſions,</hi> which are, <hi>Love, Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred, Anger, Joy, Grief, Fear,</hi> or <hi>Hope,</hi> to deal out their own Meaſures, but our <hi>Judgment</hi> and <hi>Deliberation:</hi> That we always keep this <hi>Affection of Love,</hi> eſpecially under Diſcipline and Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, and ſuffer it not to run a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way from us, as an unruly Beaſt with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a Chain; for it is certain, the due Government of this <hi>Affection</hi> governs all the reſt. <hi>Vae Soli.</hi> If any <hi>Affection</hi> come alone, I will ask him for his Fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low: If Love to <hi>God</hi> or <hi>Good</hi> come a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone, I will ask him, Where is Hatred for Sin? If <hi>Grief,</hi> or outward <hi>Croſſes,</hi> come alone, I will ask him, Where is thy Fellow? that is, <hi>Joy in the Lord,</hi> and in <hi>Spiritual Mercies.</hi> If <hi>Fear of
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:152497:6"/>Evil</hi> come alone, I will ask, Where is thy Fellow? that is, <hi>Hope in the Lord,</hi> in his Promiſes, and in his Providences.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Afflictions.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>NIciphorus</hi> ſaith, <hi>God</hi> ſo moderates our Actions, uſing the Scourge of <hi>Affliction</hi> for our Caſtigation and Converſion; and, after due Correction, ſhews his Fatherly Affection to thoſe that Truſt in him for Salvation. <hi>Chriſt</hi> asked <hi>Peter</hi> Three times, whether he Loved him, not for his own Informa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, but that for his Threefold Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, he may help and heal his Threefold Negation.</p>
               <p>Among the many Preparations for <hi>Afflictions,</hi> patiently take this one, which includes the reſt, <hi>viz.</hi> Labour to get thy Peace made with <hi>GOD,</hi> through <hi>Jeſus CHRIST</hi> our Lord: When this is once done and attain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, thou art above the Love of the
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:152497:7"/>World, and fear of Affliction, becauſe thou haſt an Aſſurance of a greater than this World can give, or take a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way; a Kingdom, <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.2, 9. an Hope, an Expectation, that is above the reach and Region of Affliction; and renders the greateſt and ſoreſt Afflictions as they are; namely, Light and Momentany: And yet, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, becauſe thou art in this glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Expectation, yet but in this low<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er Region, and ſo ſubject to Paſſions, Perturbations, and Fears. The Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciful <hi>God</hi> hath engaged his Promiſe to ſupport thee under them, to Better and Improve thee by them, and carry thee thro' them by his All-ſufficient Grace and Mercy, 119. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 74. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.13. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.17.</p>
               <p>Chriſtians, under your greateſt Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions lies your greateſt Treaſure: Afflictions are Good, but not Pleaſant; Sin is Pleaſant, but not Good; there's more Evil in a Drop of Corruption, than in a Sea of Afflictions: <hi>God</hi> ſepe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rates
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:152497:7"/>the Sin he Hates ſo deadly, from the Soul He Loves ſo dearly. By the greateſt Afflictions, <hi>God</hi> Teacheth us the ſweeteſt Inſtruction.</p>
               <p>A Believer, when he lies under the Hand that doth <hi>Afflict</hi> him, he lies in the Heart that doth <hi>Affect</hi> him. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers are Crucified by the World, that they may not be Crucified in the World. The Fleſh is an Enemy to Sufferings, becauſe Sufferings is an Enemy to the Fleſh: It may make a Man an Earthly Courtier, but it will never make a Man an Heavenly Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyr. They that carry not the Yoke of <hi>Chriſt</hi> on their Neck, will never carry the Croſs of <hi>Chriſt</hi> on their Backs: but the Believer Studies more how to A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dorn the Croſs, than how to avoid the Croſs: None ſo Couragious as thoſe that are Religious. A Believer never falls aſleep for Jeſus, till he falls aſleep in Jeſus. Some Glory in that which is their Shame, and ſhall we be aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med of that which is our Glory. It's
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:152497:8"/>an Honor to be Diſhonored for <hi>Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> Tell me, Believer, Is not <hi>Chriſt</hi>'s Croſs better than the Worlds Crown. Fiery Tryals make Golden Chriſtians; Sin hath brought many a Believer into Sufferings, and Suffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings hath kept many a Believer out of Sin, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 39.9.119.71.61.67. we always expecting ſome trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble or other to interrupt our outward Peace and Reſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Non prodeſt Medicamentum dum ferrum in vu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nere,</hi> Until Sin, which is the Cauſe, be removed, the Effect, which is Trouble, Afflictions, will not ceaſe.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Neopolitans</hi> are wont to ſay, <hi>They had nothing to trouble them, but than they are troubled at nothing.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The vigorous perpetuating of the remembrance of our Afflictions and Deliverances, will be an effectual means to perpetuate the due Fruit of them in their Life, Vigor, and Inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:152497:8"/>
               <p>A Worthy Divine, lying on his Death-Bed, being asked whether his Pains were great, he anſwered, <hi>That he did not eſteem that a Pain which would be to him the end of all Troubles, and the beginning of Eternal Joys.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Saint <hi>Auſtin</hi> ſaith, <hi>Not to be without, but to Overcome Afflictions, is Bleſſedneſs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Saunders,</hi> the Martyr, being in Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, Writ to his Wife, <hi>That Riches have I none to endow thee with, but that Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of taſting how ſweet</hi> Chriſt <hi>is to hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry Conſciences (whereof I do feel part) that I Bequeath to Thee, and the reſt of my Beloved of</hi> Chriſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Fini rerum Caput,</hi> as one Wittily ſaid, <hi>Begin therefore at the End, judge nothing, but hope well, till thou ſeeſt the Concluſion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>One was wont to ſay, <hi>He was not always Merry that Laughed.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Afflictions undo many Pleaſures more.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:152497:9"/>
               <head>Alms.</head>
               <p>SAint <hi>Cyprian</hi> ſaith, <hi>Let not that Sleep in thy Treaſury that may be profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table to the Poor.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>He ſaith likewiſe, <hi>That which we muſt neceſſarily part withal, it's Wiſdom for us to diſtribute, ſo that</hi> God <hi>may ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſtingly Reward us.</hi> And alſo, <hi>He that gives an Alms to the Poor, offers a ſweet ſmelling Sacrifice to God.</hi> Vide <hi>Charity.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Works of <hi>Charity</hi> do good, both to him that Relieveth, and him that is Relieved; but he that doth Good, gets more Relief by it than he to whom it is done, <hi>For it is better to Give than Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive,</hi> Acts 20.35. Giving Charitably is a caſting of Seed, bringing an ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting Harveſt: It's a ſending up ſweet Vapours into Heaven, which are thick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned there into a Rain of Bleſſings. <hi>Vid.</hi> Charity.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:152497:9"/>
               <head>To Attribute too much to Ones Self.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>G<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſtavus Adolphus,</hi> three days be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his Death, ſaid, <hi>Our Affairs anſwer our Deſires, but I doubt</hi> God <hi>will Puniſh me for the folly of my People, who</hi> Attribute <hi>too much to me, and eſteem me as it were their God; and therefore he will make them ſhortly know, and ſee that I am but a Man: I ſubmit to his Will, and I know he will not leave this great Enterpriſe of mine Imperfect:</hi> And ſoon after was Slain, yet with Victory over his Enemies.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>An Apology for the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans by</hi> Juſtin Martyr.</head>
               <p>IN his Firſt <hi>Apology,</hi> he defended the <hi>Chriſtians</hi> againſt the Senate of <hi>Rome,</hi> and purged them from thoſe
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:152497:10"/>Crimes which were falſly charged a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them by the <hi>Ethnicks.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Second to <hi>Antonius</hi> the Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſopher, (amongſt many other things) he ſaith, <hi>Other Men that are Appeached in Judgment, are not Condemned till they be Convicted; but for us, you take the very Name for a ſufficient Crime; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as you ought to ſee Juſtice done rather on your Accuſers: So that if a Chriſtian that is Accuſed, deny his Name, him you Releaſe, not being able to charge him with any other Offence; but if he ſtand to his Name, you Condemn him: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as it were your Duty rather to Examine their manner of Life, and ſo according to their Demerits, to ſee Juſtice done upon them.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Ambition.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>BErnard</hi> ſays, <hi>It is a gilded Miſery, a ſecret Poyſon, an hidden Plague, the Engineer of Deceit, the Mother of
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:152497:10"/>Hypocriſie, the Parent of Envy, the Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginal of Vices, the Moath of Holineſs, the blinder of Hearts, turning Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cines into Maladies, and Remedies into Diſeaſes.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Anger Sinful.</head>
               <p>TO keep thy Heart patient under Provocations to <hi>Anger, <hi>Firſt,</hi>
                  </hi> againſt Humble and Low Thoughts of thy ſelf; and then thou wilt have a Meek Spirit, and Peaceable Deport<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment towards others. <hi>Secondly,</hi> Be often Sweetning thy Spirits with <hi>God,</hi> and they will not be eaſily Imbittered with <hi>Wrath</hi> towards Man. <hi>Thirdly,</hi> Get due Apprehenſions of the Evil Nature, and Effects of <hi>Sinful Anger,</hi> as that <hi>Anger</hi> is a ſhort Madneſs; <hi>Anger</hi> is the Fever of the Soul, the Eclipſe of Reaſon, <hi>&amp;c. Fourthly,</hi> Conſider how ſweet a thing it is for Chriſtians to Conquer their Corruptions, and to
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:152497:11"/>carry away the Spoyl of them, <hi>Prov.</hi> 16.32.</p>
               <p>Shame your ſelves by ſetting be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you thoſe moſt eminent Patterns for Meekneſs; <hi>Learn of me,</hi> ſays Chriſt, <hi>for I am Meek and Lowly in Spirit,</hi> Mat. 11.29. and <hi>Moſes, Num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers,</hi> 12.3.</p>
               <p>Conſider more helps againſt it, <hi>Firſt,</hi> By conſidering our own Failings, eſpecially in reference to Almighty <hi>God,</hi> and our Duty to him, <hi>&amp;c. Secondly,</hi> By conſidering the unreaſonableneſs of that Diſtemper in reſpect of our ſelves; It puts thee into Perturbations, it gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifies thy Adverſary, <hi>&amp;c. Thirdly,</hi> Is in reſpect of others, even of the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons provoking; It may be they are Inſtruments permitted by <hi>God,</hi> either to Correct or Try thee, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Expedients againſt it, even when oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion is offered. <hi>Firſt,</hi> Take this peremptory Reſolution and Practiſe, <hi>viz.</hi> I will not be Angry tho' an occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion be offered. <hi>Secondly,</hi> Take this
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:152497:11"/>Reſolution, never to give thy ſelf leave to be <hi>Angry,</hi> till thou ſee any ſuch thing is done or no, <hi>&amp;c. Thirdly,</hi> In caſe of Provocation to <hi>Anger</hi> by Words, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider this, that nothing ſo much grati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies an Ill-Tongue, as when it finds an <hi>Angry</hi> hearer; and nothing ſo much diſappoints and vexeth it, than Calm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and Undiſturbedneſs: It is the moſt innocent and exquiſite Revenge in the World, to return gentle Words, or none at all to Ill-Language: But, on the other ſide, <hi>Anger</hi> and <hi>Perturba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> do not only produce what thy Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſary deſires, but alſo puts Diſcom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſedneſs and Impotency upon thee, that thou becomeſt unable to keep ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, or to ſpeak with that Reaſon or Advantage thou ſhould'ſt. <hi>J. Hale.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Give diligent Ear unto <hi>CHRIST</hi>'s Words, and thou ſhalt little regard Ten Thouſand Words ſpoken by Men. <hi>De Kempis.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>I ſtrive with my own Spirit,</hi> ſays De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour Mr. <hi>Corbet, to ſubdue it to the
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:152497:12"/>Will of</hi> God, <hi>and in whatſoever I am tempted to be Impatient, therein I labor moſt for Patience. My great Care,</hi> ſays he, <hi>is that I may not Sin againſt my</hi> God, <hi>in any kind; and more eſpecially that I may not Sin by a Rebellious Impa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiency, under his Correcting Hand.</hi> Ibid.</p>
               <p>Anger <hi>doth languiſh by Suppreſſion, but flows higher by Expreſſion.</hi> Beda.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Atheiſm.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>THe Fool hath ſaid in his Heart, There is no GOD,</hi> It is not ſaid, <hi>The Fool hath thought in his Heart there is no GOD:</hi> So that he rather ſaith it by Wrote to himſelf, as that he would have, than that he can throughly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve it.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The great Atheiſts indeed, are the Hypocrites, who are ever holding Holy things without feeling.</hi> Bacon.</p>
               <p>If <hi>Atheiſts</hi> ſay, The World or its Materials were Made, they muſt grant
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:152497:12"/>a <hi>GOD</hi> that made it? If they ſay, They were not Made, they then aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſert an Eternal Being of it ſelf; that is, they allow the Difficulties for which they pretend to deny a <hi>GOD.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Cares.</head>
               <p>WHen Men Believe weakly, and Love <hi>GOD</hi> but little, they can ſcarce find whether they Believe or Love at all; and therefore remain in doubt. To Remedy which, follow your Duty till Grace be encreaſed, ply your Work, wait upon <hi>God</hi> in the uſe of his preſcribed Means, and he will undoubtedly bleſs you with Increaſe and ſtrength of Grace. If you would lay out thoſe ſerious Affections in Praying and Seeking unto <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and for more Grace, you would, in time, Believe ſtrongly, and Love fervently; and thereby put it out of doubt, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther you Believe or Love or not. <hi>Mrs.</hi> B.</p>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:152497:13"/>
               <p>If by moderate and due Care we would reſign up our Selves and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernments into the Hands of <hi>God,</hi> He would charge himſelf with us; but if we will Immoderately <hi>Care,</hi> and be ſo peremptory in our <hi>Deſigns,</hi> and will not ſubmit them to him, then <hi>God</hi> is diſcharged, and we muſt look to our ſelves.</p>
               <p>You need not fetch the Miſery of another Day and put to this; it hath enough for its own.</p>
               <p>Let them conſider, that fear Want, that they want nothing ſo much as Faith: A little more truſting in <hi>God,</hi> and a little leſs ſinful Foreſight and needleſs Care, would do well.</p>
               <p>Our daily Defects and Diſappoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments procure <hi>Miſery</hi> and <hi>Vexations.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>He that would make Earth ſure, muſt firſt of all make Heaven ſure: Shall I, by taking thought what I ſhall Eat, and what I ſhall Drink here, never fear Wanting or Begging a drop of Water hereafter? Shall I be Solicitous
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:152497:13"/>for Cloaths, and do not know but my Soul and Body may lie naked in the ſcorching Flames of the Wrath of <hi>God</hi> to all Eternity? Beſides that, I have a Promiſe of <hi>God</hi> for outward things, if I make it my buſineſs to look after Heavenly; Its a very needleſs <hi>Care: God</hi> provides Meat for me, that I may not be taken off my Work to ſeek thoſe things that are Heavenly, <hi>Mat.</hi> 6.33.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Chriſt Crucified; the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of it.</head>
               <p>IT is a kind of <hi>Catholicon</hi> of univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal Uſe and Conveniency, in refe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence to this Life. Am I in Want, in Priſon, in Contempt, in Baniſhment, in Sickneſs, in Death? this <hi>Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge</hi> gives Contentedneſs, Patience, Chearfulneſs, Reſignation of my ſelf to his Will, who hath Sealed my Peace with him, and Favor from him, in the great Covenant of his Son: I could
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:152497:14"/>live upon this, tho' I were ready to Starve, when I am aſſured that it is for my Good, and the glory of his Name, I ſhall be delivered; if not, I can be contented if my Jewel, the Peace of <hi>God</hi> and my own <hi>Conſcience,</hi> by the Blood of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> be ſafe, if not in Wealth, Honor, greatneſs in Eſteem in the World. This <hi>Knowledge</hi> teacheth me Humility, as knowing of whom I have received it: Fidelity, as know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to whom I muſt account for it; and in all, it teacheth me not to over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>value it, nor to value my Self the more by it or for it: It makes Death not Terrible, becauſe a moſt ſure Paſſage to Eternal Life. Here I find a way to get my Sins Pardoned; whereas, all the World, without this, cannot con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trive a Satisfaction for me: I find ſuch a Way to obtain ſuch a Righteouſneſs as is valuable with <hi>God,</hi> and perfect before Him, even the Righteouſneſs of <hi>God</hi> in <hi>Chriſt;</hi> and here I find the means, the only means, to avoid the
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:152497:14"/>Wrath to come, the Terror of the Judgment of the Laſt-Day. Ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting Life to all Eternity, which the bleſſed <hi>God,</hi> and the Lord <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> all the bleſſed Angels, and the Spirits of Juſt Men made perfect.</p>
               <p>The knowledge of <hi>Chriſt</hi> above all other <hi>Knowledge,</hi> and <hi>Chriſt</hi> Crucified above all other <hi>Knowledge</hi> of <hi>Chriſt;</hi> being the higheſt manifeſtation of his Love. <hi>J. Hale.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>With all my Heart</hi> (ſaith <hi>Calvin</hi>) <hi>I embrace the Mercy of</hi> God, <hi>which he hath uſed towards me, for</hi> Jeſus Chriſt's <hi>ſake, recompencing my Faults with the Merits of his Death and Paſſion, that ſatisfaction being made, by this means, for all my Sins and Crimes, and the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance of them may be blotted out. I witneſs alſo, and profeſs, that I humbly beg of him, that being waſhed and clean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in the Blood of that higheſt Redeemer, ſhed for the Sins of Mankind, I may ſtand at his Judgments-Seat, under the Image of my Redeemer.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:152497:15"/>
               <p>Had <hi>Chriſt</hi> been <hi>God</hi> only, he could not have Suffered; had he been Man only, he could not have Merited. <hi>Chriſt</hi>'s Blood was ſhed as well for Oblution, as for Abſolution.</p>
               <p>Diffidence of ones Self and Depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of <hi>Chriſt</hi> is the Motto of a Chriſtian.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Counſel.</head>
               <p>THe greateſt Truſt between Man and Man, is the Truſt of giving <hi>Counſel. <hi>For in our Confidences</hi>
                  </hi> (ſaith our Lord <hi>Bacon</hi>) <hi>Men commit the parts of Life, their Lands, their Goods, their Children, their Credit, and ſome parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Affairs; but to ſuch as they make their Counſellors, they commit the whole, by how much the more they are obliged to Faithfulneſs and Integrity.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>There is no ſuch <hi>Flattery</hi> as of a Mans ſelf; and there is no ſuch Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy againſt that <hi>Flattery,</hi> as the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:152497:15"/>of a Friend: <hi>Counſel</hi> is of Two ſorts, The one concerning <hi>Manners,</hi> the other concerning <hi>Buſineſs:</hi> For the firſt, The beſt Preparative to keep the Mind in Health, is the faithful Admonition of a Friend: The calling of a Man's ſelf to a ſtrict Account, is ſometimes too piercing and corroding. Reading good Books of Morality is a little Flat and Dead. Obſerving our Faults in others, is ſometimes impro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per for our Caſe; but the beſt Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceipt (beſt, I ſay, to work, and beſt to take) is the Admonition of a Friend.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Conviction.</head>
               <p>IF you be troubled for <hi>Sin,</hi> obſerve whether your trouble for it be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward as well as outward, and reaches not only to open Sins, but to ſecret Luſts; to Inward and Spiritual Sins, ſuch as <hi>Hypocriſie, Formality, Luke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warmneſs, Deadneſs</hi> and <hi>Hardneſs of
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:152497:16"/>Heart;</hi> and if ſo, this is a ſure ſign of the Work of the Spirit, becauſe the Trouble occaſioned by theſe Sins, bears a more immediate Relation to the Holineſs of <hi>God,</hi> who only is offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by them; they being ſuch that none elſe can ſee or know.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Covetouſneſs.</head>
               <p>HE that is <hi>Covetous</hi> when he is Old, is as a Thief that Steals when he is going to the Gallows.</p>
               <p>Bags of Gold to us when Saints, will be but as a Bag of Pebbles, when Men.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Alexander</hi> of <hi>Hales,</hi> ſays, <hi>That Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vetouſneſs deſerves the Hate of all, for theſe Reaſons:</hi> Firſt, <hi>It is a Sin againſt Nature, making the Soul Terreſtrial, which ſhould be Heavenly.</hi> Secondly, <hi>For the many Curſes againſt it in the Scripture;</hi> Wo to them that joyn Houſe to Houſe, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Thirdly, <hi>For
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:152497:16"/>the many Evils it ſubjects them unto: It is the Root of all Evil.</hi> Fourthly, <hi>It makes a Man a Fool;</hi> O Fool this Night, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Fifthly, <hi>It canſes Strifes, from whom are Strifes.</hi> Sixthly, <hi>It brings Men into Snares, which drown Men in Perdition.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Fulgentius</hi> uſed to ſay, <hi>CHRIST Died for Men and Angels; for Men, that they may riſe from Sin; and for Angels, that they may not fall into Sin. And if they go to Hell that do not Feed the Hungry, Cloath the Naked,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>If want of Charity be Tormented in Hell, what will become of the Covetous.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Tertullian</hi> ſaith, <hi>Gold to many Men, is much better than their Faith and Honeſty; And the Love of it makes many ſo Covetous, as if they were to Live here for ever.</hi> Avarice is not the Vice of Gold, but of Men that uſe it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:152497:17"/>
               <head>Conſcience.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>THe Two main Principles that guide Human Nature</hi> (ſaith Judge <hi>Dod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deridge) are <hi>Conſcience</hi> and <hi>Law;</hi> by the former we are obliged, in refe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence to another World; by the latter, in reference to This.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>St. <hi>Ambroſe</hi> was wont to ſay, <hi>A clear</hi> Conſcience <hi>ſhould not regard ſlan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derous Speeches; nor think, that they have more Power to Condemn him, than his own</hi> Conſcience <hi>hath to clear him.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Aquinas</hi> was wont to ſay, <hi>That Day will come, when Fair-Dealing will be found a Jewel; when a good</hi> Conſcience <hi>ſhall be better than a good</hi> Purſe; <hi>when the Judge will not be put off with fair Speeches, nor drawn aſide with hopes of Reward.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Iſidore</hi> ſaith, <hi>All things may be ſhun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed but a Man's own Heart; a Man cannot run from himſelf; a guilty</hi> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience <hi>will not leave him whereſoever he goes.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:152497:17"/>
               <q>
                  <p>It is very dangerous to quiet <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience</hi> with any thing but the Blood of <hi>Chriſt:</hi> It's bad being at Peace till <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſpeaks Peace: Nothing can truly ſatisfie <hi>Conſcience,</hi> leſs than that which pacifies <hi>God;</hi> and that is, the Blood of the Lord Jeſus <hi>Chriſt.</hi>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi> Mead.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                  </p>
                  <p>Whoſo will keep the Peace of his <hi>Conſcience,</hi> and his Confidence in <hi>God,</hi> muſt carefully keep himſelf from all thoſe things that diſpleaſe his Holy Eyes, and turn away his Gracious Countenance; leſt that when need of our Duty calls us to draw near him by Prayer, we feel our ſelves pulled back by Guilty Fears. <bibl>
                        <hi>Du Moulin.</hi> 63.</bibl>
                  </p>
               </q>
               <p>The Glory of a good Man, is the Teſtimony of a good <hi>Conſcience.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A good <hi>Conſcience</hi> is able to bear very much, and is chearful in Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſities. To walk inwardly with <hi>God,</hi> and not to be poſſeſſed with any out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Affection, is the State of a Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual Man.</p>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:152497:18"/>
               <p>Have a good <hi>Conſcience,</hi> and thou ſhalt ever have Joy.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Charity.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>CHriſologus</hi> ſaith, <hi>Let not thy Care be to have thy Hands full, when the Poors are empty; for the only way to have full Barns, is to have Charitable Hands.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>St. <hi>Ambroſe</hi> ſaith, <hi>It is not ſo much to be enquired, how much thou Giveſt, as with what Heart. It is not Liberality, when thou takeſt by Oppreſſion from one, and giveſt to another.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>St. <hi>Cyril</hi> ſaith, <hi>It is the beſt way for a Rich Man, to make the Bellies of the Poor his Barn; to ſuccor the Fatherleſs and Naked, and thereby to lay up Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure in Heaven, that he may be received into the Heavenly and everlaſting Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitations.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:152497:18"/>
               <head>Chaſtity.</head>
               <p>A Woman is truly <hi>Chaſt</hi> that hath Liberty and Opportunity to Sin, and doth not.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Commands.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>GOD</hi> comes to us, not a Naked <hi>GOD,</hi> but Cloathed with His <hi>Commands;</hi> and if we Love Him, we muſt receive Him ſo Cloathed.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>GOD</hi> hears our <hi>Prayers</hi> according as we keep his <hi>Commands.</hi> Whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever <hi>God</hi> forbids in the Act, he for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bids likewiſe in the Thoughts.</p>
               <p>
                  <q>If <hi>Chriſt</hi> be not our King to Rule and Govern us, he will neither be our Prophet to Fore-warn, nor our Prieſt to Expiate: If <hi>Chriſt</hi> hath freed us from the Damnation of Sin, he hath alſo freed us from the Dominion of Sin. If, with his Blood,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:152497:19"/>he hath quenched the Fire of Hell for us, he hath alſo quenched the Fire of Luſt in us. <hi>Chriſt</hi>'s Juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying Blood is given by his Sancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying Spirit. <bibl>
                        <hi>Touchſtone of a Chriſtian.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                  </q>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Converſion.</head>
               <p>LAbor after, and Pray for a through <hi>Converſion;</hi> beg of <hi>GOD</hi> that he would make a ſaving <hi>Change</hi> in your Souls, that you may be altogether Chriſtians; all other <hi>Changes,</hi> below this ſaving <hi>Change,</hi> this Heart change make us but almoſt Chriſtians.</p>
               <p>Morality and Civility may com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend us to Men, but not to <hi>God,</hi> they are of no moment or value to the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curement of Eternal Salvation. The ſober Man, not being renewed through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out by the Spirit of <hi>God,</hi> ſhall as ſurely go to <hi>Hell</hi> as the beaſtly Drunkard.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:152497:19"/>
               <head>Corruptions.</head>
               <p>
                  <q>WHilſt Grace is Imperfect, <hi>Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions</hi> will be ſtrong. The great <hi>Corruptions</hi> that the Godly find in themſelves, keep them from being Proud, and deſpiſing of others. <bibl>
                        <hi>Hilderſam.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                  </q>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Cuſtom.</head>
               <p>THe <hi>Halſion Days</hi> of the Goſpel pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voke Hypocriſie, but the Suffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings for Religion prove Sincerity. He that is a Profeſſor of Religion, meerly for <hi>Cuſtom,</hi> when it Proſpers, will never be a Martyr for <hi>Chriſt</hi>'s ſake, when it Suffers.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Covenant the Second.</head>
               <p>THe Son of <hi>GOD</hi> came to make known unto us the Will of his Father; in performance of which, we
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:152497:20"/>ſhall be ſure to be Accepted and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warded by Him: And this was one great part of his Buſineſs, which He performed in thoſe many Sermons and Precepts we find ſet down in the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel; and herein He is our Prophet, it being the Work of a Prophet of Old, not only to Foretel, but to Teach. Our Duty, in this particular, is to hearken diligently to Him, to be moſt ready and deſirous to learn that <hi>Will of God</hi> which He came from <hi>Heaven</hi> to Reveal to us. The ſecond Thing He was to do for us, was, To ſatisfie <hi>GOD</hi> for our Sins; not only that <hi>One</hi> of <hi>Adam,</hi> but all the Sins of Mankind, that truly Repent and Amend, and by this means to obtain Forgiveneſs of Sins, and the Favour of <hi>God;</hi> and ſo to Redeem us from <hi>Hell,</hi> and Eternal Damnation, which was the Puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment due to our Sins: All this He did for us, by his Death; He offered up Himſelf a Sacrifice for the Sins of all thoſe who heartily bewail and forſake
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:152497:20"/>them; and in this He is our Prieſt, it being the Prieſts Office to Sacrifice for the Sins of the People. Our Duty in this particular is truly and heartily to Repent, and forſake our Sins, without which, they will never be Pardoned us, altho' <hi>Chriſt</hi> hath Died. <hi>Secondly,</hi> Stedfaſtly to Believe, if we do that, we ſhall have the Comforts of this <hi>Sacrifice</hi> of His; all our Sins, how great, or how many ſoever, ſhall be Pardoned, and we ſaved from thoſe Eternal Puniſhments which were due to us for them. And for that other part, <hi>viz.</hi> That of Praying, that he not only performed on Earth, but conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nues ſtill to do it in Heaven: He ſits on the Right-Hand of <hi>God,</hi> and makes Requeſts for us. <hi>Rev.</hi> 8.34. Our Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty herein, is not to reſiſt this unſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Bleſſing of His, but to be willing to be thus Bleſt, in being turned from our Sins; and not to make void and fruitleſs all his Prayers and Interceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons for us, which will never prevail
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:152497:21"/>for us, whilſt we continue in them. The third thing that <hi>Chriſt</hi> was to do for us, was, To enable us, or give us ſtrength to do what <hi>God</hi> requires of us: This He doth, <hi>Firſt,</hi> by taking off from the hardneſs of the Law given to <hi>Adam,</hi> (which was, <hi>Never to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit the leaſt Sin upon pain of Damnation</hi>) and requiring of us only, an honeſt and hearty Endeavor to do what we are able; and where we fail, accept<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of ſincere Repentance. <hi>Secondly,</hi> By ſending his Holy Spirit into our Hearts, to Rule and Govern us; to give us ſtrength to overcome Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptations to Sin; and to do all that He requires of us: And in this He is our King, to Govern, Rule, and Subdue our Enemies. Our Duty in this par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular, is, To give up our ſelves Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient Subjects of His, to be Governed and Ruled by Him; to Obey all his Laws; not to take part with any Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bel; that is, not to cherriſh any One Sin, but diligently to Pray for his
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:152497:21"/>Grace to enable us to Subdue them all, and then carefully to make uſe of it to that purpoſe. <hi>Laſtly,</hi> He hath purchaſed, for all that faithfully Obey Him, and Eternal and Glorious Inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance in the Kingdom of <hi>Heaven,</hi> whither He is gone before to take Poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion for us. Our Duty herein, is, <hi>Firſt,</hi> To be exceeding careful, that we forfeit not our Parts, which we ſhall certainly do, if we continue Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penitent in any Sin. <hi>Secondly,</hi> Not to faſten our Affections on this World, but to raiſe them, according to the Precept of the Apoſtle, <hi>Col.</hi> 3.2. <hi>Set your Affections on things above, and not on things below;</hi> longing to come to the Poſſeſſion of that Inheritance of ours; in compariſon of which, all things here below ſhould ſeem Vile and Mean. <hi>Whole Duty of Man.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>
                     <hi>Chriſt</hi> indeed hath freed us from the Impoſſibilities of the <hi>Covenant</hi> of Works, and from the Burthen and Yoke of the Legal Ceremonies, but
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:152497:22"/>not from the Difficulties and Pains of Goſpel Duties. <bibl>
                        <hi>Baxter</hi>'s <hi>Reſt.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                  </q>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Comforts.</head>
               <p>
                  <q>FEtch thy <hi>Comforts</hi> from Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, and not from Pleaſures or Hopes here below. <bibl>
                        <hi>De Kempis.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>What profit can it be for thee to bewail that Sin which thou wilt not forſake? What Reward canſt thou expect for that Obedience which ſo ſoon fainteth? What <hi>Comfort</hi> in that Joy that is but Temporary?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>How truly ſweet</hi> (ſays St. <hi>Auſtin) is the loſs of thoſe Earthly Sweetneſſes thoſe Tranſitory Joys, which I was for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly afraid to loſe, and rejoyce now to Baniſh: It is Thou, O Lord, who ar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> entred in, who art ſweeter than a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> Sweetneſs,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <q>As thou haſt raiſed me by thy Power, ſo Rule me by thy Providence that thy Grace may be far ſweete<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="37" facs="tcp:152497:22"/>with my Sufferings, than my Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures with my Sins. <bibl>
                        <hi>Mr.</hi> Corbet.</bibl>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>When I walk in Darkneſs, and ſee no Light in outward <hi>Comforts,</hi> Human Helps, and viſible Means, I will Truſt in the Name of the Lord, and ſtay my ſelf upon my <hi>GOD.</hi>
                  </q> Ibid.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Contentation.</head>
               <p>
                  <q>BE not troubled if this Man lives in Tranquility, and thou in Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulation, <hi>God</hi> will have it ſo: He puts thee in the Combat; thou therefore muſt Sweat before thou comeſt off with Victory, whereas he that comes forward in the World, goes back in Grace. His Eſtate is miſerable that goes Laughing to Deſtruction; As the Fool in the Stocks for Correction. <bibl>
                        <hi>Theophilact.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>He that ſets his entireſt Love on <hi>God,</hi> yet hath Liberty to Iſſue a Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinate
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:152497:23"/>Portion of Love to other good things; as, Health, Peace, opportunity to do Good, Wife, Children, Friends, and in theſe he may be croſſed and diſappointed; but the predominant Love of <hi>God,</hi> delivers the Soul from Diſcontent and Impatience, even un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der theſe Loſſes; becauſe the Soul is ſtill aſſured of what it moſt values; the Love of <hi>God</hi> returned to the Soul, which compenſates and drowns thoſe other Loſſes, and the Diſcontent that may ariſe upon it.</p>
               <p>Trouble makes every ſad Accident a double Evil, Contentedneſs none at all.</p>
               <p>When we loſe our Eſtates, let's not loſe our Conſtancy and Chearfulneſs. If thou haſt loſt thy Health, do not loſe thy Patience alſo. If thou Die a little ſooner than thou expected'ſt, do not Die unwillingly. If thou have no Friend, be not alſo thy own Enemy. If others Vex thee, do not withal Vex thy ſelf. If thou be Ill to Day, be
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:152497:23"/>not ſolicitous for to Morrow, ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent to the Day, is the Evil thereof.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Deſpair.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>FRancis Spira,</hi> about the Year, 1548. ſaith this of himſelf: <hi>I was exceſſively Covetous of Money, and accordingly I applyed my ſelf to get it by Injuſtice, Corrupt Judgment, Deceit, Inventing Tricks to delude Juſtice; Good Cauſes I either defended Deceit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully, or Sold them the Adverſaries per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidiouſly. Ill Cauſes I maintained with all my Might. I willingly oppoſed the known Truth and Truſt committed to me, either Betrayed or Perverted: And for the Inordinate Love of the things of this World, I wholly Wounded my Conſcience by an Infamous Abjuration of the Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Truth, which I formerly Profeſſed, upon the ſerious Conſideration of what I had done in cold Blood, acknowledging my ſelf utterly undone for ever.</hi> This
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:152497:24"/>poor Man became a Spectacle of ſuch Spiritual Miſery and Woe to the whole World, that there is not any thing left to the Memory of Man more Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markable: his Spirit was ſuddenly ſmitten with the dreadful Sence of Divine Wrath for his Apoſtacy, and ſplitting in pieces (as it were by ſo grievous a bruiſe) his Heart fainted fearfully, and failed him quite, and fell aſunder in his Breaſt, like drops of Water: Hear ſome ruful Expreſſions (out of his Deſperate State) from his own Mouth: <hi>O that I were gone from hence; that ſomebody would let out this weary Soul of mine: I tell you, there was never ſuch a Monſter as I am; ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver was there a Man alive ſuch a Spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctacle of exceeding Miſery. I now feel</hi> God<hi>'s heavy Wrath, that burneth like the Torments of Hell within me, and afflicts my Soul with Pains unutterable. Verily,</hi> Deſperation <hi>is Hell it ſelf, the gnawing Worm of unquenchable Fire, Horror, Confuſion; and which is worſt of
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:152497:24"/>all,</hi> Deſparation <hi>continually Tormenting me: And now I count my preſent State worſe, than if my Soul were ſeparated from my Body with</hi> Judas: <hi>The Truth of it is, never had Mortal Man ſuch ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience of</hi> God<hi>'s Wrath and Hatred againſt him as I have: The Damned in Hell, I think, endure not the like Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery. If I could conceive the leaſt ſpark of Hope in my Heart of a better State hereafter, I would not refuſe to endure the moſt heavy Wrath of the great</hi> God, <hi>yea, for Two Thouſand Years, ſo that at length I could get out of Miſery. O that</hi> God <hi>would looſe his Hand from me; and that it were with me as in times paſt, I would ſcorn the Threats of moſt Wicked Tyrants, bear Torments with In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vincible Reſolution and Glory in the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Profeſſion of</hi> Chriſt, <hi>till I were choaked with the Flame, and my Body turned into Aſhes.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="42" facs="tcp:152497:25"/>
               <head>Diſcreſſion.</head>
               <p>
                  <q>IT's more <hi>Diſcreſſion</hi> to hold the Stile of Miſerable, which begets an Infamy without Hatred, than to deſire that of Liberal, which being maintained by neceſſitous Courſes, procures an Infamy with Hatred. <bibl>
                        <hi>Machiavil.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                  </q>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Death.</head>
               <p>
                  <q>THe Young-Man hath <hi>Death</hi> at his Back, the Old-Man before his Eyes. That's the more dangerous Enemy that Purſues thee, than that which Marches before thy Face. <bibl>
                        <hi>Aquinas.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>Set <hi>Death</hi> into your Minds, and it will put Life into your Actions.</p>
               <p>St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> ſaith, <hi>There's nothing more abateth Sin, than the frequent Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditation of</hi> Death. <hi>He cannot Die Ill
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:152497:25"/>that Lived Well; and ſeldom doth he Die Well, that Lived Ill.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ambroſe</hi> ſaith, <hi>Death is the Burial of all Vices.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To be willing to Die, conſider the harmleſneſs of <hi>Death</hi> to the People of <hi>God,</hi> tho' it keeps its Dart, yet it hath loſt its Sting.</p>
               <p>Thy Heart may be kept from ſhrinking back, in time of Sickneſs, by conſidering the neceſſity of <hi>Death,</hi> in order to the Fruition of <hi>God,</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.6. <hi>Whilſt we are at home in the Body, we are abſent from the Lord.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Another Argument to this unwil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingneſs to Die, is, <q>The immediate Succeſſion of a more excellent, and a more glorious Life; it is but Wink, and you ſhall ſee <hi>God, Rom.</hi> 8.10, 11. At <hi>Death</hi> you will be freed from Trouble here, and have Communion with <hi>God,</hi> and Communion of Saints. <bibl>
                        <hi>Flavel.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>Cardinal <hi>Richleu,</hi> being Tempted to doubt and disbelieve a <hi>God,</hi> another
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:152497:26"/>World, and the Immortality of the Soul; and by that Diſtruſt, to relieve his aking Heart, but in vain, <hi>So ſtrong,</hi> he ſaid, <hi>was the Notion of</hi> God <hi>on his Soul, ſo clear the Impreſſion of him upon the frame of the World, ſo unanimous the Conſent of Mankind, ſo powerful the Conviction of his own Conſcience, that he could not but taſte of the Powers of the World to come, and ſo Live as one that muſt Die; and ſo Die as one that muſt Live Eternally:</hi> And being asked one day, Why he was ſo ſad? he anſwered, <hi>Monſieur, Monſieur, the Soul is a ſerious thing; It muſt be either Sad here for a moment, or Sad hereafter for ever.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Cardinal <hi>Mazarine,</hi> when he came to Die, ſaid, <hi>O my poor Soul! Whither wilt thou go?</hi> ſaying, one Day, to the Queen Mother, <hi>Madam, your Favors have undone me; and were I to Live again, I would rather be a</hi> Capuchine, <hi>than a</hi> Courtier.</p>
               <p>Sir <hi>Francis Walſingham,</hi> towards the latter end of his Life, grew very Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancholy,
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:152497:26"/>and Writ to the Lord <hi>Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leigh,</hi> to this purpoſe, <hi>We have lived long enough to our Country, to our For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes, and to our Soveraign: It is high time to live to our Selves, and to our</hi> God. <hi>In the multitude of Affairs that paſs through our Hands, there muſt be ſome Miſcarriages; for which a whole Kingdom cannot make our Peace.</hi> Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon ſome Court Humoriſt being ſent to Divert Sir <hi>Francis: Ah!</hi> ſaid he, <hi>whil'ſt we Laugh, all things are ſerious round about us;</hi> God <hi>is ſerious when he Preſerveth us, and hath Patience to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards us;</hi> Chriſt <hi>is ſerious when he Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth for us; the</hi> Holy Ghoſt <hi>is ſerious when he ſtriveth with us; the Holy</hi> Scripture <hi>is ſerious when it is Read to us; the</hi> Sacraments <hi>are ſerious when they are Adminiſtred unto us; the whole</hi> Creation <hi>is ſerious in ſerving</hi> God <hi>and us; they are ſerious in</hi> Heaven <hi>and</hi> Hell; <hi>and ſhall a Man that hath one Foot in the Grave, Jeſt and Laugh?</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="46" facs="tcp:152497:27"/>
               <p>Dr. <hi>Dunn,</hi> a Man of as great Parts and Spirit, as any in this Nation, being on his Death-Bed, taking his ſolemn leave of all his moſt conſiderable Friends, left this with them, <hi>I Repent of all my Life, but that part of it I ſpent in Communion with</hi> God <hi>and doing Good. That Perſon, in a Dying hour, ſhall wiſh himſelf not a Man, that hath not been a good Chriſtian.</hi> When Queen <hi>Mary</hi> Died, Mr. <hi>Fox</hi> that Writ the Book of Martyrs, was Preaching Comfort to the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Exiles in <hi>Geneva,</hi> at which time, he did tell them, <hi>That now was the time come for their return into</hi> Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, <hi>and that he brought them that News from</hi> God; for which Words, many of the Grave Divines Rebuked him greatly for the preſent, but after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards excuſed him by the Event, for it appeared that Queen <hi>Mary</hi> Died but the Day before he ſo ſpake to them.</p>
               <p>Judge <hi>Nichols</hi> uſed to ſay, <hi>That he knew not what they called</hi> Puritan
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:152497:27"/>Preaching, <hi>but</hi> (he ſaid) <hi>that Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing which went next his Heart;</hi> and ſpake (as Attorney General <hi>Noy</hi> uſed to ſay of Doctor <hi>Preſton</hi>) as if they knew the Mind of <hi>God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Mr. <hi>Selden,</hi> that Univerſal Scholar, being ſuſpected by many, to have too little Affection to Religion, a little be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he Died, ſent for the Biſhop of <hi>Armagh,</hi> and Dr. <hi>Langbane,</hi> and told them to this effect, <hi>That he had Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veyed moſt part of the Learning that was amongst the Sons of Men: And that he had his Study full of Books and Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers, of moſt Subjects in the World, yet at that time could he not recollect any Paſſage out of thoſe many Books and Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuſcripts he was Maſter of, whereon he could reſt his Soul, ſave of the Holy Scriptures; wherein the moſt remarkable Paſſage that lay upon his Spirit was,</hi> Titus <hi>the</hi> 2. <hi>ver.</hi> 11, 12, 13, 14, 15.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Grotius,</hi> one of the greateſt of Scho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars, concluded his Life with this Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtation, <hi>That he would give all his
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:152497:28"/>Honor and Learning for the plain Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grity and harmleſs Innocency of</hi> Jean Urick, <hi>who was a Devout Poor Man, who ſpent Eight hours of his Time in Prayer, Eight in Labor, and but Eight in Sleep and other Neceſſaries.</hi> And with this Complaint, to another who admired his Aſtoniſhing Learning and Induſtry, <hi>Ah Vitam perdedi opero ſe nihil Agendo:</hi> And this Direction to a Third, that deſired, in his great Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and Wiſdom, in brief, to ſhew him what to do; who bade him, <hi>Be Serious.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Count <hi>Gundomer</hi> was as great a Wit and Stateſman as ever <hi>Europe</hi> knew, and took as much Liberty in point of Religion; till drawing towards his latter end, he would ſay, as they ſay of <hi>Anſalem; I fear nothing more in the World than Sin;</hi> often profeſſing, <hi>That if he ſaw Corporally the Horror of Sin on the one hand, and the Pains of Hell on the other, and muſt neceſſarily be plun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged into the One, he would chooſe Hell
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:152497:28"/>rather than Sin; yea, that what liberty ſoever he had taken, he had rather be torn in pieces with Wild Horſes, than wittingly, or willingly run into any Sin.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Above all</hi> (ſays Sir <hi>Philip Sidney,</hi> at the time of his Death) <hi>govern your Will and Affections by the Word and Will of your Creator; and in me behold the end of this World.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Damnation.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>PEter Lumbard</hi> ſays, <hi>GOD Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demns none before he Sins; nor Crowns any before he Overcomes.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Diſreſpect.</head>
               <p>IF any deſpiſe thee, do not bear a grudge againſt him for it: And be not offended with any, meerly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they do not Honor thee. If any neglect or ſlight thee, care not for it, yet obſerve it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="50" facs="tcp:152497:29"/>
               <head>Diſtruſt.</head>
               <p>
                  <q>IT is <hi>Diſtruſt</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> to be trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled about that which is to come; Impatience againſt <hi>God,</hi> to be trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled for what is preſent; and An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger at him, to be troubled at what is paſt, <hi>Vid.</hi> Afflictions and Sufferings.</q>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Doubting.</head>
               <p>ONe cauſe of uncomfortable Living is, That <hi>Chriſtians</hi> look more at their preſent Cauſe of Comfort or Diſcomfort, than they do at their fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture Happineſs, and the way to attain it. Another cauſe of <hi>Doubting,</hi> is, The weakneſs, and ſmall meaſure of your Graces, a little Faith and Love in and to <hi>Chriſt,</hi> is next to none at all, and therefore not eaſily diſerned as they will be when they are ſtrong; labor therefore, by Prayer, for more.</p>
               <p>What thou Doubteſt, do not.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="51" facs="tcp:152497:29"/>
               <head>Duties.</head>
               <p>INternal Acts of <hi>Duty</hi> put a Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs into Externals. It is our Faith, Fear, and Love of <hi>God,</hi> that makes our <hi>Duties</hi> good. The <hi>Almoſt-Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian</hi> can Pray, but cannot Love <hi>God;</hi> can Teach or Hear, but he cannot take delight in <hi>God, Job</hi> 17.10. for Delight ariſes from a ſuitableneſs between the Faculty and the Object. Now, none more unſuitable than <hi>God</hi> and a Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Heart: Alſo Delight ariſes from having what we deſire, and from en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joying what we have. How then can he delight in <hi>God,</hi> that neither en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyeth, nor hath, nor deſireth Good. Delight in <hi>God</hi> is one of the higheſt Exerciſes of Grace; and therefore how can he delight in <hi>God</hi> that hath no Grace.</p>
               <p>Would you be a Chriſtian indeed, then be much in the uſe and exerciſes of Religious Ordinances; but much
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:152497:30"/>more on Faith, and dependance on <hi>Chriſt</hi> and his Righteouſneſs. The Profeffor reſts in Duties, and ſo is but almoſt a <hi>Chriſtian;</hi> but ye muſt be ſure to reſt upon the Lord <hi>Chriſt:</hi> This is the way to be altogether a <hi>Chriſtian;</hi> if you believe that you are <hi>Abraham</hi>'s Seed, and Heirs according to the Promiſe.</p>
               <p>Let me Pray now, as if I ſhould ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver have Time to Pray more; Hear now, as if this were the laſt opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity to of Hearing. Leave nothing to do till to Morrow, that may poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly be done to Day. What true <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians</hi> ſhould we be, if we did not reckon of a Morrow? but ſee what a grand Deceit lies here; by putting it off till to Morrow, we gratifie our Conſcience in this, That we intend to do it hereafter; but moſt of all pleaſe Corruptions, in this, That we do it not to day.</p>
               <p>
                  <q>If thou would'ſt keep thy Heart from vain Excurſions, realize to thy
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:152497:30"/>ſelf, by Faith, the Holy and Awful Preſence of <hi>God</hi> in <hi>Duties.</hi> Flavel.</q>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Delays.</head>
               <p>
                  <q>THe <hi>Ripeneſs</hi> of the Occaſion muſt ever be well weighed: there is ſurely no greater <hi>Wiſdom</hi> than well to Time the firſt onſet of things. If a Man watch too long for Dangers, it is ods but he will fall aſleep.—On the other hand, to be deceived with too large Shaddow, as ſome have been, when the Moon was low, and ſhone on their Enemies Back, and ſo to ſhoot before the time. To teach Dangers to come on by too early buckling to them, as another extream. <bibl>
                        <hi>Bacon</hi>'s <hi>Eſſays.</hi> 195.</bibl>
                  </q>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Diſparagement.</head>
               <p>
                  <q>CErtainly, he that <hi>Diſparages</hi> ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by a Satyrical Wit, as he makes others afraid of his Wit, ſo he
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:152497:31"/>hath need to be afraid of others Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mories. <bibl>
                        <hi>Ibid.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                  </q>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Diſſimulation.</head>
               <p>
                  <q>THe beſt Diſpoſition and Temper, is, to have openeſs in Fame and Opinion, ſecreſie in Habit, Diſſimu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation in ſeaſonable uſe, and a Power to feign, if there be no Remedy, <bibl>
                        <hi>Ibid.</hi> 31.</bibl>
                  </q>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Doctrine.</head>
               <p>
                  <q>
                     <hi>CHRIST</hi> came down from <hi>Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven</hi> for this very end; namely, To teach us the way to Eternal Life, and therefore ſaith of himſelf, <hi>I am the Way, the Truth, and the Life, I come to Teach all theſe things unto you, and all the World. </hi>
                     <bibl>B. of <hi>Hereford.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                  </q>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="55" facs="tcp:152497:31"/>
               <head>Dignities.</head>
               <p>SOme that lived commendably be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they attained to <hi>Dignity,</hi> being ſet on the Candleſtick of the Church, turn their Light into Dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; It had been better for ſuch Lights ſtill to have been under a Buſhel.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Drunkenneſs.</head>
               <p>
                  <q>AS the Clouds darken <hi>Heaven,</hi> ſo Intemperate Banqueting the Mind: As the Violence of Winds and Waves ſinks a Ship; ſo <hi>Drunken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi> and <hi>Gluttony</hi> ſinks our Souls and Bodies into <hi>Hell.</hi>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi> Chriſologus.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Qui peccat ebrius luat ſobrias,</hi> If thou Offend when thou art <hi>Drunk,</hi> thou muſt be Puniſhed when thou art Sober.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="56" facs="tcp:152497:32"/>
               <head>Delights.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>THeodoret</hi> ſays, <hi>The</hi> Delights <hi>of the Soul are to know her Maker, and to know her own State.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Devils Power.</head>
               <p>
                  <q>THe <hi>Devils,</hi> without <hi>Chriſt</hi>'s leave, had no Power over the <hi>Gaderan</hi>'s Swine; much leſs have they Power over <hi>GOD</hi>'s Sheep. <bibl>
                        <hi>Tertullian.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                  </q>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Equity.</head>
               <p>EQUITY without Goodneſs, is Severity; and Juſtice without Piety, Cruelty.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="57" facs="tcp:152497:32"/>
               <head>Earthly Things.</head>
               <p>COnſidering the Vanity of <hi>
                     <hi>Earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Things</hi> Iraeneus</hi> ſaith, <hi>What is that Honor that is ſo ſhort lived, as that perhaps it was not of Yeſterday, neither will be to Morrow: And ſuch Men that labor ſo much for it, are but like Froth, which, tho' it be uppermoſt, yet is unprofitable.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Evidences.</head>
               <p>WHen thou haſt <hi>Evidences</hi> of thy Sincerity, which cannot in reaſon be gain-ſaid, hold to them and take Comfort in them; yet ſtill endeavor, by reviews, and diligent ſearchings, to clear it more and more. We keep our <hi>Evidences,</hi> by keeping our Graces in lively Exerciſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="58" facs="tcp:152497:33"/>
               <head>Election.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>GOD</hi> by his Word calleth all; but his Secret <hi>Election</hi> appointeth who ſhall hear with Fruit.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>GOD</hi> hath, according to the Tenor of his Covenant, procured Salvation for all, if they will Believe; but he hath procured for his Choſen, even this condition of Believing.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Envy.</head>
               <p>OF all other Affections, it is moſt Importune and continual; for of all other Affections, there is an oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion given but now and then; but <hi>Envy</hi> is ever working on ſome or other: And it is alſo noted, that <hi>Love</hi> and <hi>Envy</hi> make a Man Pine, which other Affections do not, becauſe they are ſo continual: It is alſo the vileſt Affection, and moſt depraved; for
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:152497:33"/>which cauſe, it is the proper Attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute of the Devil, who is called the <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vious Man,</hi> that ſoweth Tares among the Wheat by Night; as it always cometh to paſs that <hi>Envy</hi> worketh Subtilty, and in the Dark, and to the prejudice of good things, ſuch as Wheat. <hi>Bacon</hi>'s <hi>Eſſays.</hi> 49.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Proſper</hi> ſaith, <hi>The Envious Man hath ſo many Tortures, as the Envied hath Praiſes. It is the Juſtice of Envy to Torment and Kill the Envious.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Examination.</head>
               <p>THe end of <hi>Examination</hi> is to bring a Man to ſuch a ſight of his Sins, as might truly humble him, and make him ſenſible of his own danger, that hath provoked ſo great a Majeſty, who is able ſo ſadly to revenge himſelf upon him: and that will ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, even to the moſt Carnal Heart, appear a moſt reaſonable ground of
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:152497:34"/>Sorrow. But that is not all, It muſt likewiſe bring him to a ſence and Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horrency of his Baſeneſs and Ingra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude, that hath thus offended ſo good and Gracious a <hi>God;</hi> that hath made ſuch unkind and unworthy Returns to thoſe tender Mercies of his. <hi>Whole Duty of Man.</hi> Vide <hi>here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in Humility.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It's ſaid of Sir <hi>Thomas More, That the Government of his Family was, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>act enjoyning all his Children to take Vertue for their Meat, and Play for their Sawce.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Encouragement.</head>
               <p>ONe Writ to the Duke of <hi>Bucking<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham, That</hi> Diſincouragements <hi>would deter Men of Parts, whom <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragements</hi> might make Servic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="61" facs="tcp:152497:34"/>
               <head>Elegancy.</head>
               <p>SIR <hi>Francis Bacon</hi>'s Axiom was, <hi>Words ſhould wait on Things, and not Things on Words.</hi> And his Reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution was, <hi>That all affected Elegance was below the Gravity and Majeſty of a publick Diſcourſe.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>FAITH.</head>
               <p>I Have One Definition of <hi>Faith,</hi> which is the beſt: <hi>Faith,</hi> ſaith Lord Chief Juſtice <hi>Hales, is a firm aſſent to the Sacred Truths, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Truths relate to things paſt; as, that</hi> God <hi>made the World; that</hi> Chriſt, <hi>the</hi> Meſſias, <hi>is come in the Fleſh,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Or to Things preſent; as, That Almighty</hi> God <hi>knows all I do, and knows all I think; or, That he is a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciled Father unto me, in</hi> Chriſt Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus;
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:152497:35"/>
                  <hi>Or Things to come, which principal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly excite thoſe Two great movers of the Soul, <hi>Hope</hi> and <hi>Fear,</hi> in relation to the future Life of Rewards and Puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</hi> Hale.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Faith</hi> worketh by Love, conſumeth our Corruptions, and Sanctifieth the whole Man throughout.</p>
               <p>I come to <hi>God,</hi> by <hi>Jeſus Chriſt;</hi> and as I believe in <hi>God,</hi> ſo I believe alſo in <hi>Jeſus Chriſt;</hi> and rejoyce and glory in Him, acknowledging my own un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthineſs and ſinfulneſs: I reſt en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirely on Him, as the ground of my Juſtification to Life, and of all favour and acceptance with <hi>God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I moſt heartily take <hi>Chriſt</hi> accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the offers of the Goſpel; not only to be Juſtified from my Sins, and delivered from the Wrath to come, by his Merits, but alſo to be Sanctified by his Word and Spirit; and to be Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verned by his Law, and to be brought by him unto Fellowſhip with <hi>GOD.</hi> Corbet<hi>'s Self-Imployment.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="63" facs="tcp:152497:35"/>
               <p>Tho' there be not a co-operation of <hi>Faith,</hi> and other Graces to Juſtifie, yet there is a co-exiſtence of <hi>Faith</hi> and other Graces in the Perſons Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtified.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Faith</hi> cannot be the Hand to take <hi>Chriſt,</hi> but Love will be the Warmth to heat our Affections to <hi>Chriſt;</hi> they always go together like Mother and Daughter, <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.6. <hi>Phil.</hi> 5.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Faith</hi> is required as an Hand which we ſhould put forth to receive Pardon for our Sins. <hi>Firſt,</hi> At <hi>God</hi>'s Hands, as a Free-Gift, for he blotteth out our Tranſgreſſions for his own ſake. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 43.25. <hi>Secondly,</hi> At <hi>Chriſt</hi>'s Hands, as a purchaſed Commodity bought for us, with his own precious Blood, and given to you.</p>
               <p>There is <hi>Firſt</hi> an Heart mollifying <hi>Faith. Secondly,</hi> An Heart purifying <hi>Faith. Thirdly,</hi> A fruitful <hi>Faith. Fourthly,</hi> An Heart Praying <hi>Faith. Fifthly,</hi> A Victorious <hi>Faith.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="64" facs="tcp:152497:36"/>
               <p>
                  <q>Tho' we are Juſtified by <hi>Faith,</hi> yet it is by <hi>Faith working by Love,</hi> Gal. 5.6. And he that <hi>Loves</hi> God, <hi>keeps his Commandments,</hi> John 14. <bibl>
                        <hi>Biſhop of</hi> Hereford<hi>'s Legacy,</hi> 66, 67.</bibl>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>As to <hi>Faith</hi> Juſtifying, and the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of Good-Works, Biſhop <hi>Cranmer</hi> concluded with this, <hi>That our Juſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation was to be aſcribed only to the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of</hi> Chriſt Jeſus; <hi>and that thoſe that are Juſtified muſt have Charity as well as</hi> Faith; <hi>but that neither of theſe is the Meritorious Cauſe of our Juſtification.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>When ever we read of our Juſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation by Faith, it is meant of our Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtification in a Goſpel way; and that is by <hi>Chriſt</hi> alone Meritoriouſly, and by what he hath done and Suffered: <hi>Faith</hi> being but the conditional means. <hi>Chriſt</hi>'s Satisfaction contrived, provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, accepted, and the Conditions per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed, then every Saved Perſon will appear Righteous before <hi>God;</hi> and it will be very apparently a Righteous thing with <hi>God,</hi> to bring ſuch to Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:152497:36"/>who have <hi>Chriſt</hi>'s Righteouſneſs by way of Satisfaction, to anſwer for them in reſpect of the Law, and their own <hi>Faith,</hi> and ſincere (tho' imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect) Obedience to anſwer the terms of the Goſpel.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Faith, to Live by it.</head>
               <p>IT is an Heavenly and Dutiful com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting our whole Perſons, and of our whole Eſtates upon <hi>God,</hi> with a Pious dependance on <hi>Chriſt,</hi> for ſuit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able and ſeaſonable Supplies in all our Exigencies, Occurrences, and Changes whatſoever. When the Soul is in any Exigence, and comes to <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and puts it ſelf upon him, and truſts to him for help: This is to <hi>Live by Faith;</hi> and this <hi>Faith</hi> extends it ſelf both to our Spiritual and Temporal Eſtate. The Juſt ſhall Live by his <hi>Faith, Gal.</hi> 3.11. ſpeaking of the <hi>Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral</hi> State; <hi>And Live by Faith of the
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:152497:37"/>Son of</hi> God, (ſays St. <hi>Paul</hi>) Gal. 2.2. ſpeaking of the <hi>Spiritual</hi> State.</p>
               <p>
                  <q>By reaſon of the Dignity of <hi>Chriſt's</hi> Perſon, his Obedience and Sufferings being performed in our Nature, and wholly upon our account, <hi>God</hi> by an Infinite Gracious Statute, in <hi>Heaven,</hi> accepts them for us; (tho' not as done by us) and reckons all the Ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects and Advantages of them by way of Imputation to us. <bibl>
                        <hi>Juſtification Evangelical.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>We ſhould not try Mens <hi>Faith</hi> by their Perſons; but their Perſons by their <hi>Faith.</hi> 
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>Tertullian.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi> ſaith, <hi>As a Rock, tho' the Winds blow, and the Waves beat againſt it, is Immovable; ſo</hi> Faith, <hi>grounded on the Rock</hi> Chriſt, <hi>holds out in all Temptations, and Spiritual Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bats.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Chryſologus</hi> ſaith, <hi>Neither in the Steel alone, nor in the Flint alone, any Fire can be ſeen, nor Extracted, but by Conjunction and Colliſion; ſo, nor by</hi>
                  <pb n="67" facs="tcp:152497:37"/>Faith <hi>alone, nor by Works alone is Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation to be attained, but by joyning both together.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Alexander</hi> of <hi>Hales</hi> ſaith, <hi>What the Eye is to the Body, Faith is to the Soul, it's good for direction if it be kept well. And as Flies hurt the Eyes, ſo little Sins, and Ill-Thoughts do the Soul.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Says <hi>Luther</hi> to <hi>Melancthon, Who feared to Profeſs the Truth, If the Cauſe be bad, lets revoke it, and fly back; but if it be good, why do we make</hi> God <hi>a Lyar, who hath made us ſuch great Promiſes,</hi> viz. <hi>Caſt thy Care on the Lord, and be of good Comfort, I have Overcome the World. If</hi> Chriſt <hi>be the Conqueror of the World, why ſhould we fear it, as tho' it would Over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come us? therefore be not afraid, but Couragious and Chearful, ſolicitous for nothing, the Lord is at hand to help us.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Calvin</hi> ſaith, <hi>With all my Heart I embrace the Mercy which</hi> God <hi>hath uſed towards me, for</hi> Jeſus Chriſt<hi>'s ſake, recompencing my Faults with the
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:152497:38"/>Merits of his Death and Paſſion, that Satisfaction may be made, by this means, for all my Sins and Crimes, and the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance of them may be blotted out.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>I have not lived ſo, that I am aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to live longer, neither do I fear to Die, becauſe I have a Merciful Lord, in that a Crown of Righteouſneſs is laid up for me:</hi> Chriſt <hi>is my Righteouſneſs. Father, let thy Will be done, thy Will, I ſay, and not my own, which is imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect and depraved. This Day let me ſee the Lord</hi> Jeſus, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Jewel.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Fall of Man.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſelm</hi> ſaith, <hi>O hard hap! What did Man loſe? What did he find? He loſt the Bleſſedneſs to which he was made, and found Death, to which he was not made.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="69" facs="tcp:152497:38"/>
               <head>Fortune.</head>
               <p>SIR <hi>William Saint James</hi> was wont to ſay, <hi>That none Fought well, but thoſe that did it for a <hi>Fortune.</hi>
                  </hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Fortune</hi> (ſaith Sir <hi>Ralph Winwood) may begin a Man's Greatneſs, but Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue muſt continue it.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Friendſhip.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Friendſhip</hi> (ſaith my Lord <hi>Bacon) eaſeth the Heart, and cheareth the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding, making clear Day in both; partly by giving the pureſt Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil, or partly from our Intereſt and Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſeſſions, and partly, by allowing op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity to Diſcourſe, and by that Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe to clear the Mind, to recollect the Thoughts, to ſee how they look in Words, whereby Men attain to the higheſt Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, which</hi> (Dioniſius Aeriopagitus <hi>ſaith) is the Daughter of Reflection.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="70" facs="tcp:152497:39"/>
               <head>Forgiveneſs.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>IF a Man</hi> (ſaith Sir <hi>David Brooke) wrongeth me once,</hi> God <hi>forgive him; If he wrong me the ſecond time,</hi> God <hi>forgive me.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>O <hi>God</hi> Forgive me my Ten Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand Talents: I come to <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> who hath made ſatisfaction, and lay this heavy Reckoning to his Account. Lord forgive me mine Iniquity, for it is very great. <hi>Vid.</hi> Pag. 70.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Frugality.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Frugality</hi> is the Left-Hand of Fortune, and Diligence the Right.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Faſting.</head>
               <p>
                  <q>
                     <hi>FAſting,</hi> and other Holy Revenges upon our ſelves for our Sins, are very acceptable to <hi>God;</hi> yet we muſt
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:152497:39"/>not think, that either thoſe, or any thing elſe we can do, can make ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction for our Offences; for that nothing elſe but the Blood of <hi>Chriſt</hi> can do: And therefore, upon that, and not upon any of our Performan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, we muſt depend for Pardon; yet, ſince that Blood ſhall never be applied to any but Penitent Sinners, we are as much concern'd to bring forth all the fruits of Repentance, as if our Hopes depended on them wholly. <bibl>
                        <hi>Duty of Man,</hi> 126.</bibl>
                  </q>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Fear.</head>
               <p>
                  <q>THe Man that <hi>Fears <hi>GOD</hi>
                     </hi> is the Wiſeſt Man; and he that upon that account departs from Evil, is the Man of greateſt Underſtanding. <bibl>
                        <hi>Hales</hi>'s <hi>Contemplations,</hi> 15.</bibl>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>When Trembling is the Fruit of a Spirit broken for Sin, and the Law in its own Eyes, there <hi>God</hi> will look. <bibl>
                        <hi>Mead.</hi> 72.</bibl>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <pb n="72" facs="tcp:152497:40"/>
               <p>
                  <q>How great a Madneſs is it to <hi>Fear</hi> Man, will ſoon appear, if we do but compare what Man can do unto us, and what <hi>God</hi> can do: And <hi>Firſt,</hi> It is ſure, it is not in the Power of Man (I may ſay, Devils too) to do us any hurt, without <hi>God</hi> permit and ſuffer them to do it: So that if we do but keep him to be our Friend, we may ſay with the <hi>Pſalmiſt, The Lord is on my ſide, I need not fear what Man can do unto me;</hi> for let their Malice be ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſo great, he can reſtrain, and keep them from hurting us: Nay, He can change their Minds towards us, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to that of the Wiſe-Man, <hi>Prov.</hi> 16.7. <hi>When a Man's Ways pleaſe the Lord, he can make his very Enemies to be at Peace with him.</hi> A notable Example of this, we have of <hi>Jacob, Gen.</hi> 32. Who, when his Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Eſau</hi> was coming againſt him, as an Enemy, <hi>God</hi> wonderfully turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed his Heart; ſo that he met him with all the loving Expreſſions of
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:152497:40"/>Brotherly kindneſs, as you may read in the next Chapter. But <hi>Secondly,</hi> Suppoſe Men were left at liberty to do thee what Miſchief they could; alas! their Power goeth but a little way; they may perhaps rob thee of thy Goods, it may be they may take away thy Liberty, or thy Credit, or perchance thy Life too, but that thou knoweſt is the utmoſt they can do. But now <hi>God</hi> can do all this when he pleaſes; and that which is infinitely more, his Vengeance reach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es even beyond Death it ſelf, to the Eternal Miſery both of Body and Soul in Hell: in compariſon of which, Death is ſo inconſiderable, that we are not to look upon it with any dread. <hi>Fear not them that Kill the Body, and after have no more that they can do,</hi> ſaith Chriſt, <hi>Luk.</hi> 12.4. and then immediately adds, <hi>But I will forewarn you whom ye ſhall fear; fear him, which after he hath Killed, hath Power to caſt into Hell; yea, I ſay
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:152497:41"/>unto you, fear him.</hi> In which words, the Compariſon is ſet between the greateſt Ill we can ſuffer from Man, the loſs of Life, and thoſe ſadder E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vils <hi>God</hi> can inflict on us: And the latter are found to be the only dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful things, and therefore <hi>God</hi> only to be Feared. <bibl>
                        <hi>Duty of Man.</hi> 20.</bibl>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>Let your Fear of Men, ſtir up an Holy Fear of <hi>GOD.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Grace and Merits.</head>
               <p>CArdinal <hi>Pool</hi> was wont to ſay, (tho' a <hi>Papiſt) We cannot give too much to</hi> God<hi>'s Grace, nor too little to our own Merits.</hi> He ſaid, when he returned into <hi>England, I came hither not to Condemn, but to Reconcile; not to Compel, but to Deſire.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="75" facs="tcp:152497:41"/>
               <head>God's People.</head>
               <p>THey are a ſmall part of loſt Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind, whom God hath from Eternity Predeſtinated to the Glory of Heaven, for the Glory of his Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, and given to his Son, to be by him in a Spiritual manner Redeemed from their loſt Eſtate, and advanced to this higher Glory; all which Chriſt doth in due time accompliſh accordingly for them, and by his Spirit upon them: But this is but a piece of their Deſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion concerning God's Work for them and upon them. Lets ſee alſo what they are to do in regard of the work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of their own Souls towards God and their Redeemer again, <hi>viz.</hi> Theſe People of God are that part of the Externally called, who having been by the Spirit of Chriſt throughly, tho imperfectly Regenerated, and hereby Convinced, and ſenſible of the Evil
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:152497:42"/>in Sin, that Miſery in themſelves, that Vanity in the Creature, that Neceſſity, Sufficiency, and Excellency of Jeſus Chriſt; that they abhor that Evil, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wail that Miſery, and turn their hearts from that Vanity, and moſt affectio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nately accepting of Chriſt for their Saviour and Lord, to bring them to <hi>God</hi> their chief Good, and preſent them perfectly juſt before him: Do accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly enter into a Cordial Covenant with him, and herein perſevere to their lives end. <hi>Baxter.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A Godly Man is one of thoſe whoſe Converſation is in Heaven, his Hopes and Heart are likewiſe there, for his Riches, his Houſe, and his Relations are in Heaven, a Godly Mans All is there; ask him what he hath on Earth, and he will tell you nothing, or leſs than nothing: Ask him then, wherein are his Bleſſings? he will tell you, where his Father is, there are my deſired Bleſſings, there are my hopes, there is my All, there
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:152497:42"/>I wiſh that I my ſelf were with them. <hi>Wadſworth</hi> on <hi>Phil.</hi> 12.</p>
               <p>I would not only have God here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after, but in this World for my chief good; for, as far as I am able to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcerne my heart and ways, I have cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen the Lord for my Portion, I take my reſt in him, and not in the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; to Love, Fear, Admire, and Bleſs him, and to have my Communion with him, is my Joy: an Eternal Viſion and Fruition of God, is my great hope, he is even now better than the whole World. Mr. <hi>Corbet</hi>'s <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiry,</hi> pag. 6.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Lactantius</hi> ſays, Godlineſs Enriches the owner.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Grace.</head>
               <p>GRace flowing from the Spirit of God, makes the Soul like a Fountain, whoſe Waters are pure and wholeſome; for Grace Beautifyeth, Cleanſeth, and Saveth the whole Man. <hi>Ignatius.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="78" facs="tcp:152497:43"/>
               <p>When a Man deſires Grace from a right ſence of his natural State, when he ſees the vileneſs of Sin, and the woful, defiled, and loathſome condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion he is in by reaſon of Sin, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore deſires the Grace of Chriſt with unceſſant earneſtneſs, to renue and change him, this is Grace. <hi>Mead</hi> 68.</p>
               <p>Grace is a comprehenſive Word, and includes in it not only favour and acceptance with God, but alſo thoſe other acceſſaries of the Gifts of Boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and Goodneſs, which comes from the great Giver of every good and perfect Gift, as Wiſdom, Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, Purity of Heart, and the like. <hi>Hales.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Grace is precious, it ſuffereth not it ſelf to be mingled with External things, nor with Earthly Comforts; thou oughteſt therefore to caſt away all hindrances of Grace, if thou de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire the Infuſion thereof. <hi>De Kempis.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The leaſt Grace gives a full Intereſt in the Blood of Chriſt, whereby we
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:152497:43"/>are fully and throughly Purged; and it gives a full Intereſt in the ſtrength and power of Chriſt, whereby we ſhall be perfectly preſerved. <hi>Mead.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To quicken your Graces, you muſt firſt quicken your Humility, by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering your many Sins repeated. Secondly, you muſt quicken your Faith, by Meditating on the Promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes to all Penitent Sinners. Thirdly, by quickening your Love to God, by conſidering his Mercies, eſpecially thoſe remembred in the Sacrament; his giving Chriſt to Die for us, and your Love to your Neighbour, nay, to your very Enemies, by conſidering that great Example of his Suffering for us, when we were Enemies to him.</p>
               <p>You muſt know, that it is not gifts but Grace that makes a Man a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian; a Man may Preach like an A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle, and Pray like an Angel, and yet have the Heart of a Devil: It is Grace only that can change the heart, a graceleſs Profeſſor may have more
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:152497:44"/>gifts than the moſt ſound Believer; he may out-Pray, out Preach, and out-do them; but they in Sincerity, and Integrity, out-do him.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Good and Wicked Men, and Hypocrites.</head>
               <p>THey are like True and Counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feit Money, the one ſeems to be good, and is not; the other both ſeems and is good. <hi>Ignatius.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Goodneſs.</head>
               <p>GOod things of this life, if they be our only Portion, we are in a ſad Condition; ſo <hi>Gregory</hi> the Great thought, for he could never read thoſe words: <hi>Son, remember thou in thy life time received thy good things,</hi> without Horror and Aſtoniſhment, leaſt hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſuch Dignities and Honours as he
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:152497:44"/>had, he ſhould be excluded from his Portion in Heaven.</p>
               <p>The ſigns and parts of goodneſs are theſe; If a man be Courteous to Strangers, it ſhews he is a Citizen of the World, and that his heart is no Iſland cut off from other Lands, but a continent that joyns to them: If he be Compaſſionate towards the Affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions of others, it ſhews his Heart is like the noble Tree, that is Wound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed it ſelf, when it gives the healing Balm: If he eaſily pardons and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mits Offences, it ſhews his Mind is planted above Injuries, ſo that it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be ſhot: If he be thankful for ſmall Benefits, it ſhews he weighs mens Minds, and not their Traſh: But above all, if he have St. <hi>Pauls</hi> affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, That he could wiſh himſelf <hi>Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thematized</hi> from Chriſt for the Salvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of his Brethren, it ſhews much of a Divine Nature, and a kind of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity to Chriſt himſelf. <hi>Bacon</hi>'s <hi>Eſſays.</hi> 70.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="82" facs="tcp:152497:45"/>
               <head>Grandees.</head>
               <p>It is ſaid that <hi>Great Men</hi> are the firſt that find their own Griefs, and the laſt that find their own Faults: The Lord <hi>Rich</hi> was quick in both, and hath taught us this, that certainly Men of great Fortunes are ſtrangers to themſelves, and while they are in the puzzle of Buſineſs, &amp; have no time to attend the Welfare either of Body or Soul; and that they muſt with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draw from this World, before they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire to another.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Happineſs.</head>
               <p>THe way to attain to it in ſhort is, by the conſtant and ſincere en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours of a holy Life, in and through the Merits of Jeſus Chriſt: Chriſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed is the Author of Eternal Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, but Obedience is the Condition of it; ſo the Apoſtle tells us, That
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:152497:45"/>Chriſt is the Author of Eternal Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation to them that Obey him, <hi>Heb.</hi> 5.1.</p>
               <p>I long to enjoy thee, O Lord, moſt inwardly, but I cannot attain unto it; my deſire is, that I may be given up to Heavenly things; but unmortified Paſſions and Temporal things weigh down my Mind. I would be above all things, but with the Fleſh I am forced to be ſubject againſt my will. Thus unhappy Man that I am, I fight againſt my ſelf, and am grievous to my ſelf: Whilſt my Spirit ſeeks to be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove, my Fleſh ſeeks to be below.</p>
               <p>Say not that we are unable to ſet our Hearts on Heaven, this muſt be the Work of God, and therefore all your Exhortations are in vain; for I tell you, though God be the chief diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſer of your Hearts, yet, next under Him, you have the greateſt Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of them your ſelves; and a great power of ordering your own thoughts and determining your
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:152497:46"/>own Wills in their choice; tho' with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out <hi>Chriſt</hi> you can do nothing, yet un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der him you may do much, and muſt do much, or elſe it muſt be undone, and you undone thro' your own neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect. Do your own Parts, and you will have no cauſe to Diſtruſt whether <hi>Chriſt</hi> will do his: Do not your own Conſciences tell you, when your Thoughts are abroad, that you may do more than you do, in the reſtrain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of them; and when your Hearts be flat, and neglect Eternity, and ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom mind the Joys before you, that is moſt wilful. If you be to ſtudy a ſet Speech, you can force your Thoughts to the intended Subject. If a Miniſter be to Study a Sermon, he can force his Thoughts to the moſt ſaving Truths, and that without any ſpecial Grace. Might not a true Chriſtian then, mind more the things of the Life to come, if he did not neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect that Authority over his own Thoughts, which <hi>God</hi> hath given him;
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:152497:46"/>eſpecially in ſuch a work as this, where he may more confidently ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect the Aſſiſtance of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> who u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth not to forſake his People, in the work he ſetteth them upon. <hi>Mr.</hi> Baxter<hi>'s Reſt. Part the Fourth.</hi> 53.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Heavenly Sayings.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Robert Rollock</hi> ſaith, <hi>I bleſs</hi> God <hi>I have all my Senſes entire, but my Heart is in Heaven; and Lord</hi> Jeſus <hi>why ſhould'ſt not thou have it? It hath been my Care, all the Day long to Dedicate it unto thee: I pray thee take it, that it may live with thee for ever.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Hooper</hi> Martyr, ſaid, <hi>Impriſonment is painful, but Liberty upon Evil Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions is worſe: The Priſon ſtinks, yet not ſo much as ſweet Houſes, where the Fear of</hi> God <hi>is wanting. I muſt be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone, and Solitary; it is better be ſo, and have</hi> God <hi>with me, than to be in the Company of the Wicked. Loſs of
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:152497:47"/>Goods is great, but the loſs of Grace and</hi> God<hi>'s favour is greater: I cannot tell how to anſwer before Great and Learned Men; yet it is better do that, than ſtand Naked before</hi> God<hi>'s Tribunal. I ſhall Die by the hands of Cruel Men: He is Bleſſed that loſeth his Life, and finds Life Eternal. There is neither Felicity nor Adverſity in this World is great, if it be compared with the Joys of the World to come.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Bilney</hi> the Martyr being going to be Burnt, was, by a Friend, Exhorted to take his Death patiently: to whom he ſaid, <hi>I am Sailing, with the Mariner, thro' a boiſterous Sea, but ſhortly ſhall be in Heaven; help me with your Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Biſhop <hi>Ridley</hi> Writing to Mr. <hi>Brad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford,</hi> ſaid, <hi>Bleſſed be</hi> God, <hi>notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding our hard reſtraint, and the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil Reports raiſed of us, we are Merry in</hi> God, <hi>and all our Care is and ſhall be (by</hi> God<hi>'s Grace) to pleaſe and ſerve him; from whom we expect (after
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:152497:47"/>theſe Temporary and Momentany Miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries) to have Eternal Joy and Felicity with</hi> Abraham, Iſaac, <hi>and</hi> Jacob, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And Writing to Mr. <hi>Latimer,</hi> in Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, he ſaid, <hi>Good Father, let me have ſomewhat more from you to Comfort my Stomach; for unleſs the Lord aſſiſt me, in his Service, I ſhall play the White<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver'd Knight; but he can make a Cow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ard in his Cauſe to Fight like a Man.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Jerom</hi> of <hi>Prague</hi> being ready to be Burned, theſe were his laſt words, <hi>This Soul of mine, in Flames of Fire, O</hi> Chriſt, <hi>I offer unto thee.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Sir <hi>Thomas More</hi> ſaid, <hi>We go to Hell with more pain than we may go to Heaven with.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Honor.</head>
               <p>IT is <hi>Machiavils</hi> Rule, <hi>That they that riſe very high ſhould deſcend timely, to quit the Envy, leſt they loſe the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor of their Greatneſs.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="88" facs="tcp:152497:48"/>
               <p>Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> asked Sir <hi>Nicholas Bacon, Why his Houſe was ſo little;</hi> he anſwered, <hi>My Houſe is not too little for me, but you have made me too big for my Houſe.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Heavenly Country.</head>
               <p>HOw Worthy, yea, how neceſſary a thing it were that they (that is, the Lord <hi>Burleigh,</hi> and Sir <hi>Francis Walſingham</hi>) ſhould at length bid fare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wel to the Snares, one of a Secretery, and the other of an Ambaſſador, and ſhould both of them ſet their Minds upon their <hi>Heavenly Country;</hi> and by Repentance, ask Mercy of <hi>GOD.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Human Affairs.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Human Affairs</hi> are ſo uncertain, that he ſeemeth the Wiſeſt Man, not who hath a Spirit to go on, but
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:152497:48"/>he that hath a Warineſs to come off: And that ſeems the beſt Courſe that hath moſt Paſſages out of it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Hatred.</head>
               <p>THe World perhaps doth not Love us, have we not reaſon to thank it, if it make us place our Affections on Heaven.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Epiphanius</hi> uſed to ſay, <hi>That he ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver let his Adverſary Sleep; not that he diſturbed him in his Sleep, but becauſe he agreed with him preſently, and would not let the Sun go down upon his Wrath.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Proſper</hi> ſaith, <hi>Thou ſhalt neither</hi> Hate <hi>the Man for his Vice; nor</hi> Love <hi>the Vice for the Mans ſake.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Heart and Tongue.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>CYprian</hi> ſaith, <hi>Two things never wax Old in Man, the <hi>Heart</hi> ever ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gining new Cogitations, and the <hi>Congue</hi> uttering vain Corruptions of the Heart.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="90" facs="tcp:152497:49"/>
               <head>Hearing the Word.</head>
               <p>Cyril ſaith, <hi>Some came to Church to ſee Faſhions, others to meet their Friends; yet it is better come ſo, than not at all: In the mean time, the Net is laid, and they that intend nothing leſs, are drawn into</hi> Chriſt, <hi>who catches them not to deſtroy them, but that being Dead, he may bring them to Life Eternal.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>St. <hi>Bernard,</hi> when he came to the Church Door, uſed to ſay this to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf; <hi>Stay here all my Worldly Thoughts and Vanity, that I may entertain Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly Meditations.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Hereticks.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>IRaeneus</hi> was wont to compare the <hi>Hereticks</hi> and <hi>Schiſmaticks</hi> of his Time, to <hi>Eſop</hi>'s Dogg, that loſt the Subſtance of Religion, whil'ſt they gaped too earneſtly after the Shaddow.</p>
               <pb n="91" facs="tcp:152497:49"/>
               <p>It was St. <hi>Hierom</hi>'s ſaying, <hi>Dead Fleſh is to be cut off for fear of Gangrene.</hi> Arias <hi>at firſt was but a Spark, but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing not ſuppreſſed betimes, proved the Incendary of the whole Church.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Holineſs.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>ISodore</hi> faith, <hi>Knowledge and a Good Life are both very profitable; yet if both cannot be attained, a Good Life is rather to be ſought than much Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Hope.</head>
               <p>WE will never part comfortably with our Enjoyments on Earth, till we have comfortable Thoughts of better in Heaven.</p>
               <p>That <hi>Hope</hi> of Salvation that is not accompanied with Heart Purification, is vain <hi>Hope.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="92" facs="tcp:152497:50"/>
               <head>Humility.</head>
               <p>IT is a lowly frame and habit of Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, ariſing from a due ſence of the glorious Excellency of Almighty <hi>God,</hi> and our own Frailties and Infirmities, and upon our Infinite dependance on his Bounty, Goodneſs, and Mercy, whereby we are under a conſtant, firm, and ſound Conviction; that all that is in us, or that is Injoyed, or can be expected by us, is from the free and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſerved Liberality of that glorious <hi>GOD.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>An Humble Man</hi> (ſays <hi>Alexander</hi> of <hi>Hales) is like a good Tree; the more fuller of Fruit the Branches are, the lower they bend themſelves.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It is the empty Soul (I mean, one empty of Pride, Self-conceit, and Vain-Glory) that is capable of Satisfaction with the Divine Goodneſs.</p>
               <p>
                  <q>If an Humble Man doth any Good, Noble, or becoming Action, he
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:152497:50"/>checks the firſt motions of Pride and Oſtentations in himſelf, and receives not the Applauſe of others, but di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rects all to the Praiſe and Glory of it to that <hi>God</hi> that hath done it for him, and by him, <hi>Not unto us, but unto thy Name give the Glory.</hi> 
                     <bibl>C. J. <hi>Hales.</hi> 141.</bibl>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>And Juſtice <hi>Hales</hi> ſaid, <hi>I can call my own Experience to witneſs, that even in the external Actions, Occurrences, and Incidencies of my whole Life, I was ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver diſappointed of the beſt Guidance and Direction, when in</hi> Humility, <hi>and the ſence of my own deficiency and diffidence of my own Ability to direct my ſelf, or grapple with the difficulties of my Life, I have with Humility and Sincerity em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed the ſecret Directions and Gui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of the Divine Providence; and I dare therein appeal to the vigilant and ſtrict Obſervance of any Man's Experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, whether he hath not found the ſame Experience in relation to himſelf, and his own Actions and Succeſſes, whether
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:152497:51"/>thoſe Counſels and Purpoſes which have been taken up, after an humble Invocation of the Divine Direction, have not always been moſt ſucceſsful in the end.</hi> 146, and 130.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Hypocriſie.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Hypocriſie</hi> is to do the outward Acts, without the inward Since<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity; now, to do them without Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerity, is to do them without Love; for to do a thing in Love, is to do it in Sincerity; that is the beſt way to know it by: A man that doth much to God, but not out of Love, all that he doth is out of Hypocriſie. Doctor <hi>Preſton.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Hypocrite</hi> hath a Profeſſion that he may not ſeem Wicked, but it is but a Profeſſion, and therein he is Wicked. He that pretends to God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs by a ſpecious Profeſſion, and yet doth not practiſe Godlineſs by an
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:152497:51"/>holy Converſation, he hath a Form, but doth deny the Power. <hi>Mead.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It is ſeriouſneſs and earneſtneſs a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout fleſhly Vanity, and want of ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſneſs about things Spiritual and Eternal, which is the temper and Character of the Hypocrite.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Jeſts.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>ARche</hi> made King <hi>James</hi> ſenſible of the danger the Prince was in in <hi>Spain,</hi> by telling him he would change Caps with him; <hi>Why, (ſaid the King?) becauſe thou haſt ſent the Prince into</hi> Spain, <hi>from whence he is never likely to return;</hi> But ſaid the King, <hi>What wilt thou ſay, if thou ſee him return back a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain; Marry,</hi> ſaid he, <hi>I will take off the Fools Cap which I now put on thy head for ſending him thither, and put it on the King of</hi> Spains <hi>for letting him return.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="96" facs="tcp:152497:52"/>
               <p>Secretary <hi>Baurus</hi>'s Son kept a Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemans Wife in <hi>Shropſhire,</hi> and when he was weary of her, cauſed her Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band to be dealt with to take her home again, aſſuring him of 500 <hi>l.</hi> for Reparation: The Gentleman went to Sir <hi>Henry Sidney</hi> to take his Advice, telling him, That his Wife promiſed him to live a new Life, and to ſay the truth, 500 <hi>l.</hi> would be very ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable at that time: <hi>By my troth,</hi> ſaid Sir <hi>Henry, take her home and the Money with her, and then whereas other Cuckholds wear their Hornes plain, you may wear yours Guilt.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Injuries.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>INjuries</hi> of Evils preſent, are to be neglected for hopes of things to come. St. <hi>Cyprian.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>You muſt</hi> (ſaith St. <hi>Jerom</hi>) <hi>be a Dove and a Serpent, the one not to do hurt to others, the other not to be hurt by others.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="97" facs="tcp:152497:52"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>He knows not how to live, that kno<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> not how to bear Wrongs.</hi> David Chiterus.</p>
               <p>The Mercies and Forgiveneſs that I find and hope for, at the Lords hands, engageth and diſpoſeth me to forgive <hi>Injuries</hi> and <hi>Abuſes</hi> done to me: And I ſhould not think it much, that I, who am ſo ſinful, ſhould bear ſome Contumelies and Abuſes from Men. <hi>Corbet.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The more Men Wrong thee, the more watchfully maintain thy Love to them. <hi>Ibid.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>When that another hath ſpoken to thy Diſgrace, beware of a tranſport of Anger, that thou ſpeak not harſhly and unadviſedly againſt him, or too Paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onately, or as too much concerned for ſelf. <hi>Ibid. Vid.</hi> Wrongs.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Incarnation.</head>
               <p>TO believe the Incomprehenſible Miſtery of our Saviour's <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carnation,</hi> that the omnipotent Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:152497:53"/>Nature, and the weak Nature of Man are united in one Perſon of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> is ſure a very hard thing of Belief, and requires the expreſs Word of <hi>God</hi> to ſubmit to and captivate our Underſtandings, in Obedience to it, for the Union of the Divine Nature. <hi>Vid.</hi> John 1.1.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Idleneſs.</head>
               <p>HE is a Sluggard that would raign with <hi>God,</hi> and will not labor for <hi>God.</hi> In the promiſed Reward he takes delight, but the Commanded Combats affright him. <hi>Bead.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Ingratitude.</head>
               <p>ST. <hi>Auſtin</hi> called <hi>Ingratitude</hi> the <hi>Devils Spunge, whereby he wipes out all the favours of the Almighty.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="99" facs="tcp:152497:53"/>
               <head>Integrity.</head>
               <p>SAint <hi>Cyprian</hi> ſays, <hi>There can be no <hi>Integrity</hi> whereby they that ſhould Condemn the Wicked are ever wanting; and they only which ſhould be Condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, are ever preſent.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Judgment.</head>
               <p>SAint <hi>Jerom</hi> ſaid, <hi>Whatſoever he did he ſtill thought that that Voice was ſtill in his Ears, Ariſe ye Dead, and come to Judgment.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Intereſt.</head>
               <p>THey who leaſt conſider Hazard in the doing of their Duty, fare beſt ſtill: The ſureſt way to Safety is, to have one Intereſt eſpouſed firmly, as never to be changed.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="100" facs="tcp:152497:54"/>
               <head>KINGS.</head>
               <p>IT is a Maxim, that <hi>KINGS</hi> are like the Sun; and Uſurpers like Falling-Stars: for the Sun, tho' it be Effuſcated, or Eclipſed with Miſts and Clouds, yet at length becomes reful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent; whereas the others are but Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gures of Stars to the view, and prove no more than Exhalations, which ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dainly diſſolve and fall to the Earth, where they are conſumed.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt, Jeſus Chriſt</hi> is his Enemies <hi>King. Secondly,</hi> His Saints <hi>King. Thirdly,</hi> His Fathers King. The Firſt he Rules <hi>Over;</hi> the Second he Rules <hi>In;</hi> and the Third he Rules <hi>For.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Knowledge.</head>
               <p>ST. <hi>Baſil</hi> ſaid, <hi>To know thy ſelf is ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry difficult; for as the Eye can ſee all things but it ſelf; ſo ſome can di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcern all Faults but their own.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="101" facs="tcp:152497:54"/>
               <p>There is a common <hi>Knowledge,</hi> and there is a ſaving <hi>Knowledge,</hi> common <hi>Knowledge,</hi> is that which floats in the Head, but doth not Influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence and affect the Heart: This <hi>Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge</hi> Reprobates may have, <hi>Numb.</hi> 23.10. but then the ſaving <hi>Knowledge</hi> of <hi>God</hi> and <hi>Chriſt,</hi> which doth include the aſſent of the Mind, and conſent of the Will: This is <hi>Knowledge</hi> which im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plies Faith, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 5.8. <hi>By his Knowledge ſhall my Righteous Servant Juſtifie many.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For us to know, but to know, that's Curioſity; to know, to be known, that's Vain-Glory; but to know, to Practiſe what we know, that's Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel-Duty.</p>
               <p>He only knows <hi>GOD</hi> aright that knows how to Obey him; and Obeys according to his <hi>Knowledge</hi> of him, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 111.10. a good Underſtanding have all they that keep his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="102" facs="tcp:152497:55"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>Law of</hi> GOD.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>E<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſebius</hi> ſaith, <hi>That</hi> Moſes <hi>Wrote the</hi> Old Law <hi>in dead Tables of Stone; but</hi> Chriſt <hi>did write the lively and perfect Documents of the</hi> New Law, <hi>in Tables of the New-Teſtament, in liv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Souls.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>One Law Executed, is worth Twenty Made.</p>
               <p>No Laws, ſo no good could be done by a Governor that was not Abſolute, without either reſtraint or a Compe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titor. <hi>Machiavil.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Law and Equity have Two Courts, but Law and Equity ſhould dwell in one Breaſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Light Gold.</head>
               <p>THe Maſter of a Company affirm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, That they had a pair of Scales that would turn with the Two hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dredth
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:152497:55"/>part of a Grain: I ſhould be loath ſaid Mr. Attorney General <hi>Noy,</hi> ſtanding by, that all my Actions ſhould be weighed by thoſe Scales. We are all but <hi>Light Gold.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Liberty.</head>
               <p>A People accuſtomed to live under a Prince, if by accident they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come free, are like Beaſts let looſe, and have much ado either to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain their Government or their Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty. <hi>Machiavil.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Love.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>LOve</hi> is nothing but a diſpoſition of the Will, whereby it cleaves or makes forward to ſome good thing that is agreeable to it ſelf. <hi>Preſton.</hi> 216.</p>
               <p>St. <hi>Jerom</hi> uſed this excellent ſaying, <hi>If my Father ſtood Weeping on his Knees
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:152497:56"/>before me, and my Mother hanging on my Neck behind me, and all my Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, Siſters, Children, and Friends howling on every ſide, to retain me in a ſinful Life, I would run over my Father, fling my Mother to the Ground, deſpiſe my Kindred and fling them under my Feet, that I may run to</hi> CHRIST. Heres Love and Fortitude!</p>
               <p>St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> ſaith, <hi>Love is ſtrong as Death; as Death killeth the Body, ſo Love of Eternal Life kills Worldly De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires and Affections.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Love</hi> of <hi>Chriſt</hi> being predo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minant in the Soul, deadens the Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections to any thing elſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Chriſt</hi> asked <hi>Peter</hi> Three Times, <hi>Loveſt thou me,</hi> not for his own Infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, but that by his Threefold Profeſſion he might help his Three<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold Negation of him. <hi>Nicephorus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To Love <hi>God,</hi> and to be conforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to him, is that which I moſt of all deſire ſhould be in me. <hi>Corbet</hi>'s <hi>Enquiry.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="105" facs="tcp:152497:56"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>God</hi> will never Damn in Hell any Soul, that hath the habitual Predomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of the Love of <hi>God</hi> in his Soul, tho' culpable or otherwiſe ſinful whil'ſt remains ſuch; yea Hell and ſuch Love are inconſtant. <hi>Ibid.</hi> 30.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>I</hi> Love <hi>to</hi> Love <hi>GOD</hi> (ſays Mr. <hi>Corbet</hi>) <hi>and deſire this Love, not only as an evidence of my Salvation, but for it ſelf: I had much rather have an Heart to</hi> Love <hi>him perfectly, than to have all the Honors, Riches, and Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures of this World.</hi> Ib. 17.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Love</hi> to <hi>God</hi> is the Fountain and Spring of all true Obedience; moſt of the Hypocrites <hi>Love,</hi> empties it ſelf in Vain-Glory. <hi>Mat.</hi> 6.2, 5. <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 10.1.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>We know that we have paſſed from Death unto Life, becauſe we love the Brethren,</hi> John 3.14, 10. there we un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand <hi>Brethren by Grace, and not by Nature,</hi> or otherwiſe; to love <hi>God</hi> for Godlineſs ſake, the Saints for Saint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips ſake; this is a ſure Teſtimony of our Chriſtianity.</p>
               <pb n="106" facs="tcp:152497:57"/>
               <p>A Sinner cannot Love a Saint, <hi>Quatenus</hi> a Saint; neither can a Saint love a Sinner, <hi>Quatenus</hi> a Sinner. <hi>John</hi> 15.19. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 57.4.</p>
               <p>It is a true Rule, That Love is ever Rewarded, either in the Recipoque, or with an Inward or ſecret Contempt. Watch againſt all ſecret Pleaſure, in the leſſening of another for advancing of thy ſelf.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Divine Love</hi> (ſays <hi>Baſil</hi>) <hi>is a never failing Treaſure; he that hath it is Rich, and he that wanteth it is Poor.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Chriſoſtom</hi> ſaith, <hi>A Bulwark of A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damant is not more impregnable than the</hi> Love <hi>of Brethren.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>We can hardly ſpare time for <hi>God,</hi> becauſe we Love him too little; but we have abundance of ſpare time for our Idle Averſions, only becauſe we love them too much.</p>
               <p>Sir <hi>Thomas Howard</hi> was wont to ſay, <hi>That the leſs others ſet by him, the more he would ſet by himſelf.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>God</hi> makes his Love ſenſible to the
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:152497:57"/>faithful Soul, and ſaith to it, by the Preſence of his Spirit, <hi>Soul I am thy Salvation;</hi> and the Soul ſaith to him, <hi>Lord thou art my</hi> God, <hi>I am thine, ſave me, teach me to do thy Will:</hi> God Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muneth with the Soul, by his Word and Spirit, that is by Prayer and Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Meditations. <hi>Pe. Du Moulin.</hi> 39.</p>
               <p>All the Deliverances that <hi>God</hi> ſend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth his Children, all the Bleſſings that <hi>God</hi> poureth out upon them, they take them as Productions of the Fatherly love of <hi>God,</hi> who hath Adopted them in his Son; they taſte that love in the Enjoyments of preſent Goods; they breathe that love in hope of future and eternal Good; they reſt upon that love, when they ſleep; they reſt upon that love in the Occurrences of their Life, with what face ſoever the World looks upon them; they ſee thro' them the evident love of <hi>God,</hi> being certain that nothing happens to them but is directed by the good hand of their loving Father. <hi>Ib.</hi> 37.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="108" facs="tcp:152497:58"/>
               <head>Life to come.</head>
               <p>THe Life to come is bleſſed Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, certain Security, a ſecure Quietneſs, quiet Joyfulneſs, happy E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternity, and Eternal Felicity.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Lyes.</head>
               <p>A <hi>Lye,</hi> as <hi>Mountane</hi> ſaith, is only to brave it towards <hi>God,</hi> and to be a Coward towards Man; for a <hi>Lye</hi> faceth <hi>God,</hi> and ſhrinketh from Man.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Luſts.</head>
               <p>AS a great ſhower of Rain puts out the force of Fire, ſo Meditations of <hi>God</hi>'s Word puts out the Fire of Luſts in our Souls.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="109" facs="tcp:152497:58"/>
               <head>Maxims.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>VIdeo &amp; Rideo</hi> is <hi>God</hi>'s Motto on Affronts. <hi>Video &amp; tacio,</hi> was Queen <hi>Elizabeths.</hi> And <hi>Prudens qui Patiens,</hi> Sir <hi>Edward Cooks.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Melancholy.</head>
               <p>A Mind, in the dark of Melancholy and Trouble, feareth every thing.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Miſtakes in Divinity.</head>
               <p>THere will be <hi>Miſtakes</hi> in <hi>Divinity</hi> whil'ſt Men Preach: And <hi>Errors</hi> in <hi>Government</hi> whil'ſt ſuch Govern.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Mirth and Vanity.</head>
               <p>SIR <hi>Edward Fines</hi> would ſay, <hi>That he that would be Merry for a Day, let him be Trim'd; He that would be
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:152497:59"/>Merry for a Week, let him Marry: He that would be Merry for a Year, let him Build: And he that would be Merry for Ages, let him Improve his Land.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Marriage.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>HOly</hi> Marriage (ſays St. <hi>Auſtin</hi>) <hi>is better than proud Virginity.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Meekneſs.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>THeodoſius</hi> Senior, Commanded, <hi>That he that Reviled and ſpoke Evil of him ſhould not be Puniſhed, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe if it proceeded from levity, it is not to be regarded; if of Madneſs, it was to be pittied; if of Injury received, it is to be Pardoned in them.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="111" facs="tcp:152497:59"/>
               <head>Malice.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Origen</hi> ſaith, <hi>That Gods Providence hath ordered all things for ſome End or Purpoſe:</hi> He made not Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice, and tho' he can reſtrain it, yet he will not; for if <hi>Malice</hi> were not, <hi>Virtue</hi> ſhould not have a contrary, and ſo ſhould not ſhine ſo clear: For the Malice of <hi>Joſeph</hi>'s Brethren was the means whereby God brought ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny admirable works of his Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, as the Story ſheweth.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Maſs.</head>
               <p>AT <hi>Rome,</hi> ſaith <hi>Luther,</hi> I heard them ſay Maſs in ſuch a man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, as I deteſt them: For at the Communion Table, I heard Curteſans laugh and boaſt of their Wickedneſs. And others, concerning the Bread and Wine on the Altar, ſaying, <hi>Bread thou art, and Bread thou ſhalt remain:
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:152497:60"/>Wine thou art, and Wine thou ſhalt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Martyrdom.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>IGNATI<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S</hi> ſaid of his Tormen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, That the Lions Teeth are but like a Mill, for tho' it bruiſeth yet waſteth not the good Wheat, on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly prepares and fits it to be pure Bread: <hi>Let me</hi> (ſays he) <hi>be broken by them, ſo I may be a pure Manchet for Heaven.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Mr. <hi>Latimer</hi> being ready to be burnt, ſaid, <hi>God is faithful, that will not ſuffer us to be Tempted above that we are able,</hi> &amp;c. When the Fire was brought, he ſaid to Bp. <hi>Ridley, Be of good Comfort, Brother, and play the Man, we ſhall this day light ſuch a Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle by Gods Grace in</hi> England, <hi>I truſt ſhall never be put out.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Mr. <hi>John Philpot,</hi> in a Letter which he wrote to Mr. <hi>John Careles,</hi> then a Priſoner in the <hi>Kings-Bench,</hi> he thus
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:152497:60"/>writes, <hi>I am in this World in Hell, and in the ſhadow of Death, but he that for my deſerts hath brought me down into Hell, ſhall ſhortly lift me up into Heaven, where I ſhall continually look for your coming, and others of my faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Brethren in the</hi> King's-Bench. <hi>And tho' I tell you I am in Hell in the judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the World, yet I aſſuredly feel in the ſame, the Conſolation of Heaven: Praiſed be God, their loathſom and hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible Priſon is pleaſant to me.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Mercy.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>CHriſoſtom</hi> ſays, God had rather Men ſhould love him, than fear him; to be called Father, rather than Maſter: He wins by Mercy, that he may not periſh by Juſtice.</p>
               <p>Only a Godly Man knows how to make uſe of Mercies.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="114" facs="tcp:152497:61"/>
               <head>Neatneſs.</head>
               <p>SIr <hi>Edward Cook</hi> was wont to ſay, It is profitable to be <hi>Neat,</hi> that the outward Neatneſs of the Body may be a moniter of the purity of our Souls.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Negotiating.</head>
               <p>USE ſuch Perſons as affect the Buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs wherein they are to be Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy'd, for that quickneth much, and ſuch are fit for the matter: As bold Men for Expoſtulation; fair ſpoken Men for Perſuaſion; crafty Men for Enquiry, and Obſervation; Fro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward and Abſur'd Men for Buſineſs that doth not well bear out it ſelf: Uſe ſuch as have been Lucky, and prevailed before in things wherein you have employed them; for they
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:152497:61"/>will endeavour to maintain their Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription: It is better ſound a Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon with whom he deals a far off, than to fall on the Point at firſt, except you mean to ſurpriſe him by ſome ſhort Queſtion. <hi>Lord Bacon's Eſſays.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Nobility.</head>
               <p>NObility without Virtue is a Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grace; Virtue without Nobility is low; but Nobility adorned with Virtue, and Virtue embelliſhed by Nobility, raiſeth a Man as high as Nature reacheth; and he in whom theſe two Concur, have all the Glory a Man can attain unto (that is) both an inclination and a power to do well. <hi>In the Life of</hi> Francis Talbot, <hi>Earl of</hi> Shrewsbury.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="116" facs="tcp:152497:62"/>
               <head>Obedience.</head>
               <p>LET it be thy ſerious and fixed pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe every Morning (through the aſſiſtance of Grace) not willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly or knowingly to commit any Sin, or to do any thing, thy Conſcience ſhall tell thee is diſpleaſing to God; but if contrary to thy ſerious inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion through Infirmity, ſudden Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſal, violence of Temptation, or In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cogitancy, thou do'ſt at any time fall, humble thy ſelf before the Lord, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wail and confeſs thy Faults with ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row and grief, and ſpeedily recover thy ſelf by a ſerious Repentance, by flying to the Blood of Chriſt for Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don.</p>
               <p>Our Natures muſt be renued before the Command can be rightly obeyed, <hi>Mat.</hi> 7.18.</p>
               <p>Whatſoever a Mans performances are, they cannot be called Obedience
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:152497:62"/>whilſt the Heart remains unregene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate, becauſe the Principle is falſe and unſound: Every duty done by a Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liever is accepted of God, as part of his Obedience to the Will of God, tho' it be done in much weakneſs; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe, tho' the Believers hand is weak, yet his Heart is right; the Hypocrite may have the moſt active Hand, but the Believer hath the moſt faithful and ſincere Heart.</p>
               <p>Our applying to God, through Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt; <hi>(id eſt)</hi> our addreſs to the Father, through his Son (begetting in us a ſenſe of that Love which our Saviour had for us) cannot but kindle returns of Love ſuitable to it; and that muſt needs reform the inward Man; upon which, purity and holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Life, will certainly follow.</p>
               <pb n="118" facs="tcp:152497:63"/>
               <p>Right Obedience to Chriſt: Firſt, It muſt be Evangelical. 1ſt. For the Matter of it, <hi>Ye are my Friends, if ye do whatſoever I command you,</hi> John 15.14. 2ly. To the manner of it, according to what God requires of us: <hi>God is a Spirit, and they that wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip him, muſt worſhip him in Spirit and Truth,</hi> John 4.24. 3ly. The ground of it; <hi>This is a faithful ſaying, and worthy of all acceptation, that Chriſt Jeſus came into the World to ſave Sinners; of whom I am chief,</hi> 1 Tim. 1.15. Secondly, It is an Univerſal Obedience, <hi>Numb.</hi> 14.24. <hi>But thy ſervant</hi> Caleb, <hi>becauſe he hath another Spirit with him, and hath followed me fully; him will I bring into the Land,</hi> &amp;c. Pſal. 119.6. <hi>Then ſhall I not be aſhamed, when I have reſpect to all thy Commandments.</hi> Thirdly, It is a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinual Obedience, Pſal. 119.112. <hi>I have enclined my Heart to perform thy Statutes always, even unto the end.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="119" facs="tcp:152497:63"/>
               <p>God is never abſent, tho' the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked have him not in their Thoughts; where he is not by Favour, he is by Puniſhment and Terror. <hi>Greg. the Great.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Painting of Faces.</head>
               <p>THey that love to Paint themſelves in this World, otherwiſe than God hath made them, may juſtly fear, that at the Reſurrection, their Creator will not know them. <hi>Cyprian.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Paſſions.</head>
               <p>IT is the greateſt Slavery in the World, to be ſubject to ones own Paſſions. <hi>Juſtin Martyr.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="120" facs="tcp:152497:64"/>
               <head>Patience.</head>
               <p>OTher Graces are but the parts of a Chriſtians Armour, but <hi>Pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence</hi> is the whole Armour of the Man of God; the Enemy foils us without it, but we foil him with it, <hi>Ignatius.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>O that I could live</hi> (ſays Mr. <hi>Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bet) by Faith, in this time of Affliction; I endeavour to preſs upon my Soul thoſe Arguments which the Scripture affords with Patience, and Long-ſuffering, with Joyfulneſs; but this will not do the Work, except the Spirit of Faith and Patience be given from him, from whom comes down every good and perfect Gift: I do pray, I do cry to my Father, that he would give me the gracious Spirit, according to his Promiſes, that I may ſhew forth the Power of his Grace, and that I may not Diſhonour him.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A Soul patient when Wrongs are offered him, is like a Man with a
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:152497:64"/>Sword in one hand, and a Salve in the other; could wound, but will heal, <hi>Alexander of Hales.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Do not promiſe to thy ſelf that which God never promiſed thee. This heals the evils that ariſe from vain hopes, and cools the anger of thoſe Sores that are cauſed by fruſtration of our Expectations. It is lawful to deſire ſeveral things which are uncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, if God ſees them good for us; but let us not promiſe to our ſelves any of them. Do not entertain thy thoughts with promiſes of Content<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in ſuch a relation, in ſuch a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, nor ſucceſs in ſuch an Enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſe, no, tho' thou goeſt about it wiſely; but promiſe to thy ſelf par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don of Sin and Eternal Life, if thou do thy Duty, and the Grace of God to do it, if thou pray for it and wilt uſe it; for this our Merciful Father hath promiſed. And if we will hope for any thing, let it be (as I ſaid be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore) in the days of our Sorrow and
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:152497:65"/>Adverſity, to ſupport our Heavineſs; but not in the days of our Proſperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, to pleaſe our Fancies.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Parents.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>PArents</hi> ought to offer theſe things to their Children, as Inſtructions both in God's Word, and Human Arts, which preſerves them from Idleneſs and Folly, gives them Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, and learns them Subjection and Obedience to their Superiours. <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtin Martyr.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Peace.</head>
               <p>WHat will it avail thee to Diſpute ſoundly of the Trinity, if thou be void of Humility, and art thereby diſpleaſing to the Trinity: high Words ſurely never make a Man, neither Holy nor Juſt; but a Vertuous Life
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:152497:65"/>makes him dear to <hi>God:</hi> I deſire rather to feel Compunction, than to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand the Definition thereof. If thou doſt know the whole Bible, and the Sayings of all the Philoſophers by Heart, what would that profit thee, without the Word of <hi>God:</hi> Vanity of Vanity, all is Vanity; but to fear <hi>God,</hi> and him only, this is the higheſt Wiſdom, by contempt of the World, to attend the Kingdom of Heaven. It is Vanity then to tend after Periſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Riches, to hunt after Honors, to climb to high Dignities, and to labor after that, for which we afterwards ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer more grievous Puniſhments. Vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty it is to wiſh to live long, and care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſsly to live well. Vanity it is to mind only this preſent Life, and not to fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſee theſe things that are to come. Vanity it is to ſtay and ſet thy love on theſe fading and Periſhing things here below, and not to haſten thither where everlaſting Joy is permanent.</p>
               <pb n="124" facs="tcp:152497:66"/>
               <p>Call often to mind that Proverb, <hi>The Eye is not ſatisfied with ſeeing, nor the Ear with hearing;</hi> endeavor there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to withdraw thy Heart from theſe Viſible things, and turn thy ſelf to the Inviſible; for they that follow their Senſuality ſhame their own Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences, and loſe the favor of <hi>God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thou muſt labor to break thy Will in many things, if thou wilt have Peace and Concord with others. It is no ſmall thing to live in Chiſtian Communion. It is no ſmall thing to dwell in Religious Communion, and to converſe therein without Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint, and perſevere therein faithfully till Death. Bleſſed is he that hath then lived well, and perſevered there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in till Death.</p>
               <p>The Kingdom of <hi>God</hi> is within you, (ſaith the Lord) turn thee with thy whole Heart to <hi>God,</hi> and forſake this wretched World, and thy Soul ſhall find reſt. Learn to deſpiſe Exterior things, and to give thy ſelf Inferior,
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:152497:66"/>and thou ſhalt perceive the Kingdom of <hi>God</hi> to come into thee; for the Kingdom of <hi>God</hi> is Peace; and within, the Holy Ghoſt, which is not given to the Wicked: <hi>Chriſt</hi> will come unto thee, and ſhew thee his Conſolations, if thou prepare for him a worthy Manſion within thee: All his Beauty and Glory is within, and there he pleaſeth himſelf; the Inward Man he often Viſiteth, and hath with him ſweet Diſcourſes, much Solace, much Peace, and wonderful Familiarity.</p>
               <p>O faithful Soul, make ready thy Heart for this Bridegroom, that he may vouchſafe to come into thee, and dwell within thee: <hi>If any love me he will keep my Words,</hi> and we will come and make our Abode with him: Give therefore admittance to <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny entrance to all others. When thou haſt <hi>Chriſt,</hi> thou art Rich, and he will ſuffice thee; he will be thy faithful and provident Helper in all things, ſo that thou ſhalt not need to truſt in
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:152497:67"/>Men; for Men are quickly changed and quickly fall; but <hi>Chriſt</hi> remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth firm, and ſtandeth ſure unto the end.</p>
               <p>Bleſſed is he that underſtandeth what it is to love <hi>Jeſus:</hi> Thou ought'ſt to leave thy beloved Creature, which is not worthy of thy Heart, and ſet it on <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> who hath the only right to it: for if thou fix thy Love on the Creature thou wilt find it de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceitful, and to fail thee then when thou ſtandeſt in moſt need of help: whereas <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> will never fail thee of help at all times, but eſpecially when there's moſt need; who hath ſaid, <hi>I will never leave thee nor for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake thee.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I will hear what the Lord will ſpeak in me; Bleſſed is the Soul that hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth what the Lord ſpeaketh in her, and receiveth from his Mouth the Word of Comfort: Bleſſed are thoſe Ears that receive the ſound of the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Voice, and liſten not to the Voice
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:152497:67"/>of the World: Bleſſed are thoſe Ears which hearken not to the Voice that ſoundeth outwardly, but to the Truth that ſoundeth inwardly: Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed are thoſe Eyes that are ſhut to out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward things, and open to thoſe things that are Internal: Bleſſed are they that enter into the Inward Man, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavor to prepare themſelves more and more by daily Excellencies to the at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining of Heavenly Secrets: Bleſſed are they that delight to converſe with <hi>God,</hi> and rid themſelves of all Worldly Impediments. Conſider theſe things, O my Soul, and ſhut the door of thy ſenſual Deſires, that thou might'ſt hear what thy <hi>God</hi> ſaith unto thee. Whatſoever I can deſire or imagine for my Comfort, I look for it not here, but hereafter; for if I ſhould alone have all the Comforts of the World, after that his Maſter hath forgiven him Ten Thouſand Talents to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>give his Fellow Servant an Hundred Pence.</p>
               <pb n="128" facs="tcp:152497:68"/>
               <p>It is in vain to come to the God of of Peace, without Peace; or to Pray for the Remiſſion of our own Sins, without Forgiveneſs of others; we muſt not come to make an Attone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment with <hi>God,</hi> without Forgiveneſs of others; we muſt not come to make an Attonement with <hi>God</hi> at the Altar, before we have made Attone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment with our Brother in our Hearts.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>God</hi> giving us <hi>Peace</hi> and <hi>Content,</hi> we muſt give him <hi>Content,</hi> by Obey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him, or elſe we do not love him. A Man is well-pleaſed with Himſelf and his own Actions, when he doth that which his own Conſcience tells him he ought to do; and is then of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended with himſelf, when he goeth againſt the Light of his own Mind, neglecting his Duty, or doing that which is contrary to it. <hi>Tillotſon</hi> on <hi>Pſal.</hi> 159.156.</p>
               <p>O how good is it, and tending to <hi>Peace,</hi> to be ſilent of others Faults, and not to believe promiſcuouſly of them,
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:152497:68"/>all that's ſaid, nor eaſily to repeat what we have heard, to lay our ſelves open to Fear. <hi>De Kempis,</hi> 257.</p>
               <p>Uſe not Animoſity and Contention in any matter that may be brought to a good Iſſue, in the way of Peace. We are apt to hinder our Peace, by dreading and fearing thoſe Troubles it may be he never intended to bring upon us. <hi>Mr.</hi> Butler, <hi>our Miniſter.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>He that ſeeketh Liberty and Eaſe, ſhall ever live in Diſquiet; for one thing or other will diſpleaſe him. <hi>De Rempis,</hi> 82.</p>
               <p>As far as is lawful, let us become all things to all Men, that we may live in Peace and Quietneſs; And let's not, by a Tumultuous handling of any Matter, give them occaſion to oppoſe themſelves unto us.</p>
               <p>It is true, that to lift up our Hands pure unto <hi>God,</hi> we had need to waſh them in a better Innocency than our own; and the pureſt have need to be waſh'd in the Blood of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt.
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:152497:69"/>David</hi> himſelf having ſaid he would waſh himſelf in Innocency, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 36. And ſoon after, <hi>But as for me, I will walk in mine Integrity;</hi> Immediately upon that, to Redeem and have Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy upon him; yet <hi>God</hi> requires our Innocency, which he examines as a Gracious Father, not as a ſevere Judge. He looks more to the Sincerity of our Hearts, rather than the Perfection of our Actions, giving Peace to the Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitent Soul void of <hi>Hypocriſie, Pſal.</hi> 32.2, <hi>Bleſſed is the Man to whom the Lord imputeth not Iniquity; and in whoſe Spirit there is no Guile;</hi> that walk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth before him, knowing his Infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and together with Confidence, knowing <hi>God</hi>'s Mercy, and the cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty of his Promiſes. <hi>Peter Du Moulin,</hi> 65.</p>
               <p>Our Confidence in <hi>God,</hi> by the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of his Beloved Son, is the Ground of <hi>Peace</hi> and <hi>Content;</hi> but that Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence is fed by Works, we bear Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony by our Faith; as by the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiration,
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:152497:69"/>we know that a Man is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>live; ſo the exerciſe of Good Works, is together the Work of Faith, and the way to maintain the Spiritual Life.</p>
               <p>Doctor <hi>Edward Fox</hi> Diſcourſing one Day, (when Embaſſador of terms of Peace) he ſaid, <hi>Honourable ones laſt long, but Diſhonourable ones no longer than Kings have Power to break them: The ſureſt way therefore to Peace,</hi> ſaid he, <hi>is a conſtant preparedneſs for War.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The only Foundation of the Peace of the Soul, and contentment of Mind, is that Peace made for us, which <hi>God</hi> by his only Son <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> who hath taken our Sins upon himſelf, and in conſequence the Puniſhment; giving us in exchange his Righteouſneſs, and conſequently the Reward of it; ſince by it we appear Righteous before <hi>God.</hi> This is the Summary of the Goſpel; it is the only Comfort of the Faithful, that being Juſtified by Faith, we have Peace with <hi>God,</hi> through <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> our Lord. Without that Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſion,
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:152497:70"/>all the Moral Precepts, and all the Reaſons of <hi>Philoſophy,</hi> cannot ſet the Mind at reſt, much leſs the Riches, Honors, Pleaſures, and Paſtimes of this World: for who can have Peace with himſelf, whil'ſt he is in Diſſention with <hi>God;</hi> and who can have Peace with <hi>God,</hi> but by the Mediation of his Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved Son, <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> there being no other Name, under <hi>Heaven,</hi> by which we muſt be Saved.</p>
               <p>What tho' my Sins be great; yet they are leſs than the Merit of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt;</hi> no Sin ſo great that it ought to take away the Confidence of <hi>God</hi>'s Promiſes; no Sin ſo great that it may Damn a Soul beaten down with Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trition, but together raiſed by Faith, and waſh'd in the Blood of the Son of <hi>God:</hi> Indeed the remembrance of my Sins muſt be bitter unto me; yet that Bitterneſs muſt be Drowned in the Joy of Salvation, and my Repentance muſt be a ſtep, and not an hindrance to my Confidence: And to maintain
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:152497:70"/>this Peace, we muſt firſt make it our earneſt task to make our ſelves ſure of our Peace with <hi>God,</hi> by a lively Faith, whereby our Hearts may be Purified from Evil Works, and made Fertile in all Fruits of Holineſs; for hereby we ſhall have Peace with our ſelves, and ſhall be Maſters at home: Alſo this Peace with <hi>God,</hi> brings Peace with our Neighbour; for he that hath a Comfortable feeling in his own Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, that <hi>God</hi> is reconciled with him, will eaſily be reconciled with his Brethren, holding it a point of E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity, Generoſity, and Gratefulneſs, after that his Maſter hath forgiven him <hi>Ten Thouſand Talents, to forgive his Fellow Servant an Hundred Pence.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Perfection.</head>
               <p>AS to the ſtrict, abſolute, and legal knowledge of <hi>Perfection,</hi> ſo there is none perfect in this Life: for as <hi>Prov.</hi> 20.9. <hi>Who can ſay, I have
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:152497:71"/>made my Heart clean and pure from my Sin:</hi> In this ſence there never was in the Earth one perfect Man except <hi>Adam,</hi> before his Fall, and that Man <hi>Chriſt Jeſus:</hi> But then there is an E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vangelical Perfection, that ſpeaks Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection in a qualified and Goſpel ſence; and thus every good Man is a Perfect Man, even whil'ſt he is here upon Earth: Take this in Five things, 1. He is Perfect as to his Juſtification, in the firſt moment of a Sinners Believ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, 2. He is perfectly Juſtified, 3. His Sins being fully Pardoned, 4. His Guilt fully Expiated, 5. His Perſon made com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleatly and perfectly Righteous, thro' the Imputation of <hi>Chriſt</hi>'s perfect Righteouſneſs, imputed unto him (for he that hath perfect Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs upon him, hath perfect Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs.) Sanctification is a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſive Act, that goeth on by little and little, ſtep by ſtep, by degrees: But Juſtification is of a different Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, that is a continued, but not a
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:152497:71"/>Progreſſive Act: We are not Sanctifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed all at once, but are Juſtified all at once; and all the Succeſſive Pardons that we have for Sin, are but the ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect of one continued Juſtification, as that is particularly applyed and drawn forth. Juſtification is, <hi>Simul &amp; ſemel,</hi> altogether at once, as the Schools ſpeak.</p>
               <p>Little Grace is perfect, in as much as it is continually growing up to Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.22. <hi>Prov.</hi> 4.18. Dr. <hi>Jacomb.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Spencer Compton,</hi> Brother to the Right Honourable the Earl of <hi>Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thampton,</hi> calling to himſelf Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend Perſons, as Biſhop <hi>Morley,</hi> and Dr. <hi>Earls,</hi> when he was on his Death-Bed at <hi>Bruges,</hi> he raiſed himſelf on his Pillow, and held forth his Hands, as tho' he were embracing one, ſaying, <hi>O my Jeſus!</hi> Intimating the Comforts that flowed in and from the Holy Jeſus into his Soul. After which ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Extaſie, compoſing himſelf to a
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:152497:72"/>calm and ſerious Diſcourſe, he ſaid to the Standers by, <hi>O! do good, and keep cloſe to the Principles of the Chriſtian Religion.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Publick Good.</head>
               <p>SIR <hi>John Fines</hi> ſaid, <hi>He is High that ſerves a Princes private In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt:</hi> He is always ſo, that is Care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful of the Publick Good.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Parents and Children.</head>
               <p>THree things there are (was Sir <hi>Anthony Cook</hi>'s ſaying) before whom I cannot do amiſs. 1. <hi>My Prince.</hi> 2. <hi>My Conſcience.</hi> 3. <hi>My Children. Seneca</hi> told his Siſter, <hi>That he could not leave her a great Portion, but he could leave her a good Pattern.</hi> Sir <hi>Anthony</hi> would write to his Daughter <hi>Mildred, My Example is your Inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, and my Life is your Portion.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="137" facs="tcp:152497:72"/>
               <head>Prophecy.</head>
               <p>HE that will ſee what ſhall be, let him conſider what hath been: As Sir <hi>Richard Weſton</hi> ſaid, <hi>There is the ſame deſires of Honour and Intereſt in every Age, that were before it.</hi> So that, as <hi>Machivel</hi> obſerves, <hi>It is very eaſie with him that uſeth Diligence, and examineth paſt Occurrances, to ſerve him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf of thoſe Remedies which were in uſe among the Ancients; or if they fail, to deviſe what is moſt like them.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Perſeverance.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>EPhraim Sims</hi> ſays, <hi>That the reſolute Traveller knows his Journey to be Long, and the Way Dirty; yet goes on in hopes to come to his Houſe.</hi> So let a Chriſtian, tho' the way to Heaven be narrow, tho' it be ſet with Trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles and Perſecutions, yet let him go
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:152497:73"/>on till he hath finiſhed his Courſe with Joy, for Heaven is his Home.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Pleaſures.</head>
               <p>WE muſt deal with <hi>Pleaſures,</hi> as we do with Hony; only touch it with the tip of the Finger, not with the whole Hand, for fear of a Surfeit. <hi>Bead.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Poverty Spiritual.</head>
               <p>HE is poor whoſe Soul is void of Grace, and not whoſe Coffers are empty of Money: Contented Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verty is true Riches. <hi>Greg. the Great.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Proſperity.</head>
               <p>SIR <hi>John Fineux</hi> ſaid, <hi>That no Man Thrived, but he that Lived as if he were the Firſt Man in the World, and
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:152497:73"/>that his Father was not Born before him.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Protection.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>DEfend me</hi> (ſaid <hi>Luther</hi> to the Duke of <hi>Saxony) with your Sword, and I will Defend you with my Pen. Maintain my Power</hi> (ſays the Miniſter of State to his Soveraign) <hi>and I will Support your Majeſty.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Proteſtant and Papiſt.</head>
               <p>SIR <hi>Henry Wotton,</hi> being in a Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh Chappel, a Merry Papiſt that knew him, ſent a Paper to him with this Queſtion: <hi>Where was your Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on before</hi> Luther? Under which he writ, <hi>Where yours is not; that is, in the Written Word of God.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="140" facs="tcp:152497:74"/>
               <head>Preaching and Preachers.</head>
               <p>SIR <hi>Auguſtine Nicols,</hi> loved plain and profitable Preaching, being wont to ſay, <hi>I know not what you call Preaching, but I like them that come neareſt my Conſcience.</hi> The Speech of <hi>Julius Caeſar</hi> is commonly known: <hi>Oportet eim parutarem ſtantem mori.</hi> Which Biſhop <hi>Jewel</hi> alter'd, and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply'd to himſelf; <hi>Decet Epiſcopum con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cionantem ſtantem mori.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Pilgrim.</head>
               <p>A Chriſtian at home in his Houſe, muſt think himſelf a Stranger; and that his Country is above, where there be no Strangers. <hi>Auſtin.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="141" facs="tcp:152497:74"/>
               <head>Providence.</head>
               <p>REmember always that God Rules the World, and thoſe things that are Accidents with us, are <hi>Providence</hi> with Him; and let this quiet thy Heart.</p>
               <p>The Earl of <hi>Arundel,</hi> when the reſt of the Council were for the Dealing with the Queen of <hi>Scots</hi> underhand at a diſtance, he was to Deal with her plainly, and ſaid to the Queen: <hi>The Wiſdom of the former Age was ſo</hi> Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vident, <hi>that it needed not; and ſo plain, that it admitted not</hi> Shifts.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Peter Lumbard</hi> ſaid, <hi>The inſtruction of Words, is not ſo Powerful as the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortation of Works; for if they which Teach well neglect to do well, they ſhall hardly profit their Auditors.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That in a great number of People of ſeveral Ages and Conditions (who are like an Harp with many Strings) it is hard to give every one ſuch a
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:152497:75"/>Touch, as may pleaſe all, and offend none. <hi>Nazianſen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Preaching.</head>
               <p>LET none Glory in the Gift of Preaching, in that they Edifie more by them; for they are not Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors of Grace, but Miniſters.</p>
               <p>It is hard to be Serious in hearing him, whom I think is not Serious in himſelf who Preacheth it; if I ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend he Trifles, it is a great Temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation to me to do ſo too.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Pride.</head>
               <p>REmember that they that <hi>Pride</hi> themſelves in Silk Apparel, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not lightly put on the Holy Jeſus Chriſt. <hi>Cyprian.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thou boaſteſt thy ſelf of thy Wealth, Honour, Strength, Beautiy; conſider what thou art by Sin, and
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:152497:75"/>what thou ſhalt be in the Grave, and thy Plumes will fall; for every Proud Man forgets himſelf.</p>
               <p>He that begins to grow Better, let him beware leaſt he grow <hi>Proud;</hi> leaſt Vain-glory give him a greater over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw than his former Vices. <hi>Iſedore.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To be Content, have a little E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteem of thy ſelf: <hi>Superbus &amp; aracus nunquam quieſcunt:</hi> No Man Whiſpers, but a <hi>Proud</hi> Man is diſturbed; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as the obſervance of this Rule, will make us ſay when we are Contemned and Diſpiſed, that they cannot think ſo low of us, as we of our ſelves, and then we ſhall not be moved: It will help us in Poverty, Sickneſs, and all Misfortunes, whilſt we ſay leſs than the leaſt of God's Mercies.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Prayer.</head>
               <p>THat <hi>Prayer</hi> that is pure and holy, entereth into the Heavens, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turneth not empty: It is a ſhelter to
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:152497:76"/>the Soul, a Sacrifice to God, and a Scourge to the Devil.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Auſtin</hi>'s Prayer was, <hi>Lord, firſt give me what thou requireſt, and then require what thou wilt.</hi> And he that Prayeth well, cannot chooſe but Live well.</p>
               <p>Mr. <hi>Perkins,</hi> upon his Death-Bed, ſaid to his Friends, praying for the eaſe of his Pain, <hi>Pray not for the eaſe of Torments, but for the encreaſe of my Patience.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>He that Prays for the good Things that he hath not, doth not ſeek for that which is good, but that which ſeems to be good.</p>
               <p>Oh! what do I inwardly ſuffer, when in my Mind I conſider Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly Things; and preſently in my Prayers, a multitude of Carnal Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginations preſent themſelves before me. My God, be not far from me; depart not in thy Wrath from thy Servant; caſt forth thy Light and ſcatter them; ſend forth thy Darts,
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:152497:76"/>and break all the Imaginations which the Enemy caſts in: Gather in, call home my Senſes unto thee, make me forget all the things of this World; grant me to caſt away ſpeedily the imaginations of Wickedneſs. Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cour thou me, thou everlaſting Truth, that no Vanity may move me; come Heavenly Sweetneſs, and let Impuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty fly from before thee: Pardon me alſo, and mercifully forgive me, as often as I think of any thing elſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides thee in Prayer. I do humbly confeſs I am wont to be ſubject to many Diſtractions, for I confeſs I am not there where I do corporally ſtand or ſit, but there am I, whither my Thoughts do carry me; where my Thoughts are, there am I. There are oftentimes my Thoughts where my Affections are, that offer themſelves quickly unto me, which is naturally delightful, and by cuſtom pleaſing. <hi>Tho. de Kempis,</hi> 268.</p>
               <pb n="146" facs="tcp:152497:77"/>
               <p>If thou be in God, Chriſt is thy Father; and therefore in Prayer, thy Applications are to thy Father, <hi>Mat.</hi> 7.7.</p>
               <p>If we being evil, know how to give good things, whatſoever thou canſt expect from thy Earthly Father; ſo much, and much more, may'ſt thou ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect from thy Heavenly Father, pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to bear with thy Infirmities and Failings, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 78.18. compaſſion to pity thy Sufferings, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 103. Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to ſupply thy Wants, Juſtice to revenge thy Injuries, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 105.14.</p>
               <p>Thoſe Prayers that are from the workings and ſighings of God's Spirit in us, from ſincere Hearts lifted up to God, through the ſenſe of our own Emptineſs, and from God's infinite Fulneſs, that are ſuited to God's Will, and the great Rule of Prayer, that are for Spiritual things more than Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral, that are accompanied with Faith and dependance; theſe Prayers ſpeak a Man altogether a Chriſtian. <hi>Mead.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="147" facs="tcp:152497:77"/>
               <head>A Prayer for Purging the Heart, and for obtaining Heavenly Wiſdom.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>STrengthen me, O God, by the Grace of thy holy Spirit; give me to be ſtrengthened in the inward Man, and to empty my ſelf of all unprofitable Care and Anguiſh, not to be drawn away by ſundry deſires, either mean or precious, but looking upon all things as paſſing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way together with them; for nothing is permanent under the Sun, where all things are vanity and vexation of Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit;</hi> Oh, how wiſe is he that conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dereth of them! <hi>Tho. de Kempis,</hi> 112.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A Powerful Letter.</head>
               <p>IN a Letter to King <hi>Henry</hi> the VIII. it is concluded thus: Wherefore Gracious King, have pity on your
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:152497:78"/>Soul, and conſider that the Day is e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven at hand, when you ſhall give an Account of your Office, and the Blood that hath been ſhed with your Sword. In which day, that you Grace may ſtand ſtedfaſt, and may have your <hi>Quietus eſt</hi> ſealed with the Blood of our Saviour Jeſus Chriſt, which will only ſerve at that day; is my daily Prayer, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Our Perſecutors.</head>
               <p>FRet, Fume, and Gnaſh the Teeth, to hear that we under theſe grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous Afflictions, can be ſo Merry; let us Pray inſtantly, that this Joy may never be taken from us, for it paſſeth the Delights of this World: <hi>This is the Peace which paſſeth all <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding.</hi> This Peace, the more it is choſen, and poſſeſſed with, the more they feel it; and therefore cannot faint, neither by Fire nor Water.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="149" facs="tcp:152497:78"/>
               <head>Proſperity.</head>
               <p>HEre lies the danger of a pleaſing Condition, in regard of Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, Credit, Delights, Riches, Friends, Habitation, Health, or any inferiour thing, the more of Good that ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth to be in them, (as diſtinct from God) the more Dangerous; for they are more like to ſtand up in Competi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion with him, and carry it with our partial and blinded Souls in the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petition. Remember this, if you love your ſelves, when you would have all things about you more Pleaſant and Lovely, here lies the danger of a proſperous Condition and State. On the contrary, here lies the bleſſed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit of Adverſity, which if Men were not Brutiſh and Unbelieving, they would heartily welcome it as the ſureſt Condition. Mr. <hi>Baxters Reſt</hi> 3d <hi>Part,</hi> 216.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="150" facs="tcp:152497:79"/>
               <head>Papiſt.</head>
               <p>MY Lord of <hi>Worceſter</hi> (being a <hi>Papiſt</hi>) had this Maxim, <hi>That he would not be Diſordered within him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf; only becauſe things were out of Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der without him.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> was wont to ſay, <hi>That my Lord of</hi> Worceſter <hi>had Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciled what ſhe thought Inconſiſtent; A ſtiff Papiſt to be a good Subject.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Puniſhment.</head>
               <p>WHenſoever God Puniſheth, he doth it for juſt Cauſe, and the Godly never accuſe him of Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gour as the Wicked do; but acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, that in themſelves is juſt cauſe why they ſhould thus intreat them, <hi>Dan.</hi> 9.7. <hi>Why ſhould a Living Man complain, for the Puniſhment of his Sins.</hi> Hale, 130.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="151" facs="tcp:152497:79"/>
               <head>Reaſon.</head>
               <p>IT's Human to uſe <hi>Reaſon</hi> rather than Force; and a Chriſtian to ſeek Peace and enſue it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Reformation.</head>
               <p>IT would be an eaſie matter (ſays <hi>Malvezzi</hi>) for Favourites to Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form Kings Palaces, if it were not an hard thing to Reform their own Houſes.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Regiment of Health.</head>
               <p>TO be chearfully diſpoſed at Hours of Meat, Sleep, and Exerciſe, is one of the beſt Exerciſes of long laſting: As for the paſſions and ſtud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies of the Mind, avoid Envies, Anxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:152497:80"/>Fears, Anger, fretting Inward, ſubtile and knotty Inquiſitions, Joys and Exhilerations in Exceſs, Sadneſs not Communicated; entertain Hopes and Mirth, rather than Joy; variety of Delights, rather than Surfeit on them. <hi>Lord</hi> Bacon<hi>'s Eſſays,</hi> 188.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Rejoycing at Death.</head>
               <p>MR. <hi>Edward Deering</hi> ſaid, <hi>As for my Death, I bleſs</hi> God <hi>I feel and find ſo much inward Joy and Comfort in my Soul, that if I were to make my Choice, whether to Live or Die, I would a Thouſand times rather chooſe Death than Life, if it may ſtand with the good Will of</hi> God: And ſhortly after he Died, in the Year of our Lord <hi>Chriſt,</hi> 1576.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="153" facs="tcp:152497:80"/>
               <head>Religion.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>REligion,</hi> and the Practice of its Vertues, is the Natural ſtate of the Soul, the condition to which <hi>God</hi> deſigned it: As <hi>God</hi> made Man a reaſonable Creature, ſo all the Acts of Religion, are equal and ſuitable to our Natures, and our Souls are then in Health, when we are what the Laws of Religion require to be, and to do what they Command us to do. Dr. <hi>Tillotſon.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The great Principals of <hi>Religion,</hi> are, <hi>Knowledge, Faith, Remembrance, Love,</hi> and <hi>Fear;</hi> by all which, the Scriptures expreſs the <hi>Whole Duty of Man:</hi> Now, why theſe are put for the whole of Religion, is, Becauſe <hi>Remembrance, Love,</hi> and the <hi>Fear</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> are ſuch Powerful Inſtruments for to make them Religious, that where any one of theſe really is, all the reſt, together
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:152497:81"/>with the true and genuine Effects, are ſuppoſed to be.</p>
               <p>The Earl of <hi>Leiceſter,</hi> in Queen <hi>Mary</hi>'s Days, although allowing him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf in ſome things very inconſiſtent with Religion, came at laſt to this Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution: <hi>That Man differed not from Beaſts, ſo much in Reaſon, as in Religion, and that Religion was the higheſt Reaſon; nothing being more Rational, than for the ſupream Truth to be Believed; the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Good to be Embraced; the firſt cauſe and Almighty Maker of all things to be Owned and Feared; and for thoſe that were made by</hi> God, <hi>and live wholly upon him, to Improve all for him, and live wholly to him, according to the Apoſtle,</hi> Give up your Souls and Bodies to him, which is your reaſonable Service.</p>
               <p>It is a great Deceit to meaſure the Subſtance of our Religion by the Bulk of our Profeſſion; and to judge of the ſtrength of our Graces, by the length of our Duties. The Scripture ſpeaks of ſome that <hi>having a form of Godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:152497:81"/>deny the Power;</hi> that is, do not live in the Practiſe of thoſe Graces they pretend unto in their Duties.</p>
               <p>He that pretends to Godlineſs, by a ſpecious Profeſſion, and yet doth not Practiſe Godlineſs by an Holy Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation, he hath the <hi>form of Godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, but denies the Power,</hi> 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.5.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Repentance.</head>
               <p>IF thou be backward in thoughts of <hi>Repentance,</hi> be forward in the thoughts of <hi>Hell;</hi> the burning Flames whereof, only the Tears of a Penitent Eye can extinguiſh. <hi>Tertullian.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>When Gold is offered to thee, thou uſeſt not to ſay, <hi>I will come again to Morrow and take it,</hi> but art glad at the preſent Poſſeſſion; but Salvation being offered to our Souls, few Men haſt to embrace it. <hi>Ambroſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Remember that <hi>God</hi> promiſed For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giveneſs to Repentant Sinners; yet
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:152497:82"/>he doth not promiſe that he ſhall have time till to Morrow to Repent. <hi>Aquinas.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Mr. <hi>Corbet</hi> was wont to ſay, <hi>That upon the beſt Judgment I can make of the Nature of Sin, the frame of mine own Heart, and courſe of Life; I know no Sin lying upon me, which doth not conſiſt with Natural Repentance, and with the hatred of Sin, and with an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feigned conſent, That</hi> God <hi>be my Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our and Sanctifier, and with the loving of</hi> God <hi>above all.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>I have done what in me lies to call to remembrance all my remarkable Sins, from my Childhood and Youth till now; and, as far as I can judge, I have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pented of them generally and particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly, and now repent of them all, from the bottom of my Heart, with a ſelf Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horrency, if I know my own Heart, and by the ſtricteſt and moſt Impartial ſearch that I can make.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>What profit can it be to thee, to bewail that Sin which thou wilt not
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:152497:82"/>forego? What Reward can'ſt thou ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect for that Obedience which ſo ſoon fainteth? What Comfort in that Joy that is but Temporary? <hi>Vid. Sorrow.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Righteouſneſs.</head>
               <p>THe <hi>Righteous</hi> doth follow the Lamb, becauſe they are waſhed in the <hi>Blood of the Lamb, Rev.</hi> 1.1.17.14. 1 <hi>John</hi> 17. for as ſoon as we are united with <hi>Chriſt,</hi> our Sins are upon him, and his Righteouſneſs upon us, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Dier 153. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 61.10. <hi>That he may preſent to himſelf a glorious Church,</hi> Eph. 5.21.</p>
               <p>There is but one Sun in the World, and but one Righteouſneſs, and one Communion of Saints: If I were the moſt Excellent of all Creatures in the World: If I were equal too in Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs to <hi>Moſes, Iſaac,</hi> and <hi>Jacob,</hi> yet had I reaſon to confeſs my ſelf a Sinner, and that I could expect no
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:152497:83"/>Salvation but by the Righteouſneſs of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt;</hi> for we all ſtand in need of the Grace of <hi>GOD.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>I would fulfil all</hi> Righteouſneſs (ſays Mr. <hi>Corbet) and owe nothing to any Man but Love: I had rather an hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred-fold ſuffer Wrong, than do Wrong.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As <hi>Baptiſm</hi> is ſaid to ſave us, ſo o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Duties too, our <hi>Righteouſneſs,</hi> which the Law of Works requires, and by which it is ſatisfied, is wholly in <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and not one grain in our ſelves; nor muſt we dare to think of patching a Legal <hi>Righteouſneſs</hi> of <hi>Chriſt</hi>'s and our own together; that is, that our Doings can be the leaſt Satisfaction for our Sins or proper Merit; yet our ſelves muſt perfectly fulfil the Conditions of the New Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, and ſo have a Perſonal Evan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelical Righteouſneſs. <hi>Baxter</hi>'s <hi>Reſt.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="159" facs="tcp:152497:83"/>
               <head>Revenge.</head>
               <p>COnſider how you daily wrong <hi>God,</hi> and you will not be eaſily en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flamed with Revenge againſt others that have wronged you.</p>
               <p>Keep down thy Heart by this Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration, that by Revenge thou can'ſt not ſatisfie a Luſt; but by Forgive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, thou can'ſt Conquer a Luſt. <hi>Flavel,</hi> 123.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Reſignation.</head>
               <p>I Will Truſt <hi>God</hi> in his Way; I will ſtrive againſt an over-timerous Solicitation for my Salvation, and will commit my ſelf to <hi>God,</hi> who is the Infinite Goodneſs and Love, and I will lye down and take my Repoſe therein. <hi>Mr.</hi> Corbet<hi>'s Enquiry.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="160" facs="tcp:152497:84"/>
               <p>I will labor in the Work of Reſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, that my Will may be confined to, and included in the Will of <hi>God. Ibid.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It will never be well with us, till we Cordially reſign up our ſelves, and all our Relations; yea, and all our Intereſts and Concerns to <hi>God</hi>'s diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, and ſay, <hi>Not my Will, but thy Will be done.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Lay thy Heart to reſt in the Will of <hi>God,</hi> for there is no other reſt for the Soul to be thought of.</p>
               <p>It is not fit or likely, that our Wills ſhould be the Rule of <hi>GOD</hi>'s Actions.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Reward.</head>
               <p>MY <hi>Alms-Deeds</hi> ſhall be Graciouſly <hi>Rewarded,</hi> not for my Works ſake, but for thy Promiſe ſake; not for my own ſake, but for my Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our's ſake: Lord, I can Merit nothing
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:152497:84"/>at thy hands, but by thy own Mercy. <hi>Vid. Tit.</hi> Faſting.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Riches.</head>
               <p>OF <hi>Riches,</hi> there is no real uſe, unleſs it be in the diſtribution, the reſt is but Conceit: ſo ſaith <hi>Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon,</hi> where much is, there are many to conſume it; and what hath the Owner but the ſight of it with his Eyes. <hi>Lord</hi> Bacon.</p>
               <p>Remember that thou haſt nothing of thy own, but all is the Lords, and ſo accordingly uſe all thou haſt to no Carnal Intereſt, but to ſerve him, as being wholly Devoted to him.</p>
               <p>I made it my choice, rather to be Poor here, and Rich in the Life to come, than to be Rich here, and Loſt in the Life to come.</p>
               <p>As a Boat over-laden ſinks, ſo much Wealth drowns a Man in Perdition. <hi>Chryſoſtome.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="162" facs="tcp:152497:85"/>
               <p>If a Man wants Wealth, it is not to be unjuſtly gotten: If they have it, they ought by Good Works to lay it up in <hi>Heaven. Auſtin.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Mr. <hi>Bradford</hi> anſwered <hi>Gardiner,</hi> concerning the Sacrament, <hi>My Lord, I do not believe that</hi> Chriſt <hi>is Corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally preſent in the Sacrament, but that he is preſent there to the Faith of the due receiver.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Satisfaction.</head>
               <p>WE are every where in Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture ſaid to be <hi>Ranſomed, Redeemed, Purchaſed, Bought with a Price;</hi> and that muſt needs be by a valuable Conſideration made. <hi>Juſtification Evangelical,</hi> 88. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.18, 19.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="163" facs="tcp:152497:85"/>
               <head>Scripture.</head>
               <p>WHen the <hi>Scripture</hi> wants a Tongue of Expreſſion, we need not an Ear of Attention; we may ſafely knock at the Council Door of <hi>God</hi>'s Secrets; but if we go further, we may be more Bold than Welcome. <hi>Cyril</hi> of <hi>Alexandria.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Baſil,</hi> when he had read the Bible over, he ſaid, <hi>It was a Phyſician's Shop of Preſervatives againſt Poyſonous He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſies; a Pattern of profitable Laws againſt Rebellious Spirits; a Treaſure of moſt profitable Jewels againſt Beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garly Elements; and a Fountain of moſt pure Water, ſpringing to Eternal Life.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Sanctification.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sanctification,</hi> and the <hi>New-Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,</hi> are no leſs than for a Man to be brought into an Intire Reſignation
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:152497:86"/>of his Will, to the Will of <hi>God,</hi> and to live in the offering up his Soul con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually in the Flames of Love, a whole Burnt-Offering to <hi>Chriſt:</hi> And how little, ſays he, are many of thoſe who profeſs Chriſtianity, experimentally acquainted with this Work on their Souls. <hi>Biſhop</hi> Uſher.</p>
               <p>The Work of <hi>Sanctification,</hi> that is true and effectual, is a Work of the Spirit of <hi>God</hi> on the Soul, enabling it to the Mortification of all Sin, and to the Obeying of every Command to work with <hi>God</hi> in all well-pleaſing. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.13. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.2. <hi>Heb.</hi> 23. Mead.</p>
               <p>There is an Inward and an outward <hi>Sanctification;</hi> Inward <hi>Sanctification</hi> is that which deals with the Soul and its Faculties, as Underſtanding, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, Memory and Affections. Out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward <hi>Sanctification</hi> is that which deals with the Life and Converſation; both theſe concur to make a Chriſtian in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed. <hi>Theſ.</hi> 5.23.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="165" facs="tcp:152497:86"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>The Sacrament of the Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy and Blood of</hi> Jeſus Chriſt.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>This is my Body,</hi> by the Word <hi>[This]</hi> our Saviour meant, <hi>This Bread,</hi> is Infinitely plain to any that is unprejudiced. What did he take? the Text tells you, he took <hi>[Bread:]</hi> What he took, he alſo Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, Broke, and Gave <hi>[This;]</hi> he ſaid, <hi>Take, Eat,</hi> and then adds, <hi>[This] is my Body;</hi> this will be put out of doubt, if by the following <hi>[This,]</hi> in thoſe Words <hi>[This is my Blood,]</hi> by <hi>[This]</hi> be meant <hi>[This Cup,]</hi> no reaſon can be aſſigned why <hi>[This]</hi> in <hi>Mat.</hi> 26.26. ſhould not denote <hi>[This Cup,]</hi> if <hi>[This]</hi> ver. 28. denote <hi>[This Cup:]</hi> It is true, that St. <hi>Matthew</hi> and St. <hi>Mark,</hi> having mentioned the <hi>[Cup,]</hi> which <hi>Jeſus</hi> Took, Bleſſed, and Gave, tell us, that
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:152497:87"/>
                  <hi>Jeſus</hi> ſaid, <hi>[This is my Blood;]</hi> and tho' it be plain, from what goes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, that by <hi>[This]</hi> be meant <hi>[This Cup:]</hi> Yet we have further proof of it ſtill; for, whereas St. <hi>Matthew</hi> and <hi>Mark</hi> ſay only <hi>[This,]</hi> St. <hi>Luke</hi> and St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſay, <hi>[This Cup,]</hi> and having this Warrant for <hi>[This]</hi> in the latter words to underſtand <hi>[This Cup,]</hi> where lies the Blame, when by the former <hi>[This Bread.]</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But I proceed, This Verb <hi>[IS]</hi> is Interpretable according to the ſubject Matter; but where it is uſed of a Sacrament, and joyns the ſign, and the thing ſignified together; and where another ſence contended for is deſtructive to our Senſes, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Reaſon and other Scripture, 'tis reaſonable to underſtand it to Import the ſame with the Word <hi>Sig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie,</hi> and this is the preſent Caſe. There are many more Reaſons, but what hath been here ſaid may ſatisfie any unprejudiced Perſon.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="167" facs="tcp:152497:87"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>Of the Real Preſence ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged by</hi> Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants <hi>in the Holy Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament, made appear by a plain and familiar Example,</hi> viz.</head>
               <p>A Father makes his laſt Will, and by it bequeatheth his Eſtate, and all the Profits of it to his Child. He delivers it into the hands of his Son, and bids him to take there his Houſe and Lands, by this his laſt Will he delivers to him. The Son in this caſe receives nothing but a Roll of Parchment, with a Seal to it from his Father: But yet by vertue of this Parchment, he is Intitled to his Eſtate, performing the Condition of his Will, and to all the Benefits and Advantages
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:152497:88"/>of it. And in that Deed, he truly and effectually received the very Houſe and Lands that were conveyed to him.</p>
               <p>Our Saviour Chriſt, in like manner, being now about to leave the World, gives this holy Sacrament as a final Bequeſt to us, in it he conveys to us a right to his Body and Blood, and to all the Spiritual Bleſſings and Graces that proceed from them. So that as we receive the holy Euchariſt as we ought to do, we receive nothing but a little Bread and Wine into our hands; but by the bleſſing and promiſe of Chriſt, we by that Bread and Wine, as really and truly become partakers of Chriſt's Body and Blood, as the Son by the Will of his Father, was made Inheriter of his Eſtate. Nor is it more neceſſary for this, that Chriſt's Body ſhould come down from Heaven, or the outward Elements which we receive, be ſubſtantially turned into it, than it is neceſſary in that other caſe, that the very Houſes and Lands ſhould
<pb n="169" facs="tcp:152497:88"/>be given into the hands of the Son, to make a real Delivery or Conveyance to them; or the Will of the Father be truly and properly Changed into the very Nature and Subſtance of him.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Soul.</head>
               <p>THat which the <hi>Soul</hi> is in the Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, that are Chriſtians in the World; for as the Soul is in, and not of the Body; ſo Chriſtians are in, but no part of the World. <hi>Juſtin Martyr.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>He that feaſts his Body but ſtarves his Soul, is like him that feaſts his Slaves, but ſtarves his Wife. <hi>Ephra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>him Cirus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As the <hi>Soul</hi> is the Life of the Body, ſo the Life of the Soul is God: When the Soul departs, the Body dies; when God departs, the Soul dies. <hi>Proſper.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The reaſonable Soul made in the likeneſs of God, may here find much Diſtraction, or no full Satisfaction; for it being capable of Good, can be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied
<pb n="170" facs="tcp:152497:89"/>with nothing but God. <hi>Auſtin.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The Soul of Man</hi> (ſays St. <hi>Auſtin</hi>) <hi>is a Spiritual or Incorporeal Subſtance; Senſible, Inviſible, Reaſonable, Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortal.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Sinful Abſurdities.</head>
               <p>Saint <hi>Cyprian</hi> obſerves Twelve Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurdities in the Life of Man.</p>
               <p n="1">1. A Wiſe Man without good Works.</p>
               <p n="2">2. An Old Man without Religion.</p>
               <p n="3">3. A Young Man without Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience.</p>
               <p n="4">4. A Rich Man without Alms.</p>
               <p n="5">5. A Woman without Shamfaced<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</p>
               <p n="6">6. A Guide without Virtue.</p>
               <p n="7">7. A Poor Man that is Proud.</p>
               <p n="8">8. A King that is Unjuſt.</p>
               <p n="9">9. A Biſhop that is Unjuſt.</p>
               <p n="10">10. A Biſhop that is Negligent.</p>
               <pb n="171" facs="tcp:152497:89"/>
               <p n="11">11. People without Diſcipline.</p>
               <p n="12">12. Subjects without Law.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Sin.</head>
               <p>GOD Condemns none before he <hi>Sins,</hi> nor Crowns any before he over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes. <hi>P. Lumbard.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It is beſt not to <hi>Sin,</hi> and next that, amend upon the Puniſhment. <hi>Juſtin Martyr.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Our <hi>Sins</hi> being Sins againſt the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite Majeſty of God, none but our Saviour, who alſo is an Infinite Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty, both God and Man, can make Satisfaction for them. <hi>Biſhop of He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reford's Legacy.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>When Sinners have no ſence of their Spiritual Condition, it is plain they are dead in Sin; the Tokens of Eternal Death are upon them. <hi>Mead.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In <hi>Deut.</hi> 5.25, 28, 29. <hi>They promiſe to fear God, and keep his Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments;</hi> but they wanted a new Heart,
<pb n="172" facs="tcp:152497:90"/>to perform what an unſanctified Heart had promiſed.</p>
               <p>There is a ſtrife againſt <hi>Sin</hi> in one and the ſame Faculty: The Will a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Will, Affection againſt Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection. And this is that the Apoſtle calls, <hi>The luſting of the Fleſh againſt the Spirit:</hi> That is, the ſtriving of one Unregenerate part againſt the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generate part; and this ever in the ſame Faculty: But ſtriving againſt Sin may be in ſeveral Faculties; as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the Will and Conſcience, as for fear of Hell; which Wicked Men may have, <hi>Acts</hi> 7.15.</p>
               <p>It is impoſſible for a Man to forſake Sin, except he forſakes all that he knows to be Sin: To hate Sin, as it is an offence to <hi>God,</hi> and wrong to his Majeſty; to hate Sin as it is a breach of his Commandments: a wicked controuling of God's Will, which is the only Rule of Goodneſs; To hate Sin as being a diſingenuous Tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of that Law of Love, eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="173" facs="tcp:152497:90"/>in the Blood and Death of Chriſt, and ſo in a degree a Crucifying of Chriſt afreſh; to hate Sin as being a grieving and quenching of the Spirit of God, as all Sin in its nature is. Thus to hate Sin is Grace; and thus every true Chriſtian hates Sin, and not for the Shame that attends it, nor as it is contrary to ſome other Sin, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I do not ceaſe to lament the more hainous Sins of my Life, and cannot forbear continually to implore the Pardon of them: I do not again re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn unto them, and reſolve never ſo to do; I watch and pray againſt all <hi>Sin,</hi> but eſpecially againſt thoſe <hi>Sins</hi> to which I eſpecially am enclined; my Conflicts are daily, and I am hard put to it, but I do not yield up my ſelf to any <hi>Sin,</hi> nor lie down in it: Yea, I do not ſuffer <hi>Sinful</hi> Thoughts or Cogitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to lodg in me; howbeit, I am much diſcompoſed and damped in Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, deadned in Duty, diſtracted in
<pb n="174" facs="tcp:152497:91"/>my Studies, and moleſted and hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered every way by Sin that dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth in me: But I reſolve that Sin ſhall never have reſt in my Soul; and that I will never enjoy it. I cannot keep Sin out of my Heart, yet it doth not raign in my Mortal Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy; nor do I yield my Members to the Service of it. <hi>Mr.</hi> Corbet<hi>'s En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiry.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It is a leſs Evil to do Sin, and not to love it, than to love Sin, and not to do it; for to do Sin may argue weakneſs of Grace, but to love Sin argues ſtrength of Luſt. What I hate, that I do, <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.14.</p>
               <p>A Man may forſake the Life of Sin, and yet retain the Love of Sin. True Mourning for Sin, is more for the Evil that is in Sin, than the Evil that comes by Sin; more becauſe it diſhonoureth <hi>God</hi> and Wounds <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and grieves the Spirit, and makes the Soul unlike <hi>God,</hi> than becauſe it Damns the Soul, <hi>Mat.</hi> 7.11.</p>
               <pb n="175" facs="tcp:152497:91"/>
               <p>O Lord, when I confeſs Sin unto thee, grant that I may feel the bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then and weight of it upon my Conſcience, that it may not be a cuſtomary Confeſſion. Where Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion is right, it will be diſtinct, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially of thoſe which were our chief Sins. Confeſſion ſhould come like Water out of a Spring, which runs freely; not like Water out of a Still, which is forced by Fire.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Salvation by <hi>CHRIST</hi>'s Blood.</head>
               <p>TAke it for granted, there is no Man under <hi>Heaven,</hi> whereby we can be ſaved, but <hi>Jeſus Chriſt;</hi> all Grace for this Life, and for that which is to come, muſt come to you, through the Channel of <hi>Chriſt</hi>'s Blood. <hi>Acts</hi> 16.30, 31.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="176" facs="tcp:152497:92"/>
               <head>Sorrow.</head>
               <p>I Could have born any <hi>Sorrow</hi> ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than this I am under; this is a good ſign, <hi>GOD</hi> hath let me Blood in the right Vein, he will have me part with all manner of Sin without exception.</p>
               <p>It is doubtleſs our Sin to diſable our ſelves by our <hi>Sorrow,</hi> for our ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral or particular Callings.</p>
               <p>Let us be heartily <hi>Sorrowful,</hi> that we have ſo Carnally, ſo Hypocritical<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, ſo Covetouſly, ſo Vain-gloriouſly Profeſſed the Goſpel. Let the Plagues and Anger of <hi>GOD,</hi> moſt juſtly fallen upon us, be applyed to our Sins; that, from the bottom of our Hearts, every one of us may ſay, It is I Lord that have Sinned againſt Thee: It is my Wickedneſs that cauſeth ſucceſs, and encreaſe of Authority to my Enemies. <hi>M. Bradford.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="193" facs="tcp:152497:92"/>
               <head>Speech.</head>
               <p>THERE is no Man that talks, but I may gain by him; and none that holds his Tongue, but I may loſe by him.</p>
               <p>As <hi>Henry Wotton,</hi> being bound for <hi>Rome,</hi> asked his Hoſt in <hi>Vienna,</hi> a Man well verſed in Men and Buſineſs, What Rules he would give him for his Port, Conduct and Carriage? He anſwered, There is one ſhort Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance, which will carry you Safe throughout the whole World, and that is nothing but this, <hi>Keep your Thoughts cloſe, and your Countenance looſe.</hi> He that knoweth to ſpeak well, knoweth alſo where he muſt hold his Peace: Said that Old <hi>Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cian, Think an Hour before thou ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keſt, and a Day before thou Promiſeſt.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="194" facs="tcp:152497:93"/>
               <head>Spirit.</head>
               <p>SPirit in the un-erring Senſe, is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but Reaſon illuminated by Revelation out of the Written Word; for when the Mind and Spirit hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly conform and ſubmit to the Writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten Will of God, then are you ſaid to have the Spirit of God, and to walk according to the Spirit, and not according to the Fleſh. Mr. <hi>Hales</hi> of <hi>Eaton</hi> College.</p>
               <p>There is an Having of the Spirit, which is a ſure Work of Saintſhip: Where the Spirit is an effectual pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailing Principle of Grace and San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctification, renewing and regenera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the Heart: Where the Spirit is as a potent Worker, helping the Souls Infirmities, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.26. Where the Spirit is ſaid to abide for ever. <hi>John</hi> 14.16.</p>
               <pb n="195" facs="tcp:152497:93"/>
               <p>The true Believer hath ſo much of the Spirit, ſuch a work of it in him, that he cannot ſin that Sin unto Death; <hi>He that is born of God, ſinneth not;</hi> to wit, that Sin unto Death; for that is meant. 1 <hi>John,</hi> 7.16, 1.</p>
               <p>Mr. <hi>Smith,</hi> in a Sermon ſaid to this purpoſe: <hi>If God be our Father in Chriſt, he lays hold of us by his Spirit, and we lay hold of Him by Faith.</hi> Now it is his Hold-faſt of us that ſaves us; ſo that tho our Faith be as it were a ſleep, yet the Fathers Hold-faſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinues firm.</p>
               <p>Many when they hear that Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Comforts are the Gifts of the Holy Spirit, preſently conceive them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to be meerly Paſſive therein; and that they have nothing to do, but wait when God will beſtow them: Notwithſtanding, tho theſe Comforts are Spiritual, yet they are rationally raiſed up on the Underſtanding's Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſion of the Excellency of God,
<pb n="196" facs="tcp:152497:94"/>our Happineſs, and our Intereſt in Him; and by the rolling of theſe bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Objects, in our frequent Medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, the Spirit doth advance, and not deſtroy our Reaſon; it doth ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifie, and then uſe it as its ordinary Inſtrument, for the Conveyance of ſuch things to our Affections, and Exciting them accordingly, and not lay it aſide, and affect us without it: Therefore our Joys are raiſed diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſively, and the Spirit firſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealeth the Cauſe of our Joy, and then helps us to rejoice upon thoſe revealed Grounds; ſo that he rejoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth groundedly, who knoweth why he rejoiceth ordinarily. Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi>'s <hi>Reſt,</hi> 3d. part. p. 159, 160.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Sufferings.</head>
               <p>I May be Poor, but ſtill I may be Juſt and Contented; I may be Evil ſpoken of, but ſtill I can do Well; I may be Sick, but ſtill I may be Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient;
<pb n="197" facs="tcp:152497:94"/>I may be in Priſon, but there I may Pray, and Sing Pſalms, as <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Silas</hi> did; That which can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not hinder our Duty, ſhould not be ſo ſadly lamented, <hi>Baxt. Hearts Eaſe.</hi> The World perhaps does not love us; have we no reaſon to thank it, if it make us place our Contentment and Comfort in God, and a pure Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience? <hi>Ibid.</hi> 17.</p>
               <p>It is our grand Fault, that we are affected preſently, according as eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry thing appears in the Face, and we ſtay not till it turn the other ſide.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>I ſaw not my Children when they were in the Womb, yet there the Lord fed them without my knowledge; I ſhall not ſee them when I go out of the Body, yet they ſhall not want a Father. Mr.</hi> Cooper.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Auſtin</hi>'s uſual Wiſh was, <hi>That Chriſt, when he came, might find him either Praying or Preaching.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>When the <hi>Donatiſts</hi> upbraided him unworthily with Impurity, and
<pb n="198" facs="tcp:152497:95"/>Impiety of his former Life: <hi>Look,</hi> ſays he, <hi>how much they blame my for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer faults; by ſo much more I commend and praiſe my</hi> Phyſitian.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Beliſarius</hi> having been the Thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derbolt of War, &amp; made the Eaſt, Weſt, and South to tremble, the mighty Power of the Earth crawling in the Duſt before him; he that drew the whole World in throngs after him, was forſaken, and walked through the Streets of <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> with two or three Servants, as a man that had out-lived his Funerals, to ſerve as a Spectacle of pity; and having his Eyes put out by the Emperour <hi>Juſtinians</hi> Widdow, ſhe being a <hi>Neſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian,</hi> went up and down the Streets of <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> begging, <hi>Date quaeſo obelum</hi> Beliſario.</p>
               <p>This ſad Example, and others of the uncertainties of humane Affairs, and the neceſſity of yielding to Religious Thoughts, made <hi>Carolus Magnus,</hi> at the Crowning of his Son,
<pb n="199" facs="tcp:152497:95"/>utter theſe ſerious words: <hi>My dear Son, It is to day that I die in the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pires of the World, and that Heaven makes me born again in your Perſon; If you will Rule happily, fear God, who is the Force of Empires, and So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraign Father of all Dominions; Keep his Commandments, and cauſe them to be obeyed and obſerved with unviolable Fidelity: Serve Him firſt of all, for an Example of the World, and lead an holy Life before God and Man Irreprovable.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A young Gallant, that viſited Saint <hi>Ambroſe</hi> lying on his Death Bed, ſaid to his Comrade then with him: <hi>O that I might live with thee, and Die with</hi> St. Ambroſe.</p>
               <p>Danger is better then Safety, a Storm more eligible than a perpetu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Calm, if before our fears we were the Worlds, but after them became God's. <hi>Nazianzen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="200" facs="tcp:152497:96"/>
               <head>Sickneſs.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>J<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nius</hi> being Sick, one asked him, How he did? ſaid, <hi>That he had quiet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed himſelf in God, who would do for him that which was moſt for his Glory, and his own good.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Serving of God.</head>
               <p>WHen Mr. <hi>Calvin</hi> was Baniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, he ſaid; <hi>Truly, if I had ſerved Men, I ſhould have had but an ill Reward; but it's well, I have ſerved God, who doth always perform to his Servants that which he hath once promiſed.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>See the Difference betwixt Him, and Cardinal <hi>Wolſey;</hi> who ſaid, <hi>Had I been as diligent to ſerve my God, as I have been to pleaſe my King, he would not have ſorſaken me now in my Gray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hairs.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="201" facs="tcp:152497:96"/>
               <p>One of the Kings of <hi>Sweeden</hi> thought, ſaid, <q>That he ſhould not live long, becauſe the people did over-value him for his many Victories:</q> Who was ſlain a little after in Battle, but with a great Victory.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Superstition.</head>
               <p>THe School-men have framed a Number of intricate, and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tile Actions and Theorems, to ſerve the Practice of their Superſtitious Church. Lord <hi>Bacon.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Suſpition.</head>
               <p>THere is nothing makes a Man more to ſuſpect, than to know little; and therefore men would remedy that, by procuring to know more, and not to keep their Suſpicion in ſmother. <hi>Bacon's Eſſays.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="202" facs="tcp:152497:97"/>
               <head>Secrecy.</head>
               <p>SIr <hi>John Cooke</hi> broke an Affair to a <hi>Partiſan,</hi> that kept him under all his days; and he that entertains a dangerous deſign, puts his Head into an Halter, and the Halter into his Hand, to whom he firſt imparts it.</p>
               <p>The Habit of <hi>Secrecy</hi> is Policy and Virtue.</p>
               <p>Speak no more than thou canſt ſafely retreat from without danger, or fairly go through without oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Thoughts.</head>
               <p>WHen a ſenſual Thought breaks in, then excite and taſte the Powers of the World to come, and labour to recover the Divine Frame.</p>
               <pb n="203" facs="tcp:152497:97"/>
               <p>Abhor every Thought, Word, or Deed, which is contrary, and tends to the hurt of others.</p>
               <p>Evil Thoughts are Natures Kiſſes.</p>
               <p>Thoughts being neither free from God's Knowledge, Judgments, Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhments, Laws, nor from Chriſt's Government, nor from the power of Conſcience; ſurely Thoughts are not then free to think what we pleaſe. <hi>Reynard.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thoughts are roving and reſtleſs, till they come to their Center or pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per place; as a ſtone to the Earth, ſo are our Thoughts, till we pitch them upon God, and acquieſce in Him; and they will be unquiet, till they reſt in God, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.7.</p>
               <p>So before a Prayer againſt Evil Thoughts. <hi>De Kempis</hi> 201.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Temptations.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Chryſtome</hi> ſaith, <hi>The Devils aſſault us violently; reſiſt the firſt, and the
<pb n="204" facs="tcp:152497:98"/>cond will be weaker; and That being reſiſted, he becomes a Coward.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Devil runs with open Mouth upon God's Children, to devour them; if they manfully reſiſt him, he thinks to weaken their Faith, and they by his Aſſaults are made ſtronger; he fights againſt them, but they get Ground upon him; and ſo what he intends for their Deſtruction, (full ſore againſt his Will) makes for their Advantage. <hi>Cyril</hi> of <hi>Alexandria.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Time.</head>
               <p>SAys <hi>Aquinas,</hi> 
                  <q>Make much of Time, eſpecially in that matter of Salvation: Oh! how much would they that now lies Frying in Hell rejoyce, if they might have the leaſt moment of Time, whereby they might get God's favour.</q>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="205" facs="tcp:152497:98"/>
               <head>Troubles and Afflictions.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>VIctorinus</hi> was wont to ſay, <q>There is a time to ſay nothing, there is a time to ſay ſomething; but there is never a time to ſay all things.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>I have not Reigned to Day,</hi> ſaid the Emperor, when he had done no good; <hi>To day I have not lived,</hi> ſaid Judge <hi>Fineux;</hi> and that we ſhould not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain we have little time; but that we ſpend much in doing evil, or in doing nothing to purpoſe.</p>
               <p>Secretary <hi>Walſingham</hi> would ſay, My Lord, ſtay a while, and we ſhall have done the ſooner. Secretary <hi>Cecil</hi> ſaid, It ſhall never be ſaid of me, that I do defer till to morrow, what I can do to day: And Sir <hi>Richard Morri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi> uſed to ſay, Give me this day, and the next take your ſelf.</p>
               <p>The Martyr, Mr. <hi>Bradford,</hi> account<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed that hour ill ſpent, wherein he
<pb n="206" facs="tcp:152497:99"/>did not not ſome good either with his Pen, Study, or Exhortation of others.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Truſt.</head>
               <p>AT what time I am afraid, I will put my Truſt in thee; let us be confident he will diſpoſe of us there, where it is moſt neceſſary for us to be either in this World, or the other. Mr. <hi>Patrick.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I truſt God with my chiefeſt out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Concernments, even that which I am moſt Solicitous in; and therein to be ſatisfied is of great Moment un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to me; for that it hath as great an Influence on my Spirit, as any in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward thing hath; and I believe God will provide for me herein, or other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe ſupply the want of it: My earneſt requeſt therefore to God is, That my outward Condition may be ſo ſtated, by his wiſe and gracious Providence, as may be leaſt expoſed
<pb n="207" facs="tcp:152497:99"/>to Temptations, and beſt diſpoſed and furthered as to Duty. Mr. <hi>Corbet.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Truth.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>DIoniſius Areopagitus,</hi> ſaid, <hi>That he deſired Two Things of God,</hi> 1ſt. <hi>That he might know the Truth him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf.</hi> 2d. <hi>That he might Preach it as he ought to others.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Help me, O Lord, that I may exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine my Self in the Evening, how I have born the Troubles and Croſſes of the Day? Did I not Murmur, Vex and Sink? Did I not Entertain hard Thoughts, nor utter hard Words againſt God?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>One being deſigned an Agent, waited on the knowing Lord <hi>Went<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worth,</hi> for ſome Directions for his Conduct and Carriage; who delivered himſelf thus, To ſecure your ſelf, and ſerve your Country, you muſt at all Times, and upon all Occaſions,
<pb n="204" facs="tcp:152497:100"/>ſpeak Truth; and by this means Truth will ſecure your ſelf, if you be que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtioned; and thoſe you deal with (who will ſtill run counter) to a loſs in all your Diſquiſitions, and Undertakings.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Theodoſius Junior</hi> ſaid, <hi>That Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perors of all other Men were moſt Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable, becauſe commonly the Truth of Buſineſs was concealed from them.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ntowardlineſs.</head>
               <p>SIR <hi>Edward Fox,</hi> in his Firſt years, none more untowardly; in his laſt, none more ſtaid. The untoward Youth makeſt the ableſt Man; he that hath Mettle to be Extravagant, when he cannot govern himſelf, hath a Spirit to be eminent when he can.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="207" facs="tcp:152497:100"/>
               <head>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurpation.</head>
               <p>THE Earl of <hi>Strafford</hi> uſed this Maxime, <q>That there is no dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger ſmall, but what is thought ſo: This was his great Principle, Uſurp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Royalty was never laid down by Perſwaſion from Royal Clemency for with Tirants, <bibl>
                        <hi>Omne, Jus Regni.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                  </q>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Vain-Glory.</head>
               <p>I Have an Inclination to ſeek Self particularly in vain Applauſe, and that in Religious Services; and here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in I have been highly Guilty; but I ſhame my Self for it before God, and am willing to be ſatisfied with the Praiſe that comes from Him alone. I truſt through his Grace, that I my ſelf in matter of Reputation ſeek to do his Will. <hi>Corbet</hi>'s Enquiry.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="208" facs="tcp:152497:101"/>
               <head>Victory.</head>
               <p>THere is a compleat Victory, and an incompleat, over the World, 1 <hi>John</hi> 1.3. <hi>If we ſay, we have no Sin, we deceive our Selves, and the Truth is not in us;</hi> The compleat Victory our Saviour only performed, <hi>John</hi> 14.30. <hi>The Prince of this World hath nothing in me;</hi> which cannot be ſo with us, <hi>until our Change come;</hi> for until then we carry about with us Luſts, Paſſions and Corruptions; which without Vigilancy kept under, and daily impaired in their Power and Malignity, will hold Coreſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dency with the Prince thereof, and be ready to betray and deceive us, tho never to regain their Empire and So veraignty; and the Reaſon is ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficantly given by the Apoſtle, 1 <hi>John</hi> 3.9. <hi>For his Seed abideth in him, and he cannot Sin, becauſe he is born of God:</hi> Indeed he may, and ſhall have Sin,
<pb n="209" facs="tcp:152497:101"/>as he hath Fleſh about him, 1 <hi>John</hi> 1.3. <hi>If we ſay, we have no Sin, we de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive our ſelves, and the Truth is not in us;</hi> for tho we have Sin ſtill abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding in us, and like the Byas of a Bowl warping us to the World; yet that Vital Seminal Principle of the Grace of God in Chriſt, always keeps its Ground, its Life, its Tendency towards Heaven, and wears out, and gradually ſubdues the contrary Ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dency of Sin and Corruption. <hi>Hales</hi> 101.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Vertues.</head>
               <p>TO ſet out Vertues, and by Words to deſtroy the ſame, are nothing worth: All the Vertues are ſo linked together, that he that hath one, hath all; and he that wants one, wants all.</p>
               <p>Vertues ſeparated are annihillated. <hi>Chryſologus.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="210" facs="tcp:152497:102"/>
               <head>Heavenly Sayings.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>SEneca,</hi> a man of great Parts, Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence and Experience, after a ſerious Study of almoſt all the Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophy then in the World, was al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt a Chriſtian in his ſevere Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proofs of Vice, and Excellent Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſes of Vertue; (and <hi>Jerom</hi> rec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>koning him for his ſuppoſed Epiſtle to St. <hi>Paul,</hi> and St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s to him;) be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing read by them that ſtudy (ſaith Mr. <hi>Gattater</hi>) Divinity, as they that ſtudy other Learning; came to that Excellent Temper by the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration of his reduced years (which is to be ſeen in his Excellent Preface to his Natural Queſtions;) <q>What a pitiful Thing is Man, were it not that his Soul ſoared above theſe Earthly Things?</q> yea, and was ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what dubious, as to the future Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of the Soul: Yet he could tell his dear Friend <hi>Lucilius,</hi> 
                  <q>With what
<pb n="211" facs="tcp:152497:102"/>Pleaſure he could think of it;</q> and at laſt, he was ſettled in his Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of an everlaſting State; with thought, That the Soul had the mark of Divinity in it, That it was moſt pleaſed with Divine Speculations, and converſed with them, as matter that did not merely concern it; and when it had once viewed the Dimen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions of the Heavens, it was aſham'd of the Cottage it dwelt in: Nay, were it not for theſe Contemplations, it had not been worth the while for the Soul to have been in the Body, (as he goes on.) Whence come ſuch amazing Fears, ſuch dreadful Appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſions, ſuch ſtartling Thoughts of their Future Condition in Mind, that would fain eaſe themſelves, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving that Death would put an end or period to Soul and Body? When, on the other ſide, come ſuch encouraging Hopes, ſuch confident Expectations, comfortable Prepoſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions of their future State, in the
<pb n="212" facs="tcp:152497:103"/>Souls of Men, when their Bodies are neareſt the Grave? and whilſt the Soul is kept in its Cage, it is coutinually fluttering up and down, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lights to look out now at this part, and then at the other, to take a view by Degrees of the whole Univerſe. To theſe Notions of the future State, it was, that <hi>Caeſar</hi> owed that Opinion of Death, That it was better to die once, than to loſe his Life in conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nual Expectations of Death; being troubled with that Unhappineſs of Men, mentioned in <hi>Atheneus,</hi> That he had done his Work, as if it had been his Play; and his Play, as if it had been his Work.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Daniel Henſive,</hi> Hiſtoriographer at <hi>Leyden,</hi> Secretary and Bibliotheatory of that Famous Univerſity, appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Notary of the Synod at <hi>Dort,</hi> ſaid at laſt; Ah, as to Humane Learning, I may uſe <hi>Solomon</hi>'s Expreſſion, <hi>That which is crooked, cannot be made ſtreight.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="213" facs="tcp:152497:103"/>
               <p>Methinks, ſaith the ſame <hi>Henſive,</hi> (and Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> out of him:) I can bid the World farewel, Immure my ſelf among my Books, and look forth no more, (were it a Lawful Courſe) but ſhut the Door upon me, as in the lapſe of Eternity; and among thoſe Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Sages, employ my ſelf with Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent, and pitty the Rich and Great Ones, that know not this Happineſs. Surely, then, it is true Delight in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, which in the true Lap of Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity is enjoyed.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Francis Junius,</hi> a <hi>Gentile,</hi> and Inge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nious Perſon, who hath written his own Life; as he was reading <hi>Tully de Legibus,</hi> fell into a Perſwaſion, <hi>Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hil curare Deum, nec ſui, nec alieni;</hi> till in a Tumult at <hi>Lyons,</hi> the Lord wonderfully delivered him from emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent Death; ſo that he was compel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led to acknowledg a Divine Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence therein; his Father ſeeing the dangerous ways his Son was led into, ſent for him home; where he carefully
<pb n="214" facs="tcp:152497:104"/>and holily inſtructed him, and cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed him to read over the New-Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, of which he himſelf writeth thus: When I read over the New-Teſtament, I firſt lighted on the Firſt Chapter of St. <hi>John, In the beginning was the Word,</hi> &amp;c. I read part of the Chapter, and was ſuddenly convin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, that the Divinity of the Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and the Majeſty and Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the Writing, did exceedingly excel all the Eloquence of Humane Writings; My Body trembled, my Mind was aſtoniſhed, and ſo affected all the Day, that I knew not where, or what I was: Be thou mindful of me, O my God, according to the Multitude of thy tender Mercies; call home thy loſt Sheep, into thy Fold: And as <hi>Juſtin Martyr</hi> of Old, ſo he of late profeſſed, that the Power of Godlineſs, in a plain ſimple Chriſtian, wrought ſo upon him that he could not but take up a ſtrict and ſerious Life.</p>
               <pb n="215" facs="tcp:152497:104"/>
               <p>Mr. <hi>Howard.</hi> afterwards the learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Earl of <hi>Northampton,</hi> being trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled with Atheſtical ſuggeſtions, put them all off this way; <hi>viz. If I could give any account how my ſelf, or any thing elſe, had a Being without God; how came there ſo uniform, and conſtant a Conſent of mankind, in all Ages, Tempers, and Educations (otherwiſe differing in their apprehenſions) about the Being of God, the Immortality of the Soul and Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, in which they could not likely come ſo many; or being ſo many, could not be deceived, I could be an Atheiſt:</hi> And when he was urged, that Religion was a State-policy, only to keep men in awe; he replyed, <hi>That he would believe it, but that the greateſt Politici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans have ſooner or later felt the Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of Religion, in the grievous laſhes of their own Conſciences, and dreadfulneſs of their own apprehenſions, about that State wherein they muſt live for ever.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="216" facs="tcp:152497:105"/>
               <p>Sir <hi>John Maſon,</hi> having been im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed much in State-Affairs, ſaid; <hi>I have learned this, after ſo many expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riences, that Seriouſneſs is the greateſt Wiſdom, Temperance the beſt Phyſitian, and a good Conſcience the beſt Eſtate; and if I were to live again, I would leave the Court for a Cloyſter, my Privy Councellors Buſtles, for a retired Life; and the whole Life I lived in the Palace, for one Hour Enjoyment of God in the Chappel; all things forſake me, beſides my God, my Prayer, and my Duty.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Sir <hi>Henry Wotton,</hi> after ſo many years Study, with proficiency and applauſe of the Univerſity; his being a Favorite of <hi>Robert</hi> Earl of <hi>Eſſex;</hi> his intimacy with the Duke of <hi>Tuſcany,</hi> and <hi>James</hi> the 6th. of <hi>Scotand;</hi> his Embaſſies into <hi>Holland, Germany,</hi> yet deſired to retire with this Motto, <hi>Tandem didicit animas ſapientiores fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eri quieſcendo.</hi> He was very Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitious of the Provoſt-ſhip of <hi>Ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton,</hi> that there he might enjoy his
<pb n="217" facs="tcp:152497:105"/>beloved Study, and Devotion; ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>That that day he put on his Gown, was the happieſt day of his Life; that being the utmoſt happineſs a man could attain to</hi> (he ſaid) <hi>to be at leaſure, and to do good;</hi> never reflecting on his former years, but, with Tears in his Eyes, he would ſay, <hi>How much Time have I to repent of, and how little to do it in?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Charles</hi> the <hi>Fifth,</hi> Emperor of <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>many,</hi> King of <hi>Spain,</hi> and Lord of the <hi>Netherlands;</hi> after 23 Pitch-fields, 6 Triumphs, 4 Kingdoms won, and 8 Principalities added to his Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions, and 14 Wars finiſhed, he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned his Empires and Kingdoms; retiring to his Devotions in a Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſtery, and had his own Funeral Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lebrated before his Face, leaving this Teſtimony of the Chriſtian Religion; That the ſincere Profeſſion of it had in it Sweets and Joys, that Courts were ſtrangers to.</p>
               <pb n="218" facs="tcp:152497:106"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Salmaſius,</hi> that excellent <hi>French</hi> Scholar, whom the Learned men of his Time never mention, without ſuch Expreſſions as theſe; <hi>Vir nunquam ſatis laudatus;</hi> went out of this World, with theſe words in his Mouth: <hi>Oh! I have loſt a World of Time, that moſt precious thing in the World; whereof, had I but one year more, it ſhould be ſpent in</hi> David's <hi>Pſalms, and</hi> Paul's <hi>Epiſtles. Oh! Sirs,</hi> (ſaid he to thoſe about him) <hi>Mind the World leſs, and God more; all the Learning in the World, without Piety, and the true Fear of God, is nothing worth; The Fear of the Lord, that's wholſome, and to depart from Evil; that's underſtanding.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Robert Rollock</hi> ſaid at the time of his Death: <hi>Haſte, Lord, and do not tarry; I am a weary both of Nights and Days: Lord Jeſus that I may come to Thee, break theſe Eye-ſtrings, and give me others: I deſire to be diſſolved, and to be with Thee: Haſte, Lord Jeſus, and defer no longer: Go forth my weak
<pb n="219" facs="tcp:152497:106"/>Life, and let a better ſucceed. Oh my Lord Jeſus Chriſt, thruſt Thy Hand into my Body, and take my Soul to Thy Self. O Lord Jeſus, ſet my Soul free, that ſhe may enjoy her Husband.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Earl of <hi>Strafford</hi> ſaid; <hi>Oh truſt not in man that ſhall Die, nor to the Son of Man, as ſhall be made as Graſs; there is no Confidence in Princes; the only things that ſtands by a man, are the Blood of Chriſt, and the Teſtimony of a good Conſcience.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>An Excellent Perſon having writ exquiſitly for the Chriſtian Religion, hath this Diſcourſe of the Nature of it; <hi>viz. Doth now the Conqueſt of Paſſions, forgetting of Injuries, doing Good, Self-denial, Patience under croſſes, which are the expreſſions of Piety, abound to the ſupport of a Luxuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, Malitious, and Impatient Spirit? Is there nothing more becoming Malitious, Proud, and Impatient Soul of Man, in examplary Piety, and an Holy and well ordered converſation, than in the
<pb n="220" facs="tcp:152497:107"/>Lightneſs and Vanity; not to ſay, in Rudeneſs, and Debauchery in them, which the World accounts the greateſt Gallants? Is there nothing more grace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful and pleaſing in the Sweetneſs and Ingenuity of a truly Chriſtian-temper, and diſpoſition, than in the revengeful Spirit of ſuch, whoſe Honour lives, and is fed by the Blood of their Enemies? Is it not more truly Honourable and Glorious to ſerve that God, that Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandeth and Ruleth the World; than to be a Slave to thoſe Paſſions and Luſts, that put men upon continual hard Service, and torment them for it, when they have done it? Is there no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elſe to Commend Religion to the Minds of men, beſides that Tranquility and Calmneſs of Spirit, that Serene and placable temper, which follows a good Conſcience, where ſoever it dwells? it were enough to make Men to welcom that Gueſt, which brings ſuch good En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertainment which it: wherefore the Horrors, Anxiety, and Amazement of
<pb n="221" facs="tcp:152497:107"/>Mind, which brings at one time or other, which proſtitute their Conſciences to a Violation of the Laws of God, and of the Rules of rectified Reaſon, may be e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to perſwade any Rational Perſon, that Impiety is the greateſt Folly, and Irreligious Madneſs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Sir <hi>Thomas Smith,</hi> after he had ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> as Secretary of State, and done many good Services, to the Kingdom; eſpecially, in ſetling the Corn-Rate for the Univerſities; Diſcharged himſelf of all publick Affairs and Attendants a quarter of a year before he died: Deſiring the Biſhop of <hi>Wincheſter</hi> and <hi>Worce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter,</hi> to draw him out of the Word of God the plaineſt and exacteſt way of making his Peace with God in this preſent World; adds, That it was great pitty, that Men know not to what end they were born into this World, until they were ready to go out of it.</p>
               <pb n="222" facs="tcp:152497:108"/>
               <p>My Lord <hi>Bacon</hi> hath ſaid, at the latter end of his Life, <hi>That a little ſmattering in Philoſophy would lead a Man into Atheiſm; but a thorough In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſight into it, would lead a Man back again unto a firſt Cauſe;</hi> and that the firſt Principle of Right Reaſon, is Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion; in Reference to which, it was the wiſeſt way to live ſtrictly and ſeverely; for if the Opinion of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther would not be one, yet the ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt thing in this World is Piety, Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue and Honeſty. If it be true, none are ſo miſerable as the Looſe, the Carnal, and Profane Perſons, who live a Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honorable and Baſe Life in this World, and are like to Fall into a moſt wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful State in the next.</p>
               <p>The E. of <hi>Arundel,</hi> lying on his Death. Bed, ſaid, <hi>My Fleſh, and my Heart fail me;</hi> and his Chaplain an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered the next Words, <q>That God was the ſtrength of his Heart, and his portion for ever; he would never
<pb n="223" facs="tcp:152497:108"/>fail him. He anſwering, tho all the World hath failed, He will never fail me.</q>
               </p>
               <p>Sir <hi>Tho. Coventry,</hi> Lord Keeper of the Great Seal, hearing ſome Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lants jeſting with Religion, ſaid, <hi>That there was no greater Argument of a Foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh and Inconſiderate Perſon, than to droll at Religion: It is a ſign, he hath no regard of himſelf, and that he is not touched with a Sence of his own Intereſt, who playeth with Life and Death, and makes nothing of his Soul. To examine ſevere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and debate ſeriouſly of Religion, is a thing worthy of a wiſe Man: Whoſoever turns Religion into Railery, with two or three bold Jeſts, rendreth not only Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, but himſelf Ridiculous in the Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of all Wiſe and Conſiderate Men, becauſe he ſports with his own Life:</hi> For a good Man ſaith, <hi>If Principles were doubtful, yet they concern us ſo nearly, that we ought to be ſerious in the Exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of them.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="224" facs="tcp:152497:109"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Carolopator</hi> relateth, how the excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Painter <hi>Methoclius</hi> Drawing the laſt day, the Heavens black, the Earth on Fire, the Sea in Blood, the Throne of God environd with An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels in the Clouds, wrought ſo upon <hi>Bogaris</hi> the barbarous <hi>Prince</hi> of <hi>Bul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garia,</hi> that in a ſhort time he yielded himſelf to God, by an happy Converſion; for he dreaming of the whole proceedings of that day, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt other things, ſaw the things he made ſo light of, by ſpeaking thus: <hi>I am the pleaſure thou haſt obeyed, I am the Ambition whoſe Slave thou waſt: I am the Avarice, which was the aim of all thy Actions: Behold ſo many Sins, that are thy Children; Thou begotteſt them, thou beloveſt them ſo much; as to prefer them before thy Saviour.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Mr. <hi>John Bruen</hi> ſaid, <hi>At his Fune<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral, he would have no Black; for I love not,</hi> ſaid he, <hi>any proud nor pom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pous Funeral; neither is there any cauſe of Mourning, but Rejoycing rather in
<pb n="225" facs="tcp:152497:109"/>my particular.</hi> Immediately before his death, lifting up his Hands, he ſaid; <hi>The Lord is my Help, my Portion, and my Truſt; His Bleſſed Son Jeſus is my Saviour and Redeemer,</hi> Amen. <hi>For ſo ſaith the Spirit to my Spirit: Then come Lord Jeſus, and Kiſs me with Kiſſes of thy Mouth, and embrace me with the Arms of thy Love: Into thy Hands I commit my Spirit; Take me to thy own ſelf. Come Lord Jeſus, come quickly; O come, O come, O come.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Mr. <hi>Brown</hi> of <hi>Norwich,</hi> Phiſitian, entertained one Attribute of God, to recreate his Devotion, and that is <hi>Wiſdome; In which,</hi> ſays he, <hi>I am Happy; for the Contemplation of this on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, I do not Repent me, that I was brought up to Study; the advantage I have over the Vulgar, with the content and happineſs I conceive therein, is an ample Recompence of all my endeavours, in what part of Knowledge whatſoever; Wiſdom is his moſt glorious Attribute, no man can attain unto it; yet</hi> Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon
<pb n="226" facs="tcp:152497:110"/>
                  <hi>pleaſed God, when he deſired it; he is wiſe, becauſe he knoweth all things, and he knoweth all things, becauſe he made them all: Yet his greateſt know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge is, in comprehending, what he made not, Himſelf; and this alſo is the greateſt Knowledge in man; for this I do ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour my Profeſſion, and Embrace the very Council of the Devil himſelf. Had he read ſuch a Lecture in</hi> Paradice, <hi>as he did at</hi> Delphos, <hi>we had better known our ſelves; neither had we need to ſtand in fear of him: I know he is Wiſe in all things; he is Wiſe in all, and Wonderful in what we conceive; but farmore in what we comprehend not; for we behold him but a ſquint up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on reflex or ſhadow: Our <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing is dimmer then</hi> Moſes <hi>his Eye; we are Ignorant of his Back-parts, and his lower-ſide of his Divinity; there to pry into his Councels, is not only Folly in Man, but Preſumption even in Angels; like us, they are his Servants, not his Senators; he holds Councel but with that
<pb n="227" facs="tcp:152497:110"/>myſtical One, the</hi> Trinity, <hi>where tho there be three Perſons, there is but one Mind, that decrees without contradicion; nor needs he any of his Actions to be begot with deliberation; his Wiſdom knows naturally what's beſt; his Intellect ſtands fraught with the ſuperlative and pureſt I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deas of Goodneſs; Conſultation and Electi on, which are two Motions in us, make but one in Him; his Actions ſprung from his Power at the firſt touch of his Will: There are Contemplations metaphyſical; my hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Speculations have another Method, &amp; are content to trace and diſcover thoſe Expreſſions, he hath left in his Creatures, and the obvious effects of Nature: there is danger to confound theſe Myſteries; no</hi> Sanctum Sanctorum <hi>in Philoſophy; the world, to be Inhabited by Beaſts, but Study'd and Contemplated by Men. It is the debt of our Reaſon to Owe unto God the Homage we pay, for not being Beaſts; without this, the World is ſtill as though it had not been, or as it had been before the ſixth day, when as yet there was not
<pb n="228" facs="tcp:152497:111"/>a Creature, that could conceive or ſay, there was a World. The Wiſdom of God receives ſmall Honor from the Vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar Heads, that uſually ſtare about with groſs Ruſticity, &amp; admire his works. Thoſe highly magnifie him, whoſe Judicious Enquiry into his Acts, and deliberate Reſearch into his Creatures, return the duty of a Learned and Devout Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration.</hi>
               </p>
               <lg>
                  <l>Therefore ſearch whilſt thou wilt, and let thy Reaſon go,</l>
                  <l>To ranſom Reaſon even to the Abyſs below;</l>
                  <l>Rally the Scattered cauſes, and that line,</l>
                  <l>Which Nature twiſts, be able to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twine.</l>
                  <l>It is thy Makers Will; for unto none,</l>
                  <l>But unto Reaſon, can he e're be known.</l>
                  <l>The Devil knows thee, but thoſe Damned Metors,</l>
                  <l>Build not thy Glory, but confound the Creatures.</l>
                  <pb n="229" facs="tcp:152497:111"/>
                  <l>Teach my endeavours, ſo thy Work to read,</l>
                  <l>That learning them, in Thee I may proceed.</l>
                  <l>Give thou my Reaſon, that Inſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive flight,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe weary Wings, may on thy Hands ſtill light.</l>
                  <l>Teach me to ſoar aloft, yet ſo,</l>
                  <l>When near the Sun, to ſtop again below.</l>
                  <l>Thus ſhall my humble Feathers ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly hover,</l>
                  <l>And tho' ne'er Earth, more than the Heavens diſcover.</l>
                  <l>And then at laſt, when homeward I ſhall drive,</l>
                  <l>Rich with the Spoils of Nature to my Hive;</l>
                  <l>There will I ſit like that Induſtrious <hi>Flie,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Buzzing thy praiſes, which ſhall ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver Dye.</l>
                  <l>Till Death abridge them of exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Glory,</l>
                  <l>Bid me go on in a more laſting Story.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="230" facs="tcp:152497:112"/>
               <head>Will of God.</head>
               <p>SOME have ſatisfied themſelves with this ſingle Thought, that 'tis in vain to be troubled, ſince things muſt not be as we will, but as the Almighty Being pleaſes. Cold comfort! But God be thanked, we have much better to Comfort us. <hi>viz.</hi> That the World is not governed meerly by God's Will, but by his Wiſdom; he diſpoſeth of all things, according to his good Pleaſure, but it pleaſeth him to diſpoſe of all things to the beſt: He ruleth the World, not only as an abſolute Lord, but as a loving Father.</p>
               <p>It is a poor center of a Man's Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, Himſelf, it is Earth; for that only ſtands faſt upon its own Center; where, all things that have Affinity with the Heavens, move upon the Center of another, which they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit. L. <hi>Bacon.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="231" facs="tcp:152497:112"/>
               <p>Seeming wiſe Men may make ſhift to get Opinion, but let no Man choſe them for Employment; for certainly, you had better take for Buſineſs, a Man ſomewhat abſurd, than over for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mal. <hi>Bacon</hi> 148.</p>
               <p>A Noble Lord, at the time of his Death, told his Son, That he would leave him a Legacy out of <hi>David</hi>'s Pſalms: <hi>Lord, lead me into a plain Path</hi>; for, ſaid he, <hi>I would have you a plain Honeſt Man.</hi> To which I may add that excellent ſaying, of the ſame No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Lord, <hi>The Wiſdom of thoſe young Men is moſt Excellent, who by Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence and Diſcourſe of Reaſon, do ſo Order their Affairs, that they ſtay not till Neceſſity and Experience force them to that Order, which fore-ſight would much ſooner have taken.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="232" facs="tcp:152497:113"/>
               <head>Wrongs.</head>
               <p>WRongs many times make way for better Fortune: If Men ſlight us, and deſpiſe us, and ſpeak evil and unjuſtly againſt us, and take away our good Name; yea, if they take away our Eſtates, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> if we be not angry, nor fill'd with Deſpight, nor retaliate their wrongs, then it is not we, but they that ought to be troubled.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Word.</head>
               <p>HE that Delights in the Word, becauſe it is Spiritual, he is a Chriſtian indeed; the more Spiritual the Ordinances, the more Spiritual they are, the more doth a gracious Soul delight in them; when the word comes cloſe to the Conſcience, rips up the Heart, and diſcovers Sin, and yet delights in it; notwithſtanding
<pb n="233" facs="tcp:152497:113"/>this is a ſign of Grace: Alſo, when Delight ariſes from that Communion, that is to be had with God there, this is from a Principle of Grace, in the Soul. <hi>Mead</hi> 73.</p>
               <p>The Word was made Fleſh, to teach Patience, and to perſwade to Vertue. <hi>Vide</hi> Scripture.</p>
               <p>Mr. <hi>Knox</hi> was tempted by Satan, to think, that he merited for his great Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, until God brought into his mind that of St. <hi>Paul, What haſt thou, that thou haſt not received? Not I, but the Grace of God that is in me. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nleſs,</hi> ſays <hi>Luther, My Adverſaries can convince me by ſound Arguments, taken out of the Word of God, I cannot ſatisfy my Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence; for I can plainly prove, that both Pope and Councel have often erred grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouſly; and therefore it would be an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly thing in me, to aſſent unto them, and to depart from the Holy Word of God, which is plain and cannot err.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="234" facs="tcp:152497:114"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Cromwel,</hi> from K. <hi>Henry</hi> the Eighth, adviſes the Covocation,</p>
               <q>
                  <p>That they conclude all Differences by the Word of God; neither will his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty ſuffer the Scriptures to be wre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted by falſe Gloſſes, Papiſtical Laws, or by any Authority of Doctors or Councels; much leſs, will he ſuffer any Articles not contained in Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, but only founded on a Conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuance of Time and Cuſtom, or by unwritten Verities, as you were wont to do: But the only way to Unity, is to determine Acts and Things, by the Rule of Gods Word, as himſelf requireth.</p>
                  <p>In thy Zeal againſt others, be mindful of thy own exceeding Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs; call to mind thy great Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fences, which when they are unfeig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nedly repented of, give thee to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand what Cauſe thou haſt to be Meek, Humble and Patient towards all Men; for Right Zeal is a Coele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtial Fire, the true temper and heat
<pb n="235" facs="tcp:152497:114"/>of all the Affections to God and Chriſt, <hi>Qui non Zelat, non Amat;</hi> It is a Zeal kindled in the Soul, by the Spirit of God, who firſt knows it, and then ſets it on work: It is a Zeal, that hath the Word of God for its Guide, directing it in its wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kings, both in regard of its Object, and End, in Manner and Meaſure: It is a Zeal that checks Sin, and fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers an Heavenly Life: It is a Zeal, that makes God, and the Glory of God its chief end, and ſwallows up all by-ends: <hi>The Zeal of thine Houſe hath eaten me up.</hi>
                  </p>
               </q>
               <p>The Emperor <hi>Valence</hi> ſent a Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage to St. <hi>Baſil,</hi> promiſing him great Preferment, if he would turn <hi>Neſſorian</hi> but he replied, <hi>i.e.</hi> 
                  <q>Theſe Speeches are fit to catch little Children, that look after ſuch things; but we that are nouriſht by the Holy Scriptures, are readier to die a thouſand Deaths, rather than to ſuffer one Syllable or Tittle of the Scriptures to be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered.</q>
               </p>
               <pb n="236" facs="tcp:152497:115"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Theodoſius</hi> was wont to ſay, <q>That he accounted it a greater Honour, that he was a Member of the Church, than that he was the Head of the Empire.</q>
               </p>
               <p>It is reported, That a Miniſter ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving reproved a Gentleman's Ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, for many Diſorders, yet would not forgo them; for which, he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plained of him to his Landlord, who adviſed him to admoniſh him once more; and that if he did not then a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend, <hi>That he ſhould then ſanctify his Hand, and give him a Box on the Ear.</hi>
               </p>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <l>Full quickly waxeth cold Religious Fame.</l>
                     <l>Unleſs by Zeal, we do uphold the ſame.</l>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               <pb facs="tcp:152497:115"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:152497:116"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:152497:116" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
